<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Poleo-nao-daphne. Londons laurell: or a branch of the graft of gratitude First budded in the temple, and now begun to blossome, upon Davids thankfulnes to the Lord for a cities kindnesse. By Edw. Dalton one of the lecturers in the Cathedrall Church of S. Pauls, London.</title>
            <author>Dalton, Edward.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 244 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A73787</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6204A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S125303</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900567</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900567</idno>
            <idno type="VID">131928</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A73787)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 131928)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2060:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Poleo-nao-daphne. Londons laurell: or a branch of the graft of gratitude First budded in the temple, and now begun to blossome, upon Davids thankfulnes to the Lord for a cities kindnesse. By Edw. Dalton one of the lecturers in the Cathedrall Church of S. Pauls, London.</title>
                  <author>Dalton, Edward.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 200 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Iohn Haviland,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXIII. [1623]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:131928:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:131928:1"/>
            <p>ΠΟΛΕΩΣ-ΝΑΩ-ΔΑΦΝΗ. Londons Laurell: <hi>OR</hi> A BRANCH OF THE GRAFT OF GRATITVDE. Firſt budded in the TEMPLE, and now begun to bloſſome, VPON <hi>DAVIDS THANKF<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LNES</hi> TO THE LORD FOR a Cities kindneſſe. By EDW. DALTON one of the Lecturers in the Cathedrall Church of S. PAVLS, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>D. Chryſoſt. ſuper Matth. homil. 25.</hi>
               </bibl> Optima beneficiorum cuſtos, eſt ipſa memoria beneficiorum, &amp; perpetua confeſſio gratiarum.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Senec. lib. de benef.</hi>
               </bibl> Gratum hominem <hi>ſemper</hi> beneficium delectat, ingratum <hi>ſemel.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by IOHN HAVILAND, M.DC.XXIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:131928:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:131928:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR <hi>PETER PROBY</hi> KNIGHT, Lord MAIOR; the Right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and Worſhipfull, the <hi>Sheriffes, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, Companies,</hi> and <hi>Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens,</hi> of the Honourable Citie of <hi>London, Grace and Glorie.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable, right Worſhipfull, and Worſhipfull:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the caſe ſtands with a man and the parts of his body; ſo it may fall out with a Citie and the members of it; one part is the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall in the Act, and another in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne, which redoundeth from that Act: yet the man himſelfe, as is due, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth away the glory of the deſerued
<pb facs="tcp:131928:3"/>praiſe. The hand by the <hi>Mercurialiſts</hi> Penne, or <hi>Martiall</hi> Pike, ſets a wreath, as the embleme of worthineſſe, vpon the head only; yet blazeth the Fame of the whole man. A worthy Gouernour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, my much reſpected friend, (whoſe name, when euery BRANCH ſhall beare a particular name, another BRANCH, if God permit, ſhall men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) as it is not vnknowne, not onely himſelfe ſhewed me a fauour, but tooke order with his ſucceſſor in his place, that that ſtorme which did threaten my ruine, ſhould not with that violence, which was intended, fall vpon me, if a chearing calme ſhould not come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene, which by Gods prouidence and his meanes came to paſſe. Senſible yet of that fauor and other curteſies which I haue receiued from, and perceiued in diuers of you, in the good intentions of ſome, endeuours of other, wel-wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of many, I haue aduentured to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to your eies part of that which ſometime ſounded in ſome of your
<pb facs="tcp:131928:3"/>eares, as they eſpecially can witneſſe who were the Lords inſtruments to manifeſt his care, in preuenting the violent courſe of ſome who would haue wrongfully enthralled my freedome, and damned vp the ſtreames of my iuſt and legall proceedings, yet ſo as my thankfulneſſe is made knowne vnder the name of your honourable citie, my Text caſting a fauourable countenance that way, and referreth its entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to your kindneſſes. Now goe on (right worthy) as the Lord ſhall miniſter occaſion, and your ſeuerall places call for, in Chriſtian and charitable actions, for ſuch haue carried your cities and predeceſſors fame beyond the Ocean, and aſſuredly God himſelfe will not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get (though thoſe who haue felt the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit ſhould be (which God forbid) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of) your works of either pietie or pittie: &amp; for my ſelfe my tongue and penne ſhall not ceaſe to afford you moe diſhes of fruit, as Teſtimonies of my gratefull heart, if the Lord be pleaſed to
<pb facs="tcp:131928:4"/>proſper my endeuours about the roote of this GRAFT. In the meane ſeaſon I ſhall not ceaſe by my prayers to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to draw from the fountaine of all goodneſſe, all needfull bleſſings for your whole city and all in it, from the higheſt Cedar to the loweſt Shrub, and euer reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours and the Churches denoted Seruant, <hi>EDVV. DALTON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:131928:4"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, SIR IVLIVS CAESAR Knight, Maſter of the Rolles, and Sir EDWARD COKE Knight, both of his Maieſties moſt honourable Priuie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell: Sir HENRY HOBART Knight and Baronet, Lord chiefe Iuſtice of his Maieſties right honourable Court of Common Pleas, and Sir LAVRENCE TANFEILD Knight, Lord chiefe Baron of his Maieſties right honourable Court of Exchequer; and the right worſhipfull his Maieſties Iuſtices and Barons of the ſame COVRTS. AS ALSO To the honourable Societies, the right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and worſhipfull, the Maſter, Benchers, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, Barriſters, Gentlemen Students, and members of either Temple: <hi>Mercy, truth, righteouſneſſe, and peace.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable, Honourable, and truly Worthy,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou (who haue, in an aſpectuall, either <hi>Trine</hi> or <hi>Sextile, radiation,</hi> vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed Your auſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>influences,</hi> and ſome directly, other collaterally, all of you fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourably
<pb facs="tcp:131928:5"/>beheld me; mitigated with your gentler <hi>aſpects</hi> the malice of my oppoſite Planets, in this inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Orbe;</hi> hindered by Your <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolent powers</hi> the <hi>maleuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent motions</hi> of ſome irregular Starres in our earthly <hi>Globe;</hi> and in proceſſe of time, the <hi>reuolution</hi> of heauen ſo bringing it about, as your ſeuerall places and my ſeuerall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings required, met almoſt in the ſame degree, though carried in your diſtant <hi>Spheres,</hi> to the clayming, through your concurrences, of the denomination of a <hi>Coniunction</hi> for my good) may as iuſtly as ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; as ioyntly as iuſtly, both iuſtly and ioyntly, challenge the publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe effects which your worths out of good will produced, and my weakeneſſe in way of gratefulneſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:131928:5"/>was, is, or ſhall be, enabled to make knowne.</p>
            <p>To you therefore doe I dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate this firſt BRANCH OF my GRAFT OF GRA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>DE, which hitherto hath not appeared, lacking the life-giuing Rayes of one or other <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary;</hi> yet now at laſt through a happier <hi>conſtellation,</hi> buds and begins to bloſſome in open view vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your Patronages; whoſe beames of kinde acceptance, if I ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, Sunne-like to reflexe vpon it, I ſhall be animated to gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe Siens which lie diſperſed in my <hi>nurſerie;</hi> to adapt and in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable time to <hi>inoculate</hi> them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one <hi>Stocke;</hi> to <hi>digge</hi> about the <hi>root</hi> of this GRAFT; and ſo to <hi>prune</hi> euery BRANCH
<pb facs="tcp:131928:6"/>of it, that it may anſwer the aime of my now attempt, in yeelding ſome fruit wherewith the <hi>Lords name,</hi> the Author of all grace, may be magnified; <hi>Your names,</hi> who are and haue beene the inſtruments of much good, as with LAW<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RELL were honoured the heads of the well-deſeruing, with condigne fame according to your deſerts, for patterne ſake, an end of my preſent endeuours, diuulged; mine owne thankefulneſſe, who haue bin in ſome ſort the paſsiue ſubiect of aduerſe might, obiect of affected malice, to God and man, the inſtant wiſhing of my ſoule, expreſſed; the meaneſt of the Tribe of Leui (in their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, rights, perſons, diſeſteemed, wronged, contemned, ſo much as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hypocriſie, irreligion, error, or
<pb facs="tcp:131928:6"/>ſuperſtition can preuaile) notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all iniurious diſgraces, and diſgracefull iniuries, in our heauen-reſpected calling, as my heart hopeth, incouraged; and all men leſſe or more, which the Lord now and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way vouchſafe, ſome way bettered. Till when and euer, that your LO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E and FEARE may ſo be fixed vpon the Lords MER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIE and J<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>STICE (the onely bloſſomes which as yet this BRANCH doth beare) and all your affections ſo ordered and ſo diſpoſed by God himſelfe to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that you neuer, either want the ſenſible feeling of ſauing <hi>Grace,</hi> or goe without the full fruition of eternall <hi>Glory,</hi> hee praieth who is till death,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours and the Churches deuoted Seruant,</hi> Edw. Dalton.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="analysis">
            <pb facs="tcp:131928:7"/>
            <p>The Text analy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<list>
                  <item>Analogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally: three parts, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the courts of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. 1 Pet. 1.12.
<list>
                        <item>1. For all, <hi>Hee</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. For the Prieſts, <hi>Shewed.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. For the High Prieſt where were the Heb. 9.3, 4.
<list>
                              <item>1. Arke or mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy-ſeat.
<list>
                                    <item>1. <hi>Kindneſſe.</hi>
                                    </item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>2. Two Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims prying into that Arke
<list>
                                    <item>2. Time when and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom, moue admiration.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>3. Two Tables by which, and to which, all duties to God and man are directed, both ayming at Gods glory.
<list>
                                    <item>3. <hi>His.</hi> In himſelfe abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, yet to man ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and in both reſpects reflexing vpon his owne praiſe.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>4. Manner, not ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, but beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon euent, <hi>Maruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>4. <hi>Aarons</hi> rod by which mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles were wrought.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>5. Place, where this <hi>Kindneſſe</hi> was reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, <hi>in a ſtrong Citie.</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>5. Pot of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>6. The Heart, from which <hi>thanksgiuing,</hi> a ſacrifice ſo accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, iſſued: <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord.</hi>
                                 <list>
                                    <item>6. Cenſor from which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſmell of incenſe ſo ſweetly aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>Logical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the
<list>
                        <item>1. Agent, <hi>He</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 Act, <hi>ſhewed</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, <hi>Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> its
<list>
                              <item>Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. in the Time when, <hi>Hath</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom <hi>Mee.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>Propriety in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by whom <hi>His.</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>Rarity in the Manner how, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellous</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity in the Place where, <hi>In a ſtrong citie.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAg.</hi> 4. <hi>in marg. read</hi> 2 Sam. ch. 17, 18, 19. 1 Sam. 30. 1 Sam. 23. <hi>pag.</hi> 19. <hi>in marg. adde</hi> Amos 6.6. <hi>p.</hi> 35. <hi>l.</hi> 12. <hi>for</hi> but <hi>r.</hi> to be. <hi>p.</hi> 44. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>after</hi> loue, <hi>r.</hi> loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king on the Compaſſe of his mercy. <hi>p.</hi> 46. <hi>l.</hi> 11. <hi>before</hi> For <hi>r.</hi> Freely. <hi>p.</hi> 54. <hi>in M. for</hi> Verſ. <hi>r.</hi> Cha. <hi>p.</hi> 55. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>r.</hi> as God <hi>p. ib. l.</hi> 3. <hi>r.</hi> as our God. <hi>p.</hi> 68. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>r.</hi> former, in that. <hi>p.</hi> 69. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r.</hi> ſpeciall. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>for</hi> word <hi>r.</hi> houſe. <hi>p.</hi> 79. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>r.</hi> teares. <hi>p.</hi> 84. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> publiſhing. <hi>p.</hi> 85. <hi>l. penult. r.</hi> did in.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:131928:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALME 31.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bleſſed be the Lord, for he hath ſhewed mee his maruellous kindneſſe in a ſtrong Citie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Very thing hath its turne and time,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.1.</note> yea time giues to euery thing its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe neuer continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in one ſtay:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.2.</note> the truth whereof no glaſſe can better ſhew than the Pſalmes: for in them wee may liuely behold the variable and mutable condition of man, though neuer ſo neere in affection or deare in eſtimation vnto God: in them <hi>Dauid</hi> that anointed of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:131928:8"/>the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.26.</note> (and in him all Gods choſen) may be ſeene in this life, as the Ship in the Sea; in eſtate and reſpect euen now lifted vp to the clouds ſayling with a pleaſant gale, in the calme of proſperity, and by and by let downe to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome with the impetuous violence of the blaſt of one or other calamitie in ſoule and ſpirit; ſometimes ſoaring with the wings of hope aboue the heauens, and againe plunged as low as hell with the weight of diſtruſt, through ſome diſaſter either inflicted or feared. Whence proceed ſuch and ſo ſundry va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of expreſſing, in diuers of them, his owne hopes and feares, comforts and coraſiues, ſolace and ſorrowes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraints and deliuerances. But in this Pſalme, he ſtands as it were in the view of all vpon the worlds Theater, and ſounds in the eares of all a Diapaſon, whiles warbling vpon his harpe, hee toucheth the ſtring of euery paſſion. For he powreth out his praier with inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, in the firſt and ſecond verſes; gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:131928:8"/>aſſured hope in the third; and yet as one not fully freed from feare, nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſt of hope, returnes againe to prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and giues the reaſon of his aſſurance in the third, fourth, and fift; pleadeth in expreſſe termes, his holy affection and confidence which hee had in the time paſt, in the ſixt; publiſheth his reſolute purpoſe of gladneſſe and reioycing in the time to come, by reaſon of the Lords fauour already ſhewed, as one forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and not fearing any preſent miſery, in the ſeuen and eighth. Yet on the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, calling, as it ſeemes, to minde, the trouble and danger he was then in, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neweth his ſuit, which is preſſed and amplified with relating by way of complaint, ſundry miſeries and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities which he doth endure, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had vndergone, to the fourteenth; in which miſeries and indignities, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports what was and is his truſt and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in the fourteenth and fifteenth; and that againe is ſeconded with another ſupplication, in the fifteenth and ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:131928:9"/>as alſo with an imprecation, in the ſeuenteenth and eighteenth; after both which without interruption, as the Riuer in a cleare channell into the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, he falleth into an admiring excla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, for the greatneſſe of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, towards them that feare, and truſt in him, in the nineteenth; together with a reaſon of that his admiration, in the twentieth; from thence hee comes to giue thanks for a kindneſſe, whereof the Lord had made him partaker in his owne particular, in ſome extraordinary manner, and that <hi>in a ſtrong Citie.</hi> Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ieruſalem which <hi>Abſolom</hi> had ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.19.</note> and where <hi>Achitophels</hi> counſell by <hi>Huſhaies,</hi> to his preſeruation was delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ianſen. Lorinus.</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.</note> as ſome; or <hi>Ziglag,</hi> where the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were in minde to ſtone him, and the ſpoiles whereof he recouered,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arias.</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.</note> as other; or <hi>Keilah</hi> which <hi>Saul</hi> purpoſed to haue beſieged, and to whom the citizens thereof, as the Lords, Oracle reuealed, had deliuered him if there he had ſtaied, as the moſt imagine. Howſoeuer, or in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:131928:9"/>what citie ſoeuer, <hi>Dauid</hi> is mindfull of that mercy, and thankfull for that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, in ſuch termes as iuſtly giues me occaſion to thinke vpon <hi>Salomon</hi> his ſonne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salomon</hi> the mirror of men,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.25.</note> the <hi>belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the Lord,</hi> not liked as a ſeruant,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 8.35.</note> but beloued as a <hi>Sonne that abides in the houſe for euer,</hi> built a glorious Temple to the God of Iſrael, and diuided it into three parts. The firſt or outmoſt was <hi>Atrium Populi,</hi> the court of the people, called o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the Porch of <hi>Salomon;</hi> the next was <hi>Atrium Sacerdotum,</hi> the place for the Prieſts; the third and inmoſt was <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum Sanctorum,</hi> the Holy of Holies. When I ſee theſe words of <hi>Dauid,</hi> I ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey that worke of <hi>Salomon,</hi> and hearing this warbling tune of the Father, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold that worthy Temple of the Sonne. For if we looke for that part which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes all, it is here in the Author, <hi>He,</hi> who maketh his <hi>Sunne to riſe on the euill and the good,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.45.</note> 
               <hi>and ſendeth raine on the iuſt and vniuſt.</hi> Would we ſee what concernes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:131928:10"/>thoſe that are ſequeſtrated to his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and linked to him by a neerer bond, as are all faithfull, who being a <hi>royall Prieſt-hood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</note> enioy a rarer priuiledge than others? here we find it. All haue not the Lords mercy manifeſted to them as had <hi>Dauid;</hi> or if it be made apparant to them, yet are not they made partakers of it, as was this anointed of the Lord. <hi>He ſhewed me,</hi> that is, made me partaker of. Long you to ſee that which <hi>Titus Veſpaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> deſired,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioſeph. de bel. Iud. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> nay commanded to be eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially preſerued from the fury of the fire, the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum</hi> into which <hi>the High Prieſt muſt enter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.7.</note> yet not oftner than <hi>once in the</hi> ſpace of a whole <hi>yeere,</hi> ſuch was the glory of it, and <hi>that it ſignified.</hi> Here is the like <hi>maruellous kindneſſe in a ſtrong City;</hi> whereof <hi>Dauid</hi> is partaker but once in all his life, as is very probable; for this mercy, in this manner, was but once conferred, ſeeing it is no where elſe in the ſame phraſe remembred.</p>
            <p>This then is a portion of Scripture, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery word whereof hath his worth, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:131928:10"/>circumſtance his weight, and preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vnto our meditations <hi>Dauids grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, Bleſſed be the Lord,</hi> and the Lords <hi>great goodneſſe</hi> towards him, <hi>He hath ſhewed me his maruellous kindneſſe in a ſtrong City.</hi> In dilating of both which, though we may perfectly diſcouer the branches before we can diſcerne the tree; yet we know that the roote and bole is in reſpect of time before the branches, and when we perceiue the effect and conſequence, we muſt needs preſuppoſe a preceding cauſe: So howſoeuer <hi>Dauids thankfulneſſe</hi> be the firſt expreſſed, yet it muſt needs be granted that the Lords <hi>kindneſſe</hi> was the firſt extended, and therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preiudice to that order which is here vſed in the expreſſing of both theſe acts, for my more methodicall proceeding, and your better profiting, Let <hi>the Lords kindneſſe</hi> be the firſt ſubiect of my ſpeech, and the firſt obiect of your attentions, becauſe it was the firſt in action. For firſt, the Lord <hi>ſhewed his kindneſſe,</hi> and then, <hi>Dauid</hi> teſtified his <hi>Thankfulneſſe.</hi> In the <hi>Lords kindneſſe</hi> obſerue three cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:131928:11"/>Firſt, the Agent, <hi>He.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the <hi>Act,</hi> what this <hi>He</hi> did, <hi>He ſhewed.</hi> Thirdly, the acts obiect, what he ſhewed, <hi>kindneſſe.</hi> Firſt of the agent <hi>He;</hi> that is, the <hi>Lord:</hi> here is the firſt court of the Temple, wherein I no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſet my foot, but on the ſudden ſo rare a Maieſty is vnueiled in my ſight, as my minde is amazed, and my feet ſo fettered that I cannot moue till I glance at the properties of that glorious Perſon, on whom if we caſt our eyes, wee may behold in him not onely the winter of ſharpe ſeuerity, but alſo the ſummer of cheering clemency. Wee may ſee as well a dimple in his cheeke, cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fauoring, as a wrinckle in his brow ſeuerely frowning: For this <hi>He,</hi> though he had before ſmitten as a Foe, yet now doth he ſmile as a Father. This <hi>He,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing drawne a foggy veile ouer his face, ſhewed a cloudy countenance, and yet remouing that veile againe, manifeſteth a gracious looke. This <hi>He</hi> now altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther refreſheth <hi>Dauids</hi> languiſhing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:131928:11"/>with a comfortable calme, who a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before had almoſt ouerturned his ſoule with a tempeſtuous ſtorme; For he ſaid in his ſudden apprehenſion of his danger, wherein he iuſtly was, <hi>through his ſinne, I am caſt out of thy ſight.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 22.</note> So that <hi>in the Lord are indifferently ſeated as in their proper ſubiect two different properties, Mercy and Iustice, and by him are indifferently execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted two diuers workes, Seuerity and Clemency.</hi> As is partly ſhadowed in the creatures, plainly ſhewed in the ſacred Scriptures, by his workes demonſtrated, in reaſon may bee confirmed, by all muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed.</p>
            <p>Shadowed in the creatures: Thinke not much by things created, to learne the knowledge of their Creator, For <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentem narrat quaelibet herba D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um,</hi> Euery plant repreſents Gods preſence. There is no creature though moſt contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but either his vnſearchable wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or his vnreſiſtable power, or the all-warming Sunne of his goodneſſe, or the all-ſeeing eye of his prouidence; One
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:131928:12"/>or other of his ineffable properties is leſſe or more ſhadowed in it. And as we may finde the Fountaine by the Riuer, and the Spring by the Streame, ſo wee may attaine at the leaſt a glance at, and ſee with <hi>Moſes</hi> the hinder parts of the Lord by his workes. For <hi>the inuiſible things of God</hi> from the creation of the world are cleerely ſeene, being vnderſtood by the things that are made, euen his eternall power and Godhead, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> affirmeth.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.20.</note> And therefore aptly is <hi>Seculum</hi> called <hi>Speculum,</hi> this worlds Globe termed a looking-glaſſe. And not without cauſe doth <hi>Iob</hi> ſend vs to the ſenſeleſſe creatures to learne our leſſons concerning him.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ch.</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Aske</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the beaſts, and they ſhall teach thee; and the Fowles of the Heauen, and they ſhall tell vnto thee: or ſpeake to the earth, and it ſhall ſhew thee; or the fiſhes of the Sea, and they ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare vnto thee:</hi> euen this amongſt other, that as the Lion hath his paw to impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, his voice to terrifie, and his teeth to teare his prey, yet withall commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:131928:12"/>the woes of the proſtrate, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth no rauenous beaſt to touch that which he hath vndertaken to protect: So the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Iuda</hi> can as well encounter his foes with terrour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 5.5.</note> as entertaine his friends in fauour. As the Eagle hath his talents to ſtrike, and his wings to ſhadow, ſo the Lord hath his threats to chaſtiſe, and his fauours to encourage. As the Leopard hath come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpots to delight as well as a crooked countenance to affright: and as whom the beautifull skinne of the Panther al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lureth to fancy, his ſpeed and cruell pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit admoniſheth to feare; ſo the Lord hath a terrible countenance to beget a dread of his might, and varietie of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to breed a delight in his Maieſty, and whomſoeuer the beames of his bounty cannot warme in affection, the flames of his fury ſhall purſue to deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. But if the creatures be not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent trumpeters of this truth, becauſe they in part doe only ſhadow it, let vs heare the ſacred Scriptures, as <hi>Heauens Heralds</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:131928:13"/>proclaiming it as vndeniable, for they plainly ſhew it. Sometimes drawing our eyes to view the Lord ſeated on a white Iuory Throne of Maieſty, with eyes ſparkling forth nothing but ſignes of fauour, with a tongue pronouncing words of comfort, to raiſe vp the deie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſoule, and refreſh the wearied ſpirit, with lips divulging promiſes in their due time certainly to be performed, to confirme the wauering mind, and make reſolute the inconſtant and vnreſolued man, with armes ſtretched out ready to imbrace thoſe that in reuerence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach vnto him, and with a counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance aſſuring the freeneſſe of his grace, and the firmneſſe of his goodneſſe: ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times deſcending from his Throne of excellency, to examine the truth of tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions cry, and ſee the ſinnes of man before he ſtrike, as a mercifull Iudge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to condemne the accuſed, till the euidence be too cleere againſt him, and loth to put the ſword of Iuſtice into the Executioners hand till the priſoners
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:131928:13"/>fault be palpably proued; but on the contrary, when the clamour of impiety is iuſtly apparant, and puniſhment is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be ſinnes deſert, they preſent him exalted on a ſable ſeat, and ſet vpon wraths tribunall, eyes darting out flames of fury, mouth threatning certaine mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, hands caſting downe fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, ſtorme and tempeſt, and a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance menacing the furiouſneſſe of his wrath, and the fulneſſe of the diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedients woe: Somtimes they call him a conſuming fire,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.29. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.3.</note> to imply the greatnes of his diſpleaſure, and a Fortreſſe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipher the firmneſſe of his fauour: Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they compare him to a Lion roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for his prey, and a Lioneſſe robbed of her whelpes, pointing at his fury; to a tender mother comforting her childe, and a pittifull father compaſſionating his owne bowels, painting out his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy: Sometimes ſaying, that he is dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, yet to be delighted in; fearefull, yet fauourable; terrible euen to the Kings of the earth, and yet tender carrying his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:131928:14"/>children vpon Eagles wings, farre and free from any danger, as loth to haue them harmed as the Apple of his owne eye hurt. A God of wrath with his Bow bent, Arrowes ready, and Weapons pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and yet a Sun to ſolace, &amp; a Shield to ſhelter thoſe that are afflicted. Truly therefore did the ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael</hi> concerning him warble vpon his Harpe, <hi>Mercy and Truth are met together, Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Peace haue kiſſed each other:</hi> For this is demonſtrated by his works of both Mercy and Iuſtice, whereſoeuer for the place, on whomſoeuer for the perſons manifeſted.</p>
            <p>For the place, whether in Heauen, Earth, or Hell. In Heauen the perſiſting of the good Angels, the ioyes prepared there for theſe bleſſed Saints, who yet continue in their fleſhly Tabernacles, and enioyed there by thoſe happy, euer happy ſoules, who in him haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued from their earthly manſions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound his mercy: In Heauen, his thence expelling the backſliding Angels, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:131928:14"/>excluding out the curſed crue, blazon his Iuſtice: for his retinue in Heauen, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide in their created condition by his goodneſſe, his redeemed on earth are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to their former farre firmer felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty through his grace, and the helliſh re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probates are for their diſobedience left altogether fruſtrate of any hope of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens happineſſe in his anger.</p>
            <p>In earth the ſeating of <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall, as Soueraigne Viceroy, and Lord Lieutenant ouer all his other creatures in Paradiſe a place of pleaſure, ready and fully furniſhed with all things to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the minde and ſuſtaine the body: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his fall, the fatherly calling, fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conuenting, mild examining of him; nay his prouiding, euen publiſhing the remedy to redreſſe his ruines, <hi>Adam</hi> not ſo much as dreaming of, much leſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring, leaſt of all endeuoring any, dictate his Clemency. But the ſharpe inflicted cenſure vpon the ſerpent perſwading, and our firſt parents perpetrating that Act of diſobedience, their then preſent
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:131928:15"/>and for euer after perpetuall exile ſo duly deſerued, from that place ſo greatly abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, declare his ſeuerity.</p>
            <p>In hell the worme of conſcience gnawing, the firie flame ſcorching, dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe moleſting the eies, howling and gnaſhing of teeth poſſeſſing the eares, bitterneſſe and vnquenchable thirſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending the taſte, ſulphurious ſtench in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting the ſmell, endleſſe, eaſeleſſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſſe paines, ſurpriſing the touch. To conclude in one word, what muſt be continued beyond all worlds, and is not to be expreſſed by any words; ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row without ſolace, mourning without melody, grieuous pangs without the leaſt gladding pleaſure; paint out his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: yet euen there this doth point at his fauour; that hee might at this preſent more ſeuerely puniſh them, ſeeing by an infinite Maieſtie offended, by an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible deity diſobeyed, an endleſſe torment might duly be exacted, an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable torture might iuſtly be infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, as well for the greatneſſe as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:131928:15"/>of the puniſhment, as ſoone as the tranſgreſſion was committed.</p>
            <p>In that then their miſeries are not more nor their ſufferings more vnſufferable; as yet is extended mercy towards thoſe who are altogether miſerable, ſo as if we conſider the place, the Lord is ſeene both in heauen, earth, and hell, neither whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly depriued of pitty, nor fully poſſeſſed with diſpleaſure. The ſame wee may note in him, if we glance at the perſons on whom his workes of Iuſtice and Mercy are executed, whether we ſuruey their diuerſity or Identity.</p>
            <p>The perſons diuerſity, the Lord being mercifull to one at that time when he is iuſt to another, &amp; contrarily againſt one furious, when to another he is fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. Thus when his wrathfull power made way to his indignation vtterly to conſume <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</note> at the ſame inſtant his mercifull Prouidence found out a path ſafely to conuey <hi>Lot</hi> and his family: In like manner when his mercy ſtaied the furious waters of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:131928:16"/>Red ſea,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.</note> for deliuering his choſen Iſrael, his rage burſt out by the ſame waters ouer the banks of that mercy and drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Egyptians. The Lord as the Sun withdrawing his preſence and light from one Nation, at the ſame ſeaſon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſeth the comfort of his raies vpon another region; and as the fire hath a diuers operation, extending its heate to things of different qualities, ſoftning hard wax, and hardning ſoft clay in the ſame moment yet herein the Creator ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds theſe creatures, that he workes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly vpon the ſame ſubiect, being both iuſt and mercifull, mercifull and iuſt vnto men, conſidered in the Iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of their perſons, where without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of, or relation to any other, the ſame man is the obiect of his actions, be he bad or good.</p>
            <p>The bad haue children at their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, leaue their ſubſtance for their babes their Tabernacles doe proſper,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 12.6.</note> and they themſelues are in ſafety, who prouoke God; their bellies are filled with his rich
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:131928:16"/>treaſure, their riches doe ſo increaſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.4.</note> and their wealth commeth on ſo faſt, in their life is ſuch a ſeeming bliſſe, and in their death no bands; that they doe euen what they liſt, they are rauiſhed with delight, paſſe their daies in iollity, make feaſts like Kings, drinke their Wine in bowles, and ſtretch their bulks vpon beds of Iuory; in this to them is exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Gods fauour, but either in that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant they are beſotted with a forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Gods mercies, ſacrificing to their owne nets, and of others miſeries, not thinking of,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.16.</note> or <hi>not caring for the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Ioſeph</hi> or they are in the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment areſted with a ſudden feare, as the rich man in the Goſpell, or they are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently attached with a ſenſleſſe deſpaire, as <hi>Nabal,</hi> or at the laſt, howſoeuer long firſt, they are ſummoned to a dreadfull ſentence as <hi>Diues;</hi> ſo that as truly ſaid <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> that long-experienced much-ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing King,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 14.13.</note> either <hi>in laughing their hearts are ſorrowfull,</hi> or <hi>their mirth doth end in mourning,</hi> either their inward griefes are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:131928:17"/>vſhered with outward gladneſſe, or their temporall proſperity attended on with eternall miſery, the one whereof in them is a badge of Gods louing boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the other the very cognizance of the Lords iuſt puniſhing equitie. But doe the bad only beare the badges of mercy and miſery? is he not alſo as well a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Lambe to the good, before, in, after their conuerſion? Yes ſurely.</p>
            <p>Before their conuerſion as they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer not from the wicked in vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo neither are they altogether free from the ſignes and ſuffering of his wrath, threatnings ſounding in their eares, hell gnawing on their ſoules, iudgement ſeaſing on them and theirs, whereby they cannot but diſcerne him iuſt. Yet in that he is ſo patient in wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for, ſo diligent in working of their conuerſion,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 65.2.</note> 
               <hi>ſpreading his hands out early and late towards them,</hi> who are as yet rebellious, <hi>deluing and digging about,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 13.8.</note> dunging &amp; prui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thoſe trees, which as yet are fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, preſenting himſelfe to them in loue,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:131928:17"/>who abſent themſelues from him in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty, intreating and wooing them, whom as a father his ſonnes, he might command; as a Soueraigne his ſubiects, he might inioine; or a Lord his vaſſals, he might compell, they cannot towards them not behold him mercifull before their conuerſion.</p>
            <p>Note now the <hi>Echo</hi> of my accent in reſounding his mercy and iuſtice, in the very moment of his childrens change, then he lets them ſee themſelues plunged in the deuouring ſea of their ſinnes, fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered in the Giues of their tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſeruants to the rigour of the Law, ſubiect to eternall death, and ſlaues to the vnſatiable tyranny of Satan, which being ſeene with feare is felt with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, for hereby their conſciences do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake, awakening accuſe, accuſing ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, conuict, condemne them of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe to ſo good, of rebellion to ſo great a God: then their hearts boile with throbs, the ſire of remorſe is kindled in their ſoules, and the flames breake out
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:131928:18"/>at their mouthes, or at leaſt is ſignified to be there by their ſighs, for either the tongue, or the heart in the tongues ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, cryeth out with the leprous, <hi>I am vncleane,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Len.</hi> 13.45.</note> 
               <hi>I am vncleane:</hi> and with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.20.</note> 
               <hi>Wretched man that I am, who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death?</hi> Thus hee appeares vnto them in the ſhape of a terrible Lion, but leſt they bee circumuented or too much endangered, hee preſently binds vp theſe wounds, ſtops and ſtaies theſe dangerous iſſues, tendreth them a plaiſter compacted of his owne mercies and his Sonnes me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, a ſalue compounded of his bounty and their Sauiours bloud, and withall ſo inlightneth their vnderſtanding, that they looking vpon his good pleaſure, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend a poſſibility of their pardon, he appeares in the meekneſſe of a lambe. In that therefore hee brings them by the mouth of Hell to the gates of Heauen, cauſing them to condemne themſelues, leſt they ſhould bee condemned with the world,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.31.</note> then offring them the meanes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:131928:18"/>of their amendment, the occaſion of their better change, when hee might iuſtly leaue them in their miſery, and paſſe by them weltring in their polluted bloud; then reuealing to them his grace,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.6.</note> when hee might righteouſly conceale from them his goodneſſe; then preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them with a pardon, when hee might duly inflict vpon them puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, yet ſo as firſt the horrour of their ſinnes muſt ſeiſe vpon their ſoules, and the hainouſneſſe of their iniquities ſet vpon their conſciences that deepe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of their deſerts, which afterward can bee defaced by no power but his owne ſpirit: hee is iuſt and mercifull, mercifull and iuſt, to the good in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtant of their change, neither is hee otherwiſe after their change, and in the continuance of their conuerſion: For ſinners hating their apparant holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and Satan enuying their prepared happineſſe, aſſault the Fortreſſe of their faith, batter the Caſtle of their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, vndermine the Bulwarkes of their obedience, and deface the Towers of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:131928:19"/>their conuerſation: all which being built and ſemented with the rubbiſh of old corruption, admit many breaches, the <hi>Luſt of the fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life:</hi> carnall pleaſures, coueted profits, enchanting vanities, are as decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing baites, whereon their fleſh as the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle fiſh too often greedily feedeth, and their corruption as Tinder with theſe ſparkes of Hell are ſet on fire; and thus becomming ſinners, they ſuffer; being to corruption affected, with croſſes they are afflicted; and tainted with pollution, are touched with puniſhment. There is the Lords iuſtice. Yet in that they are infeſted, leſt they ſhould be more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected; in that their miſeries are mixt with ioyes, and moderated according to what they are able to beare; in that their ſuffrings are ſeaſoned with heauens ſalt, and ſalued with an happy ſucceſſe, they either taken from their trials, or their tribulation remoued from them; in that grace, in the midſt of miſery, is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued in them, and glory, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:131928:19"/>all calamity is reſerued for them, is manifeſt his mercy: Doe then the good after their conuerſion feele out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſorrow when they perceiue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſolace, and are they perplexed with outward croſſes as well as repleniſhed with inward comforts? though they be euer ſeized of many graces, doe they yet ſuffer many grieuances, and is not the Lord euen to them iuſt and mercifull? iuſt he is, not freeing corruption from calamity, mercifull he is, not leauing tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation in perplexity.</p>
            <p>Thus it is demonſtrated by his works of mercy and iuſtice, whether we looke on the place where, or the perſons on whom they are executed, that the Lord as well beares a knife to cut, as brings a ſalue to cure, and hath as well a heart to raiſe vp as a hand to caſt downe.</p>
            <p>Let vs now attempt to confirme the ſame, by reaſon taken from thoſe abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities which muſt be granted if this bee denied, whether wee conſider him, our ſelues, or others. In him his attributes
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:131928:20"/>or his office are diſparaged. The Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes which ſhould adde oyle to this Lampe, and make the light of this truth ſhine more cleerely, are his liberty, his omnipotency, his verity; but his liberty is abridged, his omnipotency obſcured, his verity falſified, if either the mercy or the iuſtice of the Lord bee excluded, his liberty is abridged. For if wee ſay he is all mercy, how is not his word control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, his will violently carried againſt it ſelfe with the inundations of the ſinnes of men, which not only in this world, he muſt neceſſarily be content to winke at, but alſo in the world to come willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entertaine? If he be all mercy, thoſe who are knowne to him to be branded in conſcience, &amp; to the Deuils to be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in conuerſation with the curſe of hel, muſt by him be acknowledged to haue right to, and be made partakers of the bliſſe of Heauen. On the contrary ſide, if he be all Iuſtice, how is not the ſame will of his enforced to leaue thoſe hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, for whom hee had purpoſed, to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:131928:20"/>whom he hath promiſed happineſſe? If he had beene all Iuſtice, he had left in the pawes of Satan, that roaring deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lion, thoſe who are redeemed by the precious bloud of his Sonne that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maculate Lambe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.8.</note> 
               <hi>The winde bloweth where it liſteth,</hi> and the winds Creator worketh as him liketh, doing as ſaies the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> what pleaſeth him in heauen and earth, and in the depths, which hee could not doe if he were not free: Now confeſſing him to be free, wee muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him to bee both iuſt and mercifull, or elſe his liberty is abridged; and beſides, a Cloud is caſt ouer his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, &amp; his Omnipotency is obſcured, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he muſt either ſuffer what he would not, or not doe what he ſhould.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de ciu. Dei cap.</hi> 10.</note> Now <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur omnipotens faciendo quod vult, non pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo quod non vult,</hi> ſaies Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> To doe what he will, paints out Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potency: to ſuffer what hee will not, points at impotency. Take away his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and he muſt ſuffer the blaſpheming of his name, the violating of his lawes,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:131928:21"/>the contempt of his commands with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all remedy. An earthly Commander ſhall reuenge the leaſt offered indignity, and Heauens Creator ſhall not be able to redreſſe, but muſt endure the higheſt, the moſt hainous blaſphemy. Take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way his mercy, a worldly Monarch ſhall aduance his Fauorite, a meane Lord ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt a well deſeruing ſeruant, a poore fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gratifie a truly obedient ſonne, but he by whom Princes reigne ſhall not conferre dignity on thoſe in whom his ſoule delighteth; nor the Lord of Lords reward his ſeruants diligence; nor the Father of all that is called Father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen or earth, countenance his Childs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience. Take away iuſtice, hee who fetters the Nobles in linkes of iron, and breaks in peeces the Princes of the earth, as a Potters veſſell, ſhall himſelfe be lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the chaines of impiety, becauſe he cannot puniſh iniquity. Take away mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, he who moueth mans heart to pitty, openeth mens eares to attend, ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth mans hands to aid them who are
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:131928:21"/>in miſery, ſhall haue his owne heart ſo benummed, that he cannot commiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; his owne eares ſo ſhut, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heare, and his owne arme ſo ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that he cannot reach them who are in calamitie. But there is no Lord which liues not vnder his law, either obeying what he enioyneth, or enduring what he inflicteth. There is no honour or diſhonour, but is receiued from his hand, either as a gratious ſigne of his loue, or as the deſerued ſucceſſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty, which he diſpoſeth as power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully without reſiſtance, as freely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect. Is he then deſtitute of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Iuſtice or Mercy? far be that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit from our cogitations, for it is the falſifying of his verity, both in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and in his threatnings. His gratious promiſes are as Sugar ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning euery ſuffering, as hony deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting euery Sinne-diſtempered taſte, as Triacle driuing corruption from the ſoule; as Goats bloud ſoftning an Adamantine heart, his gratious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:131928:22"/>giue a Superſedeas againſt the band of Law, proclaime a writ of priuiledge from the Arreſt of death, and ſue out a Writ of Error, to reuerſe the doome of condemnation, paſſed againſt ſin in the court of conſcience. Yet let this be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that God is only iuſt and not merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, the minde cannot but conceiue, the vnderſtanding muſt needs aſſume, and reaſon will neceſſarily conclude, that all his faire promiſes are but bare pretences, Sinne and Deſpaire ſitting at the helme; Contrarily threatnings are the terror of the Soule, the trouble of the thoughts, the awakening of the drowſie threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, turne Sendall into Sackloth, caſt crownes of gold downe among the duſt, and aduance duſt as a more golden ornament for the head. Threatnings as bitter potions, purge the ſuperfluous humors of impietie; and as fire the wax, prepareth the heart to receiue the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Gods ſpirit; yet if God bee wholly mercifull and not iuſt, will not the ſoule ſurmiſe them to bee clouds
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:131928:22"/>without raine, Scorpions without ſtings, and leſſe to be feared than a thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derclap in another horizon, ſecurity and preſumption hoiſing the ſayles. But now though heauen and earth ſhall paſſe, though the glorious Fabricke of the worlds Globe ſhall be wrapped to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as a Scrole, yet not one tittle of his word ſhall faile: what hee promiſed in mercy, ſhall be performed in clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and what hee threatned in iuſtice ſhall bee executed in ſeueritie, the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his will, the greatneſſe of his power, the certainty of his truth, his libertie, omnipotency, verity, all and euery of them, iointly and ſeuerally, doe conuince, that the Lord as well holds out the blacke Enſigne of war, as the White colours of peace.</p>
            <p>Or elſe to come to his office, how ſhould he bee <hi>Iudge</hi> of all the world. There are three properties in a Iudge, which ſhould be as inſeparable to him, as heat is to the fire, moiſture to the aire, drineſſe to the earth, coldneſſe to the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:131928:23"/>that he <hi>Heare indifferently, Examine di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, determine vnpartially,</hi> which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per duties cannot be performed, if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeuerity be ſwallowed vp of cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, or clemency choaked with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerity. Now howſoeuer God ſeeing the hearts and reines, diſcerning the ſecreteſt thoughts and intentions, to whom all things are naked, needes not to liſten, liſtening to labour by due ſifting to winnow out the truth, yet in paſſing ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence he is to deale vnpartially. Shall the Iudge of the world not doe right; and yet when the Sheepe and Goats, Wolues and Lambes, the Children of light and imps of darkneſſe, thoſe who beare on their ſoules his owne ſtampe, and thoſe on whoſe hearts Satan may ſee the writing of his owne hand, ſhall ſtand before him to heare their ſeuerall doomes, being all mercy hee muſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue the wicked, and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng all Iuſtice, he cannot ſaue the godly, and ſo he muſt neceſſarily paſſe a partiall and vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgement, who is holy in all his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:131928:23"/>waies, and righteous in all his workes; Iuſt when hee ſpeaketh, and pure when he iudgeth; whom neither malice can iuſtly maligne, nor Error ſhall euer bee able to blemiſh with abſurdity, neither in regard of his office, or his attributes, wherewith Satan would inueigle vs, by blinding our minde with this miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that the Lord is either onely merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, to cauſe preſumption, or only Iuſt, to enforce deſpaire. But if he were only iuſt and not mercifull, the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> had either not ſinned, or hauing ſinned, had continued in vanity: if only merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and not iuſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam</hi> had either not died or died in vaine: If hee were not a God of anger, feare were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſarie; If not a God of fauour, faith a fancy: our tribulations ſhould be end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, if he only frowning; our ſufferings fruitleſſe, if not fauourable. What wipes our teares from our eies, puts them in his bottle, regiſters them in his booke? not his mercy? What heares the ſighes of the ſoule, the groaning of the ſpirit, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:131928:24"/>the crying of the heart? not his mercy? What preſerues our hands from acting, our eies from beholding, our feet from following vanitie? not his mercy? Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is the marke whereat our mourning aimeth; Mercy is the limit where our ſorrow boundeth; Mercy is that Ocean where our miſery endeth. To no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe ſhould we grieue if the Lord were not good, to no end ſhould we ſorrow if he were not gracious. On the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, what is that in him which heareth our impieties? the eares of his iuſtice: What is that in him which eſpieth our vanities? the eyes of his iuſtice: What is that in him which puniſheth our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? the hand of his iuſtice. To no ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect ſhould we feare ſpirituall death, if he be not righteous; in vaine ſhould wee flye from eternall danger, if he be not ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous: If he were not both iuſt and mercifull, mercifull and iuſt, caution to preuent ſinne were a needleſſe care; care to perfect ſanctity an vnneceſſary cora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue; either of which not to iudge moſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:131928:24"/>neceſſary in our ſelues, is an horrible ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity, from which we could not bee freed in iudging of others, if wee were once perſwaded that the Lord is not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be drawne to puniſh, or not to be induced to pity: For ſhould we not condemne the generation of the iuſt, in powring out their prayers to preuent his wrath, ſending forth their ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to obtaine his bleſſings? doubtleſſe we ſhould not but account their deſires of feruency but friuolous, and their deeds of fidelity to be ſuperfluous, which ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity ſometime preſerued <hi>Dauid</hi> from a dangerous error, and brought him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Gods Sanctuary; where wee may learne this, as he did the like, that the Lord doth both aſcend the throne of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and ſit in the ſeat of Mercy, vnleſſe in contempt of him, iniury to our ſelues, iniuſtice towards others, we deny him of freedome, power and truth, robbing our ſelues of faith, feare, and obedience, diſrobing thoſe who are good of their holy hope, and hoped for happineſſe,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:131928:25"/>vnleſſe wee ſhake hands with the bad, whoſe conuerſation expreſſe their minds corruption, and their manners teſtifie the peruerſneſſe of their opinion, and conceit Heauens happineſſe to be a ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of poeſie, and hels horror to be only a fable of policy: blaſphemies, abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble blaſphemies once to bee imagined. We will acknowledge him to be a God abundant in goodneſſe and mercy, and yet not making the wicked innocent, as by all muſt be confeſſed: For if any might pleade altogether for Gods mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, then Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne the engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen image of his ſubſtance participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his owne eſſence, equall in might and maieſty with himſelfe, doing nothing which might offend him, all things appointed by him, his begotten, onely begotten, his beloued, beſt beloued ſonne, in whom alone hee is well pleaſed: yet if he became a pawne for ſinne, he muſt beare the pangues of ſorrow; if hee will vndertake the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens faults, he muſt vndergoe the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:131928:25"/>fury, ſo as though he be preſerued becauſe a ſonne, he ſhall be puniſhed as a ſeruant; though hee ſhall weare the crowne of glory as a Conquerour, yet firſt he muſt beare the brunt of the battel becauſe a Champion: ſo that Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but confeſſe him a God of Iuſtice. From which, if any other might ſeeme to be free, then the bleſſed Angels; or if any might be thought not to partake of mercy, then the infernall and damned ſpirits: but as the former muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Lord to be iuſt, though Iuſtice in them may ſeeme to be ſwallowed vp of mercy, ſo the latter muſt confeſſe the Lord to be mercifull, though mercy in them appeare to be ſmothered by iuſtice. For if Iuſtice be to attribute to euery one his due, and Gods will be the rule of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, ſeeing that he hath purpoſed and appointed the bleſſed Angels continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in their created condition, that condition becomes their due, becauſe the Lord is in ſome ſort become their debter, not for their worthineſſe, but
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:131928:26"/>of his owne good will. Now as to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe that which he hath done, were to blemiſh his power, to brand him with impotency; ſo not to continue that which he hath once vnalterably decreed ſhall be conferred, is in him apparant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, to them manifeſt iniury. In that therefore, what he once purpoſed is ſtill performed, what he once intended is neuer deſiſted, the continuance of his will is the continuance of his iuſtice, whereof his will is the Life and Law, to which his will giues birth and being, rule and direction, ſo as they remaining within the liſts of his will, cannot bee without the limits of his Iuſtice: For ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Iuſtice giueth euery one his due, and it is equall and iuſt that the Creator ſhould binde the creature, and the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture obey the Creator, in that his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands are in force among them, and their obedience performed towards him: the bleſſed Angels muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe him iuſt becauſe they may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vnto him obedience the badge of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:131928:26"/>Iuſtice, whereby it is diſcerned as the tree by the fruit, the flower by the ſmell, the fire by the heat, the ſeruant by his liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Therefore as <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De verb. Orig.</note> 
               <hi>In coelo ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la vtique iuſtitia, nihilominus laetitia;</hi> ſo may I ſay (not againſt his ſenſe and meaning) though in Heauen there may ſeeme to be onely ioy, yet there is alſo iuſtice, for obedience the Liuery of it is there worne, and Gods will the Rule of it is there working, and howſoeuer mercy is there to them ſet vp for euer, yet his truth is eſtabliſhed in the very Heauens.</p>
            <p>But how ſhall it appeare that his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is manifeſt in any manner or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to the damned ſoules and infernall ſpirits? As for the damned ſoules, herein he is good to them, that hee as yet ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not their bodies with them, to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take of the ſame puniſhment, ſeeing as the body did increaſe the ſinne of the ſoule while they were vnited, ſo the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the body in the courſe of iuſtice muſt augment the tortures, ſorrowes, and pangs of the ſoule, ſo ſoone as they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:131928:27"/>are againe conioyned. As for the infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſpirits, herein his mcrcy towards them is vndeniable, in that their decreed and long ſince iuſtly deſerued torments are not in the greateſt and moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous meaſure as yet inflicted, as ſome of themſelues ſeeme to inſinuate, and inſinuating confeſſe to our Sauiour while they as it were complaine of and repine againſt him, <hi>Art thou come to torment vs before the time?</hi> which is not ſo to be conceiued, as though they were not now tormented, but that the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their torments is for a time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred. Tormented they now are; for can the Malefactor thinke of his doome, and his ſpirits not be daunted with the thought of death? Perhaps a Malefactor may be either comforted vpon repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, hoping for a better life, or not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, atheiſtically conceiting, there is hereafter neither better nor worſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared lot: But Satan cleerely appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends, and apprehending certainely knowes the ſentence that is decreed to
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:131928:27"/>paſſe againſt him, is as ſeuere as it is ſure, and therefore needs muſt the horrour of his iudgement for the preſent greatly perplexe him. Doth the emptineſſe of the Lions entrailes make him roare when he wants, and whiles he ſeekes his prey, and ſhall we not thinke that hee is pinched? Doth enuy conſume the bones, and malice breake out into fury, &amp; ſhall we not ſay, that the mind is grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and the man much vexed? Surely then, Satan through his vnſatiable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire alwaies hungry and roaring for his prey, neuer deſtitute of enuy and malice,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.7.</note> in that Gods glory is preſerued, Chriſts Kingdome increaſed, thoſe who were farre inferiour to him, by created con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and conſtitution, are daily prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to bee partakers of thoſe ioyes and perfections, whereof if not of greater, he is and for euer ſhall be depriued, cannot but be much tormented; or elſe whence is it that he is ſaid to rage, which is encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by how much more the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment draweth neere. An vnanſwerable
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:131928:28"/>argument, that it is out of a certaine feare and an aſſured expectation, that he ſhall be made partaker of greater torment, which without eaſe or remedy he is euer after to endure. And if the waters when they are dammed, ſwell the higher, and the putrified tumor not launched, paine the ſorer: how ſhall not he now fretting, then euen eat himſelfe in fury, when all occaſion by which, and ſubiects ſaue his owne vaſſals, whereupon to worke his malice, ſhall be fully remoued, and his powerfull rage and raging power fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally reſtrained? And the rather becauſe hee ſhall ſtill retaine a deſire to caſt duſt vpon the beauty of Gods glory, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if then it were poſſible, the felicity of the bleſſed Angels, &amp; euer happy Saints, of whom euery Alleluiah which they ſing vnto the Almighty, being as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtinging Scorpions to his malicious minde. Thus farre then God is gracious vnto them, in that though they be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered into <hi>chaines of darkneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Iud.</hi> 9.</note> where can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not want horror, yet they are as yet only
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:131928:28"/>
               <hi>reſerued vnto iudgement,</hi> which hereafter is to paſſe both againſt and vpon them. Oh the loue, goodneſſe and bounty of God, for height as <hi>Iacobs</hi> Ladder it ſtretcheth to the Heauens, for bredth as the Curtaine, it couereth all Nations, for length it extendeth to all times, for depth it pierceth the darkſome dennes of the damned ſoules and infernall ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: So as it is ſhadowed in the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, cleerely ſhewed in the ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, by his workes of both mercy and iuſtice manifeſted, in reaſon confirmed, by all muſt bee confeſſed, that God is mercifully iuſt, and iuſtly mercifull, and though his mercy be enlarged, his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is not leſſened, and though his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice be inflicted, yet his mercy is exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Oh that we were ſuch Eagles as that the eyes of our minds could ſo gaze at this Sunne, that bathing our ſelues in the water of Gods ſacred Fountaine, our old corruption might be ſhaken off, and we ſo renued in the ſtrength of our crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted condition, that the meditation of his
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:131928:29"/>mercy and iuſtice ſo indifferently ſeated in him, the conſideration of his ſeuerity and clemency ſo vnpartially executed by him, might alwaies ſit at the helme of our hearts, hoiſe the ſailes of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and be the Pilot of our practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in reſpect of him, our ſelues, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; then ſhould wee, in reſpect of him, not onely in our affections ſaile with a faire gale of fearing loue, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render to him his right of our louing feare, eſpying the Enſignes of his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: but alſo in our actions his cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency would cheriſh alacrity, and his ſeuerity inflame our ſincerity: For our affections, as the nobler metals caſt into the Furnace, are turned into the colour, and participate of the heat of fire, ſo the heart of man fixed vpon Gods mercy by meditation, ſhould be fired with the loue of his Maieſty, hauing an eye to his due, our duty, and the dignity of it. His due, it is as he is God, louely in himſelfe, louing towards vs. Louely in himſelfe, and therefore well ſaid <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tract. de dilig. Deo.</note> 
               <hi>Cauſa
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:131928:29"/>diligendi Deam Deus eſt;</hi> ſufficient cauſe of louing the Lord, is the conſideration that he is God. For whatſoeuer is deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that he is. Doth power is the <hi>Ada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant</hi> iron) draw our affections to it. He is King of Kings, the Lord of Lords, a God of Omnipotency. Does that which is auncienta lure our hearts to delight in it? He is the auncient of daies, a God of greateſt antiquitie. Doth knowledge keepe the minde in admiration of it? He vnderſtandeth our thoughts long before, neither is any thing hid vnto him, a God of omniſciency. He is the God of vnity, which is the honour of brethren; the God of conſtancy, the crowne of friendſhip; the God of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the glory of man. He is a ſhade to the weary, a ſhelter to the wronged, a treaſury to the needy. Hee is truth which is ſo much commended; He is light in which we are ſo much deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; He is life which of all things is ſo much deſired. If honour the aime of the ambitious, if riches the deſire of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:131928:30"/>couetous, if fame the hope of the vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious, if excellency, abſolute perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, endleſſe felicity, or any other thing which ſoules would wiſh to be partakers of, may glue our hearts vnto them, then the Lord: For all things that are good are in him, and deriued from him who is goodneſſe it ſelfe: to be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe in himſelfe he is ſo louely, and ſo louing towards vs, louing vs <hi>freely, fully, firmely.</hi> For before we loued him,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>he loued vs firſt,</hi> the dew of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces fell firſt vpon our fruitleſſe ſoules, the beames of his bounty reflected firſt vpon our vnſanctified hearts, the light of his countenance ſhone firſt vpon our darkened vnderſtandings: our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were firſt warmed with the fire of his loue, our deſires firſt kindled with the blaſt of his ſpirit, our dead members firſt reuiued with the hand of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, before we conceiued, affected, acted any thing which was heauenly: Till the furrowes of our hearts were ſowen with the ſeed of his bleſſings, nothing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:131928:30"/>but weeds there appeared; till we as trees were tranſplanted into the ſoyle of his Church, nothing but bitter fruits were there to be gathered; till wee as plants were inoculated into Chriſt the true Vine, nothing but ſowre grapes could there be taſted. His loue caſt ſalt into our waters and made them ſweet, put clay vpon our eies and made them ſee: then, then, not before, we watered the tender ſprigs in his orchard, and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the ſweetneſſe of his fauour; and ſo louing vs firſt, he loued vs <hi>freely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Freely, when we <hi>would not,</hi> when we <hi>could not</hi> loue him; when we would not, for when we were filled with malice, ſwelled with enmity, oppoſite to all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of Amitie, then did he ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow vs with the wings of his fauor, ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vs in the harbor of his goodneſſe, &amp; hide vs vnder the helmet of his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; when vve ſought his infamy, then wrought he our glory, when we ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uored his hurt, he deuiſed our helpe; when wee actuated his death, he redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:131928:31"/>our life; when our enmity fled, neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, reſiſted, then his kindneſſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, called, perſwaded; nay, <hi>when we were enemies we were reconciled to God by the death of his Sonne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10.</note> when we <hi>would not,</hi> he loued vs freely, no leſſe when <hi>we could not,</hi> in reſpect <hi>of our degeneration, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</hi> For our degeneration; it was ſo great as there was nothing gratious in vs, ſuch was the wound which Sathan by ſinne had giuen vs, that wee not onely <hi>lay polluted in our owne bloud,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.6.</note> but the vitall ſpirits of our ſpirituall life were ſo let out, that wee were <hi>dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.5.</note> hauing hearts, but no hearts to loue him; hauing ſoules, but no ſoules to long for him; hauing bodies, but no bodies to worſhip him; our ſoules and bodies as farre from purpoſing any ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall worſhipping, as dead men are from performing any corporall worke: foules and bodies no more willing to yeeld him the leaſt holy affections, than dead men are able to perfect the moſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:131928:31"/>honourable action. Freely then he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs, in that he died for vs and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vs by his ſpirit, when we were ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and dead in treſpaſſes; ſo that we <hi>could not</hi> loue him in regard of our <hi>dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</hi> Let vs now ſee the freeneſſe of his loue towards vs when wee <hi>could not</hi> loue him in regard of <hi>generation.</hi> We had not then receiued being, when Gods loue tovvards vs had receiued a beginning; our ſoules were then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breathed, our bodies then vnframed, when our ſoules and bodies were by him affected; When this glorious ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture laid on, nay, in the earth, when our goodlieſt building was only clay, when our <hi>houſes had no</hi> hands as <hi>Keepers to tremble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.3.</note> nor teeth as <hi>grinders</hi> to <hi>ceaſe,</hi> nor eies as <hi>Windowes to looke out at,</hi> nor mouth as the <hi>doore to be ſhut,</hi> nor iawe bones to <hi>ſound in the grinding,</hi> nor arteries or eares as the <hi>daughters</hi> of ſpeech and ſinging to be <hi>abaſed,</hi> no marrow or ſinewes as <hi>ſiluer cord to be leſſened,</hi> nor the braines
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:131928:32"/>Tunicle, as a <hi>golden Ewer to be broken,</hi> nor any Veine as a <hi>Pitcher</hi> wherein the bloud is contained, to be <hi>broken at</hi> the Liuer as <hi>the Well,</hi> nor the head which turnes as a <hi>Wheele, to be broken at</hi> the heart, whence as out of a <hi>Ciſterne</hi> all the powers of life are drawne; nor the body which was raiſed out of the <hi>duſt,</hi> nor the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> which came from God: before any of theſe were to be found, we were intereſted in Gods fauour; the earth was created for our habitation, the creatures appointed for our vſe in Gods loue, before euer either we beheld the Light, or the Light was brought out of darkneſſe, or <hi>darkneſſe</hi> was <hi>vpon the face of the deepe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2.</note> Loue is one of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and affections are ſeated in the heart, the heart is placed in the midſt of the body, but neither could the body conteine the heart, nor the heart caſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, nor the affection be carried in the chariot of Loue, till loue, affection, hart and body had a being. If then the Lords fauour was ſet vpon vs, before
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:131928:32"/>any of theſe were ſited in vs; it is cleerer than the Sunnes brightneſſe, when the cleereneſſe of the skie giues freeſt liberty to his rayes in the midſt of the Hemiſphere, that we <hi>could not</hi> loue him when he loued vs, becauſe we were not when the eies of his excellency did ſparkle the flame of his affections to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs: and therefore he louing vs before we loued him, nay when we as enemies <hi>would not,</hi> as ſinners and dead men in reſpect of degeneration, and without being in reſpect of generation <hi>could not</hi> loue him: I appeale to the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of euery conſcience, if he loued not freely. And ſeeing we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe he loued freely, we may conceit he loued <hi>fully.</hi> For in euery part of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in euery power of the ſoule, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed the character of his fauour. Is the eie at any time reſtrained from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding vanitie? it is a ſigne of his loue: Is the mouth at any inſtant ſhut, that it ſpeaketh not blaſphemy? it is a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of his care. Is the eare at any ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:131928:33"/>ſtopt from hearing calumny? it is an emblem of his mercy. Is the foot ſtaied vpon any occaſion from follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impietie, oppreſſion, and cruelty? it is the enſigne of his goodneſſe. His loue enlightneth the vnderſtanding, His loue rectifieth the Iudgement, His loue ordereth the affections, and his loue directeth the will. Such a Sunne is the Lord to vs, that there is no cranny of the heart but his rayes doe enter, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring enlighten, enlightning informe the minde, reforme the manners, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the whole man to religious cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Childhood claimes a part in his loue, Youth challengeth a portion in his fauour, and Age hath not the leaſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in his mercy. He pardoneth ſins <hi>fully,</hi> accepteth vs in Chriſt <hi>fully,</hi> receiued vs to himſelfe <hi>fully,</hi> will glorifie vs <hi>ſully,</hi> needs then he muſt loue vs <hi>fully,</hi> which hee could not doe if hee loued not <hi>firmely;</hi> for then there ſhould be with him mutability,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>with whom there is neither colour nor ſhadow of changing.</hi> Loue
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:131928:33"/>in electing vs before all time was the beginning (if I may attribute begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to that which is without all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning) Loue in redeeming vs in his appointed time was the continuing; Loue in glorifying vs beyond all time, ſhal be the conſummating of our felicity, all which trumpet out the <hi>firmneſſe</hi> of it. That friendſhip is not firme which is deſiſted, that fauour is not faithfull which is not continued, that faith not conſtant which is violated. Cancell the euidence of his Couenant, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifie the truth of his promiſes, ſtop the Fountaine of his mercies towards vs, how ſhall he be <hi>the finiſher of our ſaluation?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2.</note> Though this Ocean be diſperſed into many chanels, it ſuffers no diminution; though this Sunne bee extended into many climates, it admits no diuiſion; though this gold bee tranſported into many countries, it is free from alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſo ſtrong as labour cannot weaken it, ſo ſolid as vſe cannot weare it, ſo rich a treaſury as time it ſelfe cannot waſt it.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:131928:34"/>It followed <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in his <hi>brethrens hatred,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.</note> attended on him among the <hi>Madianites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 39.</note> houered ouer him in the <hi>Priſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 40.</note> honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him in <hi>Pharohs</hi> Court.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 41.</note> If Iſrael <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell from one Nation to another people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 105.13, 14.</note> Gods loue <hi>ſuffered no man to doe them wrong,</hi> and rather than they ſhall bee vnregarded, <hi>Kings</hi> ſhall be <hi>rebuked.</hi> Contrarieties are combined for the good of vs, if we bee within his loues compaſſe, what proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity promiſeth aduerſity bringeth, and what is denyed by calamity, is not yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by temporall felicity, loue ſeeking in all things alike our good, and kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vs alwaies at one with our God, ſo as <hi>neither death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38, 39.</note> 
               <hi>nor life, nor Angels, nor Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, nor Powers, nor things preſent, nor things to come, nor height, nor depth, nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other creature ſhall be able to ſeparate vs from his loue, which is in Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> How are not our hearts as the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ground greatly deſiring, and our bowels troubled within vs, till we finde them filled with a loue of his Maieſty, who is louely in himſelfe, louing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:131928:34"/>vs? ſeeing we yeeld vnto him no more than <hi>his due,</hi> as good, and render him <hi>our only duty,</hi> as God. The Heauens ſpeake vnto the earth, the earth cals vnto the waters, the waters crie vnto the aire, &amp; all of theſe ſummon euery one of their inhabitants to proclaime vnto man that God is onely his, and nothing ſo properly his owne as is the Lord, being <hi>his portion for euer:</hi> if we be hungry,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.26.</note> he is bread for vs; if we be thirſty, he is water to quench it; if we be in darkneſſe, he is light; if we be ſicke, he is our Phyſitian; if we be blinde, he is ſeeing; though wee be deafe, hee is hearing; though wee be lame, he is walking; though we be weak, he is ſtrong; to foreſee, to attend, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide, and to proſecute whatſoeuer may perfect our good, or preuent our euill, inſomuch as euery one of vs may truly ſay with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.26.</note> 
               <hi>Thou art my lot and inheritance, the ſtrength of my heart, and ſaluation of my ſoule.</hi> Let the Fiſh challenge the waters for their due, the beaſts claime the earth for their poſſeſſion, the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:131928:35"/>Fowles the aire for their intereſt, and the glorious Angels the Heauens for their habitation,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22, 23.</note> yet being <hi>Chriſts, and Chriſt</hi> Gods, in him all are ours, he being to vs all in all.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 73.24.</note> 
               <hi>Counſell</hi> to aduiſe vs, wiſdome to direct vs, righteouſneſſe to acquit vs, <hi>ſanctification</hi> to cleanſe vs,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30.</note> 
               <hi>redemption</hi> to free vs, and a King to receiue vs into glory; ſo as euery one of vs may well ſay with the ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25.</note> 
               <hi>Whom haue I in Heauen but thee, and here is nothing in earth that I deſire beſides thee:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be admired, admiring to bee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of vs in <hi>duty,</hi> who did firſt giue vs birth and being, protecting vs againſt all dangers, preſeruing vs in all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils, prouiding for vs in all wants, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs in all doubts, comforting vs in all diſcontents, in a word cauſing <hi>all things,</hi> euen all things, though in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of contrariety,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> to <hi>worke together,</hi> and ſhake hands in amity <hi>for our good,</hi> if as we ought, we <hi>loue him</hi> who is our God: which duty how ſhould we deny vnto him, if wee conſider the dignity of it,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:131928:35"/>which appeareth in the Lords approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, acceptation, and remuneration of it, eſteeming it highly, elſe would he not <hi>inioyne</hi> ſo <hi>ſtrictly</hi> and <hi>inculcate</hi> it ſo <hi>frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: ſtrictly</hi> he <hi>enioynes</hi> it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.5.</note> for there is no part of any <hi>heart</hi> but muſt harbour it, no parcell of any <hi>ſoule</hi> but muſt ſolace in it, nor no portion of any ones <hi>mind</hi> muſt be miſſing to it, nor the leaſt mite of any ones <hi>might</hi> muſt be deteined from it: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this Ocean as well the little ſtreames as the greateſt Riuers muſt pay their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute; vnto this Sea as well the ſmalleſt torrents as the largeſt chanels muſt ſend their preſents, ſo <hi>ſtrictly</hi> it is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and the more ſtrictly in that it is ſo often <hi>called for,</hi> called for by the <hi>Law,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for by the <hi>Goſpell.</hi> That which a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (perceiuing through his age that death approcheth) doth moſt counſell his children either by way of admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or exhortation to ſhunne or follow, the experience of his yeeres, and his haires grauity doe ſeale the neceſſity of it to them, and ſignifie, eſpecially
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:131928:36"/>if he often repeat it, how worthily it is conceited of by him. <hi>Moſes</hi> in diuers meſſages from the Lord, either by way of precept or explanation, either exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or diſſwading, either commanding or commenting vpon his former lawes or louing fauours, <hi>often</hi> plainly preſſeth this duty as the Lords due, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples debt. <hi>Often</hi> doth our Sauiour Chriſt and his Apoſtles propound it as a grace moſt excellent, decipher it as a vertue moſt orient, paint it out as a duty moſt <hi>pleaſant</hi> in it ſelfe, <hi>pleaſing vnto,</hi> nay the very <hi>pleaſing of</hi> God, and that in ſo high a degree as he <hi>graciouſly accepts it;</hi> for in the Word that infallible Truth they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, that the affecting of his Maieſtie in his account is the acting of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and the fixing vpon him our loue is the <hi>fulfilling of the whole Law.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2.</note> As he eſteemes it highly, accepts it heartily, ſo doth he <hi>recompence</hi> it manifoldly with <hi>temporall, ſpirituall and eternall</hi> bleſſings. As for <hi>temporall,</hi> without raine the earth is as braſſe, the ground as iron; but to
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:131928:36"/>thoſe that loue him, hee that is faithfull &amp; cannot either deceiue or be deceiued, he who is truth and cannot faile, he who is wiſdome and cannot erre, hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed that he <hi>will giue them raine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.13, 14.</note> theres a bleſſing; <hi>in due time,</hi> theres the greatneſſe of the bleſſing; euen the <hi>firſt and the latter raine,</hi> that is, in the ſeed time and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Harueſt, to this end <hi>that</hi> (vnleſſe they wilfully contemne his offred bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of plenty, and obſtinately draw vpon their owne heads a curſe of ſcarci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) <hi>they may gather in their wheat, their wine and their oile.</hi> Corne without raine could not grow ripe, and through raine vnſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably falling we could not reape: to haue it then is a bleſſing; to want it, a curſe; and to haue it out of ſeaſon is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a curſe than a bleſſing: In his giuing it then to them that loue him, <hi>in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> lies the ſweetneſſe and marrow of the bleſſing: but though the grapes be preſſed and the wine ſugred in the cup, yet may a man bee depriued of it at the lip, as was <hi>Ancaeus,</hi> from whence aroſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:131928:37"/>that Adage,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eraſ. Adag. chil.</hi> 1. <hi>ceat.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Multa cadunt inter calicem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premaque labra:</hi> though a man bee in full expectation to reape,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.30.</note> yet a reuengefull <hi>Abſolom</hi> may ſend to burne vp the fields of <hi>Ioab</hi> when his Corne is ripe, and <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> by his <hi>Foxes</hi> fruſtrate the hope of the Philiſtins,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jud.</hi> 15.5.</note> hindring their fruitfull har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128.2.</note> but thoſe that loue the Lord ſhall enioy the <hi>fruit</hi> of their <hi>labours,</hi> and <hi>eat the labours of their hands.</hi> No politike <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel,</hi> no malicious <hi>Abſolom,</hi> no enuious <hi>Samſon</hi> ſhal diſappoint them, their <hi>enemies</hi> muſt be <hi>caſt out before them, and their bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders much inlarged:</hi> and becauſe all theſe may be enioyed, and yet we not ioyned with him, to this temporall hee addes <hi>ſpirituall</hi> bleſſings, and ſuch whereby we may perceiue him to be ours, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to vs in the bonds of loue. And leſt ſtrangeneſſe in aſſociation ſhould beget a ſtrangeneſſe in his &amp; our mutuall affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, leſt diſcontinuance of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſhould breed a diſlike or diſunion in opinion, or leſt want of ſocietie ſhould worke the violation of amity,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:131928:37"/>Chriſt promiſeth that both his <hi>Father and He</hi> will deſcend from their glorious Thrones and Seats of Maieſtie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 29.</note> 
               <hi>and come vnto him that loueth him,</hi> and make not as gueſts whoſe ſtay is momentary, but as dwellers and Maſters of the Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, their abode with him, to whom it is impoſſible that any ſpirituall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſhould be abſent, where the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of all ſpirituall grace is preſent. Can that field be vnrefreſhed where a ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fountaine remaineth! or can waters be wanting where is a liuing Well? Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly graces neceſſarily there abound, where the giuer of them abideth, not for once but for euer; for to thoſe that loue him his bleſſings are <hi>eternall.</hi> Many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors doe enioy a crowne which is maintained, attended, with great care, &amp; ſubiect to the greateſt croſſes; nay the head which it adorneth many times is diuided from the body, but he giues to them that loue him a <hi>Crowne of life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1.12.</note> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny enioy the crowne, but want power to poſſeſſe his Kingdome, but thoſe that
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:131928:38"/>loue him,
<note place="margin">2.5.</note> he giues not the Crowne only but <hi>the Kingdome</hi> too. How ſhould not we render the Lord his due in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming our dutie for the <hi>dignitie</hi> of it which he ſo highly eſteemeth, ſo readily approueth, and ſo manifoldly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penceth, with temporall, ſpirituall, and eternall bleſſings? but ſeeing loue is the ground of all which is conferred from God on vs, and the ſubſtance of all that is owing from vs to God, let vs firſt ſee the <hi>meanes</hi> whereby it may be obtained or continued, and the <hi>markes</hi> wherby it is diſcerned.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of the <hi>meanes</hi> whereby it is obtained or continued, we muſt be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>paſsiue</hi> or <hi>actiue. Paſsiue</hi> in the hearts purity: for vpon that condition will this grace enter; and without cleanſing, no expecting it as a Companion: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Hee that was faithfull</hi> in all Gods houſe,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.2.</note> promiſing from the Lord that he will <hi>circumciſe</hi> his peoples <hi>hearts,</hi> adds withall the end of that circumciſing, <hi>that thou maiſt loue the Lord thy God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.6.</note> as if
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:131928:38"/>there could be no louing of the Lord where there was no circumciſing of the heart: and indeed onely then will this loue bee entertained when our hearts are purified: For the loue of God is a fire, and abhors vnfitting fewell, which may either cauſe ſmoke to offend the eies, or ſtench to diſtaſte the ſmell of God, and at laſt extinguiſheth it ſelfe; and therefore as <hi>Noahs</hi> Doue would not ſet one foot vpon the muddy earth, nor any Doue will delight in a foule cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, as no Lion will frequent any pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trified haunt, nor the Turtle pearke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a barren tree: ſo neither will this grace (partaking of the ſpirits qualities from whence it comes, as the water taſteth of the fountaine from whence it floweth) take footing or can delight in a corrupted conſcience; nor ſeeing it is neere allied to the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Iuda,</hi> deigne to harbour in a polluted heart; nor being the Lords trueſt Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, ſit vpon or ſeat it ſelfe in that man whoſe minde is deſtitute of holy medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:131928:39"/>Meditate then, (for you muſt be <hi>actiue</hi>) on the <hi>vngodlies deficiency,</hi> this <hi>graces excellencies,</hi> and the <hi>Lords mercies.</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate vpon that wofull yet aſſured pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of our Sauiour,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.12.</note> 
               <hi>that the loue of many</hi> ſhall wax colde, and it will bee a cocke to awake thy ſleeping conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, a goade to pricke thee forward to feruent prayers, leſt thou ſhouldſt bee one of them that muſt be tainted with ſo great a ſinne. Meditate of the graces excellency, in the <hi>quality, efficacie,</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion,</hi> and that will be as a fire to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame, and as a fewell to continue thy deſire vnto it. For in the <hi>Quality</hi> what grace more <hi>honourable,</hi> in the <hi>efficacie</hi> what grace more <hi>powerfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 4.8.</note> in the <hi>extenſion</hi> what grace more <hi>large,</hi> more <hi>laſting?</hi> remember then how of all graces this is <hi>graced</hi> with the greateſt name, as moſt partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating of the diuineſt nature. Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber how of all graces this is moſt <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> ſeeing <hi>all things</hi> though in neuer ſuch an Antipathy and contention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues, yet as vnited forces,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:131928:39"/>muſt <hi>worke together for the good of thoſe that loue him.</hi> Remember that howeuer the eye may ſee much, the eare heare more, and the heart conceiue more than either the eie can ſee, or the eare can heare; yet <hi>The things which eie hath not ſeene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>eare hath not heard, neither came into mans heart, hath God prepared for thoſe that loue him.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member how of all graces this is <hi>moſt large, moſt laſting.</hi>
               <note place="margin">13.13.</note> Faith ſhall ceaſe vpon fruition, hope end vpon poſſeſſion, loue only continue all the time of our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall happineſſe. Faith is onely for the preſent, Hope for the future, Loue both for the paſt, preſent, and the time to come. Faith is locked within a mans owne breſt, hope helpeth not anothers heart; onely by Loue, as by the Sunne, both the Sphere where it is placed is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned, and another place, vnto which it diffuſeth the rayes, is warmed. Laſtly, meditate on Gods great mercies, in his <hi>promiſes, prouidence, performances,</hi> and they cannot but beget a liking, which ere long will be ſeconded with a zealous
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:131928:40"/>louing of his Maieſtie. Thinke how there is no crowne ſo rich as that which he <hi>promiſeth,</hi> no ioyes ſo rare as thoſe which he <hi>prepareth,</hi> no kingdome ſo large as that which he intendeth, no ſociety ſo louely as that which hee purpoſeth, to them which loue him: thinke how rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily he hath enclined his eares and heard thy cries, how cheerefully hee hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened his mouth and comforted thine heart, how louingly hee hath ſtretched out his arme and remoued thy dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, how freely he hath filled his hand and enriched thy ſoule. Thus the puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of thy heart, meditating on the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlies deficiency, this graces excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and the Lords mercy, will by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of his gracious ſpirit, wrought with faithfull and vnfained praiers, lodge his loue in thy heart; where if it be lodged, by two markes it may be diſcerned.</p>
            <p>For loue begetteth firſt a <hi>deſire of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> ſecondly <hi>a ſimilitude of affection.</hi> Our Communion with the bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:131928:40"/>is twofold, either <hi>Corporall</hi> or <hi>Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall:</hi> this is to be had heere, that to be enioyed hereafter, both to be deſired euer: for they that truly and ſincerely loue Chriſt Ieſus, they will long for his comming, and thirſt for his laſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. Loue is ſuch a linke, as it cannot lacke the Vnion, nay communion with the partie loued; Loue is ſuch a fire in the heart of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that it flames out at his mouth, and manifeſts the deſires of his ſoule,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23.</note> euen to be <hi>diſſolued and to be with Chriſt;</hi> and as a violent fire which keepeth within no bounds, but being driuen with the winde of Gods ſpirit, ſparkles out the wiſhes of the whole Church, as if it were the words but of one bride calling for the company of her ſpouſe, <hi>Come Lord Ieſus, come quickly.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 22.20.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Feruency admits no deferring, and earneſt deſires endure no delaies, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where perfection, compaſſion, and mercy, ſhall vpon their meeting giue a full end to all imperfection, wants, and miſeries. A Chriſtian ſoule well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:131928:41"/>this abſolute and happy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, hauing one only ſparke of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and one onely dragme of loue, muſt needs deſire it. Nothing, ſurely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, can hold it from flying by the wings of feruent prayer, and entring heauens palace; nothing can quench the flame of it, the fire being as ſtrong as death, or hinder its burning aboue the clouds, till the affections of the Churches Spouſe, which ſeeme to bee frozen, in that he comes not at her call, be ſo warmed within him as he may be moued to deſcend, that they meeting him in the clouds may behold his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall countenance, which (becauſe they cannot yet enioy) doe manifeſt the truth and ſincerity of their loue to him ſo long as it is his pleaſure to detaine the former, the affectioned ſoule delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth here, in nothing more, than in a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſocietie with him, which often to earthly men he vouchſafeth, in the place and in the exerciſes by him ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, his houſe, <hi>word, meditation, praier,</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:131928:41"/>and <hi>Sacraments;</hi> and though he be euery where, ſo as if we would we cannot flye from his preſence, yet in that place &amp; in theſe ordinances it pleaſeth him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe with his children, and his children are partakers of his ſpirituall preſence. In his word he manifeſteth his glory, in his <hi>Word</hi> he ſpeaketh and powreth forth his mind to vs: in <hi>prayers</hi> we familiarly talke and powre forth our hearts before him; in the <hi>Sacraments</hi> hee giueth viſible pled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his fauour, and we with the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall eye of our mind, hand and mouth of faith, looke vpon, touch, and taſte the Bread of life: in <hi>meditation</hi> wee enter into his priuy Chamber, and he vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafeth vnto vs a ſight and view of all his richeſt and rareſt treaſuries, where wee may behold more pleaſing, more profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table obiects than could <hi>Berodach Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> in the <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>Hezekiah, pretious things;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 20.12, 13.</note> where we may haue cauſe of greater ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration than had the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> in the hearing of the wiſedome of <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> which to heare ſhe was content,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:131928:42"/>vpon the ſame of it, to leaue her owne Country, thereby teſtifying her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to it: and ſhall not we feeling the fruits of his preſence who is greater than <hi>Salomon,</hi> manifeſt our delight in it by our loue to his houſe and ordinances? He that loues God, glad will his heart be, ioyfull his ſoule, if he may conuerſe with him at any time, in any place, or in any manner it ſhall pleaſe him to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt himſelfe vnto him. Holy <hi>Dauid</hi> could not better expreſſe the greatneſſe of that fire in his heart, which could not be ſuppreſſed till it brake forth at his mouth, and hee in admiration cried out, <hi>O how amiable are thy Tabernacles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord of Hoſts my ſoule longeth, yea euen fainteth for the Courts of the Lord, my heart and my fleſh crieth out for the liuing God;</hi> and yet in his exile hee might haue had the fruition of Gods fauour; which leſt wee thinke hee did not conceiue, hee explaines his meaning to be this, that his affections were fixed vpon the ordinances of God, and therefore preferring the very Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:131928:42"/>and Swallow before himſelfe, as linked to the Lord in a ſurer bond of loue, addeth, <hi>Yea the Sparrow hath found a houſe, and the Swallow a neſt for her ſelfe, where ſhe may lay her young, euen thine Altars, O Lord of Hoſts, my King and my God;</hi> and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them bleſſed, not as though hee were accurſed, for how ſhould he be but bleſſed who hath the Lord for <hi>his King and his God?</hi> but herein he holdeth them more bleſſed than himſelfe, who dwelt in the Lords houſe, from which hee was exiled, and where the people of the Lord were made partakers of his will, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his Worſhip. And leſt we ſhould thinke that this loue of <hi>Dauid</hi> was only in the time of his baniſhment, thus fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent to the place where the Lord in his ordinances did manifeſt his preſence, when he might, and did ſerue the Lord free from all impediments, and deliuered from the hands of <hi>Saul,</hi> pleading in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pſalme his owne integrity, in reſpect of his fauourable dealing with <hi>Saul,</hi> thinkes that his innocency, his confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:131928:43"/>in truſting vpon God, his keeping the affections and inward motions of his heart pure, his abſtaining from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compencing euill for euill, in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Gods louing kindneſſe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, his ſhunning and hating vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly aſſemblies and perſons, his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing with pure minde and holy conuerſation (as before ſtill) to ſeeke his God; though theſe were excellent ſignes of a good and godly heart, hee thinkes all theſe nothing vnleſſe his loue which he continually had to Gods houſe be added: <hi>Lord</hi> (ſaies he, beſides all the reſt) <hi>I haue conſtantly loued the habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy houſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.8.</note> 
               <hi>and the place where thine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour dwelleth.</hi> And as hee loued Gods <hi>houſe,</hi> and all religious duties there exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, ſo before and aboue the reſt in Gods <hi>Word</hi> was he moſt delighted, it had not the meaneſt but the chiefeſt place in his heart, not the feweſt but the moſt of his affections ſet vpon it, it was his delight, his ioy, his ſtaffe, his ſtay, his reſt, his loue, as in the 119.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:131928:43"/>Pſalme, euery where appeareth. Hee that is affamiſhed, receiues not meat with more gladneſſe than <hi>Ieremy</hi> did the Word of God:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 15.16.</note> it was the <hi>ioy and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycing of his heart.</hi> Come wee now to <hi>Prayer.</hi> Oh the loue of the godly to this exerciſe! Some haue prayed often in the day, as <hi>Daniel;</hi> ſome by prayer haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented the morning watch: to pray night and day was to ſome delightſom, as to <hi>Dauid:</hi> ſome haue neglected no occaſion that was offered, as <hi>Paul.</hi> It was the vſuall practiſe of our Sauiour, hee that needed leaſt prayed moſt, teaching vs by his own patterne what we ſhould practiſe: no ſooner had he ceaſed preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but he fell to praying, hee prayed in the Mountaine, in the Garden, in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, at all times, he prayed on the Croſſe when he was ſuffering. Now for the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, in them wee behold his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in them we partake of his body, and communicate of his bloud, by them our faith is confirmed, our ſoules ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and our conſciences quieted; with
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:131928:44"/>euery of which, what Chriſtian is not delighted? Delighted with them were they in the Apoſtles times, who at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry meeting did breake their bread with <hi>gladneſſe of heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.</note> And as for meditation, by it we ſee God in his Word, behold him in his workes, looke vpon him though in the higheſt Heauens, by it is preſented to our eyes his Maieſty to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect vs that wee grow not proud; his Iuſtice to feare vs that we bee not wanton, his mercy to comfort vs that we doe not faint, his wiſdome to direct vs that we doe not erre, and his power to defend vs that we do not doubt: By Meditation is manifeſted before the eyes of our mind, the greatneſſe of Chriſts ſuffrings, his ſorrowing heart, his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy ſoule, his bleeding hands and feet, his pierced ſide, his wounded heart, and whatſoeuer elſe he endured for our miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeds, in which the Saints of God haue beene much exerciſed, and that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their loue vnto it. Thus doth our loue of God breede in vs a deſire of ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:131928:44"/>in thoſe exerciſes where God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents himſelfe if they may be had; if not, a ſeeking them according to his will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things in the world. The Spouſe of Chriſt, the Church of God, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Chriſtian ſoule ſaith of Chriſt; I <hi>deſire to ſit vnder his ſhadow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5.</note> 
               <hi>and I am ſicke of loue;</hi> that is, I faint if I want that fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip with Chriſt my head which I ſo much deſire, according to his will as he hath appointed to aſſociat himſelfe with me in his Word, Prayers, Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Meditation. Let this be the tryall of the truth of our loue: Are we as Beares drawne to the ſtake to theſe ordinances? Is the Word to vs as a bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den? Looke we vpon the Lords Table with contempt, as though ſome home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fare were offered? neglect wee pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers? meditate we neuer? wee haue no teſtimony of our loue to God: for our care, and reuerence, and reſpect to the meanes, are the emblemes of our affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to, and the demonſtrations of our delight in his Maieſty, who preſents
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:131928:45"/>himſelfe in his ordinances. True loue begetting a deſire of communion, which is alwaies ſeconded with a likenes of affection, at the leaſt hating what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he abhorreth, and louing that in whatſoeuer he delighteth. Now he (to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in three things eſpecially) loueth, Firſt, the <hi>honour of his name,</hi> Secondly, the <hi>obedience of his will;</hi> and thirdly, the <hi>proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his Church:</hi> and on the contrary, holds in deteſtation thoſe that <hi>dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate from his glory, diſobey his ſtatutes, and hinder either the flouriſhing of his Church, or the furthering of his Saints in their temporall or eternall good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the firſt, his name and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of it, how hee doth priſe it, better cannot I decipher than from his owne mouth, who when he would preſerue it as his owne peculiar, proclaimes it as in the eares of all, <hi>That he will giue his glory to no other:</hi> and leſt any might encroach vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his right, the better to detaine it, and the more to deter them from attempting it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note> hee affirmeth, <hi>That he is a iealous God,</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:131928:45"/>which word is (though but one word yet) as forcible as all the Arguments In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention can afford (if it be duely weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) and more perſwaſiue than all the flouriſhes Rhetorike can yeeld (if it bee truly viewed) to proue and paint out his delight in his glory and loue to his name: for all griefes are either to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed with ſenſible perſwaſions, or to be cured with wholſome counſell, or to be releeued with bountiful gifts, or by tract of time to be worne out, <hi>Iealouſie</hi> only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. In that then he alledgeth his Iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, he intimates that Prayers <hi>cannot</hi> preuaile againſt his diſpleaſure, ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <hi>ſhall not</hi> expiate that ſinne, time <hi>will not</hi> wipe out that blot caſt vpon his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Hee therefore that loueth the Lord will be grieued at the ſoule to ſee and heare the name of God diſhonoured, his worſhip deſpiſed, his truth reuiled, his religion ſcorned, and the profeſſion of his Goſpell neglected. He who willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly endureth his friends reproach, is a lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louer. He who patiently putteth vp the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:131928:46"/>diſgrace of his captaine, is either a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faint or a deboſht ſouldier. He who careleſly paſſeth by the contempt of his Creator, is through Satans cunning an helliſh and deformed creature. <hi>Moſes</hi> in his owne matters is the mirrour of <hi>meekeneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 12.3.</note> but if the people in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence practiſe idolatry, oh how doth vexation enuiron his breſt, wrath wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken his memory, and anger confound all the faculties of his ſoule! What though the Tables of ſtone were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the Lords owne finger, his hands cannot hold them! Cunning workmanſhip is not weighed, Charity is not regarded, if pietie ſuffer diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Their Idoll God ſhall be (becauſe a <hi>Calfe</hi>) conſumed in <hi>the fire,</hi> grinded to <hi>powder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.19.</note> throwne into <hi>the water,</hi> and the idolaters pallates be ſeaſoned, their <hi>bowels</hi> reliſht with that ſweetneſſe which aſhes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupted water can afford. Doth <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhakeh</hi> blaſpheme the liuing Lord? How will <hi>Eliakin and Shebnah</hi> expreſſe the loue to their God,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.48.</note> their loathing of that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyaltie!
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:131928:46"/>their bodies ſhall not continue couered, when his name is cloathed with diſhonour; their garments ſhall not remaine vntattered, when his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was rent with ſo great diſgrace.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.136.</note> 
               <hi>Dauids eies</hi> (in conſideration of the great diſhonour caſt vpon Gods name, through common iniquity) <hi>guſhed out riuers of waters.</hi> To expreſſe the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his griefe, it is ſaid they <hi>guſhed out.</hi> To manifeſt the multitude of his ſorrowes, they are called <hi>riuers of teares,</hi> and all was becauſe <hi>men kept not his law.</hi> Hereby demonſtrating his loue vnto God, by that griefe which he had for the diſhonouring of his name. And truly; for they that are <hi>ſealed to ſaluation doe mourne and cry for all the abhominations that bee done in the midſt of the places where they liue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 9.4.</note> Is there ſuch a miſt drawne ouer our eies that we ſet not, ſuch a thicke cloud ouer our vnderſtanding we marke not, ſuch a caule ouer our conſciences wee feele not, either in ourſelues or others, the abhominable blaſphemies of his
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:131928:47"/>name, the horrible contempts of his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, wherein he is ſo much delighted? how can we loue him? Loue begetting a likeneſſe of affection, not only to his name, but his <hi>Will</hi> alſo; the obeying whereof is the badge of our true affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: whence it is that the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> cals vpon all that are Saints, to this duty, <hi>Yee that loue the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.10.</note> 
               <hi>hate the thing that is euill;</hi> ſeeing he deteſts it, ye may not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it: and our Sauiour Chriſt who can beſt deſcribe his owne diſciple, though he gaue often loue as his liuerie, yet he will not haue them ignorant of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible ſigne whereby the truth of the liuery is diſcerned,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.15.</note> 
               <hi>If ye loue me keepe my commandements.</hi> Oh that we had hearts ſo enflamed, that with him who was a man after Gods owne heart, in the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our defects euery one would crie out,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 129.</note> 
               <hi>Oh that my waies were ſo directed that I might keepe thy Statutes,</hi> and the palpable perceiuing our failing in not doing the things we ſhould, nay thoſe we would, cauſe vs cry out with him who was a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:131928:47"/>choſen veſſell; <hi>Wretched man that I am,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death!</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.14.</note> and iuſtly plead with <hi>Nehemiah</hi> and <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechiah our goodneſſe and integritie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 38.3.</note> then might our ſoules repoſe themſelues in the ſweet bed of peace, aſſured of our vnfained loue to God. But is the pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted puddle of iniquitie our bathes, the actions of vngodlineſſe our recreations, the aſſemblies of the wicked our choiſeſt company? Is ſinne our ſureſt ſtay, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked counſells our beſt guides, helliſh drugs our wholeſomeſt Phyſicke, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans delights our ſweeteſt potions? Are we ſo farre from hating, that we delight in couetouſneſſe, pride, malice, profana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Is that moſt reſpected which God leaſt regardeth, or that contemned which he commendeth, or that diſobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed which he enioyneth? that heart and loue towards God is in a dangerous conſumption. Poore loue is that will forſake nothing at Gods prohibiting, nor reforme any thing at his perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, nor performe any thing at his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyning.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:131928:48"/>Can a woman proſtitute her body to a varlet, and yet truly ſay ſhe lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth her husband, or a childe pleade his loue to his Parents while he is vnduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or any call himſelfe, a friend, a member, a ſonne, or daughter of the Lord, diſobeying his will and acting the workes of the deuill? May the heart of a Saint neuer conceit it! for true loue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets a likeneſſe of affection to his name and will: yet if there it ſtoppeth, it were like a ſtrange affectioned wife or friend, who can bee well content, the one to maintaine her husbands credit, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his friends eſtimation, and both em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace his profitable counſels, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his pleaſure, becauſe either their owne dignity and good is continued, or diſtaſte and diſquiet preuented, but can leaſt endure that childe in whom ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares moſt the fathers image, or that friend who is moſt reſpected; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ſoule whoſe loue is wholly fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon the Lord, will loue his Church, which is his vineyard planted by his
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:131928:48"/>owne right hand, garded by his Angels, guided by his wiſdome, the flouriſhing whereof he greatly affecteth, and they who loue him are delighted in it, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ioyntly or ſeuerally conſidered. In euery particular member of it loue wee the graces that appeare in them? loue we them for the graces, which are ſignes and teſtimonies of Gods fauour to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them? We can haue no better te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, no better token of our loue to God; no ſurer marke of our ſaluation: for if we loue him, who by his eternall ſpirit <hi>did beget</hi> them to be heires of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 3.14.</note> we cannot but <hi>loue them who are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten,</hi> and are children of grace, a ſigne not to bee neglected: for hereby wee know that <hi>we</hi> are <hi>tranſlated from death to life becauſe we loue the brethren.</hi>
               <note place="margin">5.13.</note> Is thy af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection rather leſſened, then encreaſed, to a <hi>Chriſtian becauſe he is a Chriſtian?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.</note> Doth his loue to the word, his delight in good workes, his diſtaſte of wickedneſſe, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitter thy minde againſt him? Can he loue the father, who loathes the dutiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:131928:49"/>of the ſonne, or honour the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, who harbours diſlike of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects loyaltie? Chriſt will proclaime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, howſoeuer they ſoothe now themſelues, at that great day, in that they loued not <hi>his little ones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.42.</note> they had no delight in him. For the Church ioyntly: is it ioy to thy ſoule, to heare, improue, the proſperity of it, to perceiue and procure the propagation of the Goſpell in it? And doſt thou with <hi>Paul</hi> in the midſt of thy bonds and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, for ioy forget the ſorrowes of thy afflictions, at the report of Chriſt and his Goſpels proceeding? then art thou with the Lord alike affectioned. Contrarily, art thou with <hi>Nehemiah</hi> for thy outward ſtate, without all cauſe of ſorrowing, liuing in ſoft rayment and faring deliciouſly, in <hi>Artaxerxes Court,</hi> yet art in <hi>countenance ſad?</hi> art thou not ſicke, yet weepes and mournes when thou <hi>heareſt of the diſtreſſe of Ieruſalem,</hi> or with <hi>Vriah, wilt thou lodge with the kings ſeruants and not goe downe to thine owne houſe, becauſe
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:131928:49"/>the Arke of the Lord is in hazard?</hi> Art thou ſtrooke as the <hi>wife of Phinees with ſorrow, with a deadly ſorrow, hearing the glory to bee departed from Iſrael?</hi> Doſt thou in a word <hi>Preferre Ieruſalem to thy chiefeſt ioy?</hi> The Lord will not forget thy loue, when he will neglect thoſe who are ſo glued to the profits and pleaſures of this life, that ſo they may haue the fleſh-pots of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> and the plenty of <hi>Sodome,</hi> care not which way Religion goeth, harken leſſe to the well-fare of the Church then to thoſe things which are done in a ſtrange Land They ſolemniſe the feaſts of <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> as the greateſt godhead, preſent their offrings and enrich the Altar of <hi>Aeſcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius</hi> as a Diety. They honour <hi>Pluto</hi> as a diuine power, and ſo they may liue in any aire, can turne to any Religion, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meditating on Gods mercy which would moue a deſire in them to delight in, and be affected with, what he <hi>loueth,</hi> nor pondering his Iuſtice which would beget a feare of his Maieſty, as it did the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> as of himſelfe he teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth:
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:131928:50"/>
               <hi>My fleſh trembleth for feare of thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.120.</note> 
               <hi>and I am afraid of thy iudgements.</hi> Doth <hi>Dauid</hi> (deepely intereſted in the Lords euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting loue by Couenant neuer to bee cancelled) tremble? and are we, loded with ſinne, lulled in the Cradle of ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidity? Is he, a man after Gods owne heart, afraid of his iudgements? and are not we, branded with impiety, abaſhed at the contemplation and ſight of his Iuſtice?</p>
            <p>Oh feare the Lord all yee his Saints, for your ſoules, obſeruing Iuſtice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the banquetting houſe of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinity. Get the feare of the Lord, it is a faithfull <hi>Porter.</hi> Your ſoules are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther already ſicke or ſubiect to diſeaſes, ſeeke for the feare of the Lord, it is a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Phyſician.</hi> Your ſoules are as Ships in danger to be toſſed in tempeſtuous ſeas, be faſtned to the feare of the Lord, it is an aſſured <hi>Anchor.</hi> Haue you entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned diſloyall thoughts or attempted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rebellious enterpriſe, and are afraid to approach the Throne of grace to
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:131928:50"/>pleade your pardon? Call for the feare of God, it is a powerfull <hi>Aduocate.</hi> Are you trauelling in the Wilderneſſe of this world, repleniſhed with many by-paths, doubtfull which way to take? Take for your companion the feare of the Lord, it is a faithfull <hi>Counſellour.</hi> Are you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uironed in the midſt of many enemies? guard you with the feare of the Lord, it is a carefull <hi>Centinell.</hi> Haue you entred the danger of the battell? fight vnder the banner of the feare of the Lord, it is a couragious <hi>Captaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a faithfull <hi>Porter,</hi> not admitting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny rebellious ſuggeſtion, nor, though entertaining vnawares, ſuffring to abide any heauen-diſtaſting motion in the ſoule, the Lords Palace: for if <hi>Ioſeph</hi> be tempted, this either diuerts the attempt, repels the aſſault, and makes him cry out, <hi>How can I do this, and offend my God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 33.9.</note> or elſe ſubuerts the plot and expels the act; rather leauing the looſeneſſe of the thoughts, then loading the conſcience with the weight of ſinne, rather endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:131928:51"/>the loſſe of a ragged motion, then to defile the manſion of a heauenly mind: yet ſets open, wide open, the doore of the heart to euery gueſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Lord delighteth, kindly entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning euery grace which hee affecteth, cheerefully welcomming euery good thing, the preſence whereof he deſireth. Is <hi>mercy</hi> and compaſſion more <hi>pleaſing then ſacrifice?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Neb.</hi> 5.1.5. <hi>Iob.</hi> 6.14.</note> The <hi>feare of the Lord firſt</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites it.
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.9.</note> Is <hi>ſingleneſſe of heart the delight of God,</hi> the deſire of man? The feare of God admits it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 187.11.</note> Is <hi>waiting</hi> vpon the Lords <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>depending</hi> on his pleaſure, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by him, reſpected of him? The feare of the Lord brings it in his hand to the banquet. By him who feareth the Lord,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.22.</note> 
               <hi>Obedience</hi> is as readily ſaluted as the ſun-ſhine day after ſhowers in the time of Harueſt; Repentance as louingly embraced as the prodigall Sonne by the commiſerating father;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.1.</note> 
               <hi>Inſtructions as ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully receiued</hi> as Chriſt by <hi>Zacheus.</hi> Thus is it a faithfull Porter.</p>
            <p>It is no leſſe a skilfull <hi>Phyſician:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eeclus.</hi> 1.26.</note> either
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:131928:51"/>
               <hi>purging corrupt humors and reſtoring health,</hi> or <hi>preuenting ſickneſſe and preſeruing life.</hi> It <hi>purgeth</hi> corruption, not ſuffring ſinne to neſtle it ſelfe in the ſoule, or iniquity to lodge as a gueſt in the heart; but ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to it as the Lord to <hi>Ahab, Indeed haſt thou killed and alſo got poſſeſsion?</hi> And as intruding &amp; pernicious Inhabitants to ſpirituall graces, driueth them out with violence. It <hi>preuenteth</hi> impiety towards God, iniquity towards man, and ſo continueth a bleſſed life in a wretched world: whence it is that <hi>Moſes</hi> who <hi>was faithfull in all Gods houſe,</hi> ſaith, that God came to proue the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that his <hi>feare might be before them that they might not ſinne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.20.</note> Let then the feare of God bee before our eyes, preſented to our minds, ſinne, which is as ſubtile as the Serpent cannot deceiue vs; ſinne though it put on the ſhape of ſanctity, ſhall not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumuent vs; ſinne though it promiſe much affected pleaſure, much followed profit, ſhall not perſwade vs. For ſinnes Stratagems by the feare of God are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:131928:52"/>ſinnes perſwaſions by the feare of God are reiected; ſinnes ſtrongeſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments by the feare of God are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed. Thence it is that by that exact obſeruer the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi> theſe two are ſet together as if they were as inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as <hi>Hypocrates</hi> Twinnes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.5.</note> 
               <hi>ſtanding in ame, and not ſinning,</hi> fearing, and not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, for where feare hath ſeaſed, ſinne cannot be admitted; where feare hath got poſſeſſion, in vaine for ſinne to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend a title. The Lords Palace, the ſoule, ſo furniſhed, is no fit manſion by Satans tenant to be inhabited; the ſpirits tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſo garniſhed, hath no Altar on which ſinnes ſacrifice may bee offered; The bleſſed Redeemer hath there no Table whereat ſinnes ſeruice, though neuer ſo plauſible, can be entertained. Let <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> enioine,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.17.</note> if euill, <hi>feare denies obedience,</hi> and holds his directions to be deuilliſh: Let <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> preſcribe; if wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, his preſcriptions as vnſound Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples are neglected;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.</note> Let <hi>Ioſeph</hi> be entiſed, by the feare of God all entiſements are
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:131928:52"/>preuented,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 14.27.</note> for it is a <hi>Well ſpring of life to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid the ſnares of death,</hi> and not onely to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid death, but euen to <hi>preſerue life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">10.27. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> nay and <hi>encreaſe the dayes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.11.</note> what though the number of your dayes be accompanied with many dangers, and you toſſed with many tempeſts? the feare of God is an aſſured Anchor;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Moral.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>Anchora mentis pondus timoris,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory;</hi> the fire of concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence cannot faſten vpon this affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to conſume it, the waters of tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot enter into this grace to ruſt it, the earthly qualitie of Couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe cannot infect this ſeede to ſpoile it, nor the contagion of vaine-glory and falſe opinion toſſe this gift of the ſpirit to ouerthrow it. Though the raine of miſeries ſhowre vpon the ſoule, though the floud of temptation come againſt the heart, though the wind of diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions blow vpon the mind, and all theſe with vnited forces beat vpon the whole man; yet where the feare of the Lord is, thoſe ſhowres finde a good ſoile to ſucke them vp, thoſe flouds meete
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:131928:53"/>with great rampires to repell their fury, thoſe winds finde ſufficient ſtrength to reſiſt their rage;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 19.23.</note> ſo as that man <hi>conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues ſafe,</hi> and falls not, being built vpon the feare of God as vpon a rock.</p>
            <p>But be it, the violence of theſe ſtormes haue captiued your thoughts, and made you yeeld to that which hath diſpleaſed your God, ſo that you dare not approach his preſence: this feare is a powerfull <hi>Aduocate.</hi> Though ſinne made <hi>Adam</hi> hide himſelfe from him, whoſe face he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to ſee for ſhame: though murder cauſed <hi>Caine</hi> to flye from the Lord, to whoſe preſence he durſt not approach: though Trechery compelled <hi>Iudas</hi> vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently to haſten the end of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed daies, as hopeleſſe of any pardon, as he was hapleſſe in that impiety, and perſwaded him to flye from the ſight of angry Heauen (as he thought) by quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe of the horror of his owne heart; yet the feare of God, as a well-tongued Orator, perſwades ſo pithily; as a ſound Logitian, argues ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundly;
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:131928:53"/>as a Iudges fauorite, preuailes ſo powerfully; that all ſhowers of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like are ceaſed, all clouds of doubts are diſperſed, and all tempeſts of diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents are ended; and he who is ſeazed in this tenure, enioyeth and is admitted this priuiledge, to be <hi>accepted of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 10.35.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Are you yet againe doubtfull to bee <hi>drawne away</hi> to error before your Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney bee ended,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.28.</note> and feare vncertaine wandering? no better Cumrade can bee had than this <hi>Counſeller,</hi> for it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth the Minde, directeth thy Manners. Would you plucke the fruits of the tree of knowledge? this feare giueth entrance to it. Would you make vſe of <hi>knowledge</hi> in due practiſe? This <hi>feare is the beginning of Wiſdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10.</note> 
               <hi>which is to keepe the Commandements.</hi> Whoſoeuer is poſſeſſor of this grace, is ſo gracious in the eies of the Lord, that the Lord himſelfe will become his <hi>teacher</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rector, not <hi>in the way</hi> which the world,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.12.</note> nor that wherein his owne naturall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption delighteth, but that <hi>whereof hee
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:131928:54"/>himſelfe</hi> who cannot erre nor be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, <hi>maketh a choiſe.</hi> Such a ſweet Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion is this Counſeller, and ſuch a faithfull Counſeller is this Companion, that through all the tearing bryers, all the pricking thornes, all the alluring fruits, all the dangerous and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pathes, all the cares, pleaſures, and incumbrances of this world, it findes out a path,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Frou.</hi> 19.23.</note> chalkes out a way, and <hi>leades</hi> vs ſafely <hi>vnto Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Be it while we are trauelling we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet with the beaſts of the forreſt, enuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with many oppoſitions, yet ſubiect to ſecuritie. The feare of God is a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Centinell</hi> to giue notice of our dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. A <hi>Centinell</hi> it is, watching the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, diſcouering the plots of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: for Satan labours firſt of all to put out the eie of feare, well knowing the whole army remaineth ſure, though ſecurely ſleeping, while the Centinell is vnſlaine, and ſo farre prevaileth he, as this grace becomes his Captiue, aſſuring himſelfe the day when this is conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:131928:54"/>For when he had dimmed the eie of feare in <hi>Eue,</hi> ſhe became to read, as if it had beene a larger Character than it was, and with her tongue to ſpeake as Satans ſlaue in his mincing language, <hi>leſt peraduenture ye die:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.</note> whereupon the Serpent takes occaſion, and luls, as with <hi>Mercuries</hi> enchanting rod, by his char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſpeech, each corner of her minde aſleepe, <hi>ye ſhall not die at all:</hi> then ſhewed her the excellency of it; whereupon ſhe gazed: happy had ſhe, happy had wee beene, if ſhee had not glanced at that Tree,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.6.</note> and <hi>perceiued that the tree was good for foode, and that it was pleaſant to the eies, and a Tree to be deſired to make one wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>ſhe tooke and eat.</hi> Thus was it quite put out, and ſhe forgat God who gaue her this for her Centinell, which duly watched, truly warned her of her dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but ſhe treacherouſly gaue way to the ſuggeſtion of the Serpent, and ſo became a ſlaue, which otherwiſe had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer beene; for if ſhe had preſerued it liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhe had liued happily, and we holily;
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:131928:55"/>for ſo long as it watcheth, Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are diſcerned and auoided, ſinnes vglineſſe ſeene and abhorred, dangers deſcried and preuented. For feare being oppoſed, calleth vp care, care enformeth reaſon, reaſon miniſtreth the meanes of ſafety, and preſcribeth reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>And thus the feare of God hauing ſounded the Alarum, called vp all the faculties of the ſoule to the fight, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haues it ſelfe as a generous <hi>Captaine</hi> which <hi>Combats couragiouſly, Conquers victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly,</hi> and <hi>Crownes her aſsiſtants richly. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats couragiouſly,</hi> for what a conflict was in <hi>Ioſephs</hi> iudgement? What a combat in the mindes of the <hi>Aegyptian midwiues?</hi> What battels in the thoughts, what hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror-threatning Cannon-ſhot thundred in the eares of <hi>Iob? Ioſephs</hi> feare to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe his God, lothneſſe to wrong his Maſter, vnwillingneſſe to diſcontent his Miſtris, grapled furiouſly together: Her preſent authority, her future amity, her continuall eminency: His larger pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, higher place, conſtant honour, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:131928:55"/>his corruption to plead in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: Why <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> doſt thou demurre? Thou art a bondſlaue, ſhee a beautifull creature; thou her ſeruant, ſhe thy Lady: Thou a ſtranger, might to thine owne content, bragge of the abuſe of her beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yet ſhe locks her reputation in the Casket of thy ſecrecy. How many haue made knowne their ſhamefull deſires, yet haue heard to their ſhame ſerious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nials? Yet moues ſhe the ſuit before it be granted, nay grants the ſuit before it be moued. How many would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count themſelues happy in long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance to enioy onely one accepting countenance? Shee giues thee her face and her fauour too. How many haue laid long ſiege to beauties fortreſſe, and haue failed? Shee parlees, not to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a peace and be gone, but before the aſſault, to yeeld her ſelfe to thy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Doth diſcouery hinder thee? why who is heere but you two,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.</note> 
               <hi>euery one elſe of the houſhold</hi> being imployed <hi>abroadin</hi> their ſeuerall buſineſſes. Can any blab ſaue
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:131928:56"/>thy ſelfe? And for her, thy conſtancy, <hi>Putiphars</hi> fury, her owne infamy, tie the ſtrings of her tongue that ſhee cannot tell. Preuent, vnwiſe man preuent, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured repentance; nay procure thy cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine good. If thou ſhouldſt deſpiſe her, ſhe will deſpight thee; if thou faile to giue her thy heart, thou ſhalt feele the greatneſſe of her hate. Her houſe is now thy harbour, her husband thy fauourer, ſhee will bee thy continuall friend: If thou feareſt any hurt, repaire to her and preſume of her helpe; ſhee can ſpeede, when thou maieſt not ſpeake. If thou ſhew vnkindneſſe, ſhe for ſauing her owne credit may accuſe thee, and who will acquit thee? thou ſhalt be condemned, and ſhee cleared. Thy brow ſhall beare the brand of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominie for euer, ſeeing euery one will be as ready to maintaine as entertaine any miſreport of a ſtranger. Whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the feare of the Lord ſeemed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply: Pauſe a little <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> haſte makes waſte, let not a Creature cauſe thee to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:131928:56"/>forget thy Creator. Is ſhe beautifull? who did giue it? not thy God? why did he giue it? for thee to abuſe it? canſt thou embrace her motion, and not wrong thy maſter, who hath caſt all his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold affaires vpon thy fidelity? Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, oh conſider it well; the more he truſts thee, the more monſtrous thy fault if thou be faithleſſe. He hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained thee into houſe, when thou wantedſt harbour, hee hath aduanced thee from a ſlaue to be a ſeruant, from a ſeruant to a Steward, from a Steward to a Ruler. He in his houſe ſees nothing but by thine eies, heares nothing ſaue what thou reporteſt, acts nothing but ſubſcribed by thine hand, preſcribes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, vnleſſe thou direct. Hath he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured thee to diſhonour him? hath he diſplaied the banner of his curteſie to grace thee, and wilt thou obſcure his dignity with the clouds of diſgrace and diſcontent? Is thy affection ſo vnſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? are thy luſts ſo vnlimited? cannot much, nay, the moſt ſatisfie, but thou
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:131928:57"/>muſt haue thy deſire in all? Remember the firſt Creation: haſt thou forgot <hi>Adam?</hi> Doſt thou not call to minde <hi>Eue?</hi> One, onely one Tree was reſerued, and that muſt be taſted: But that taſte did ſo much diſtaſte the Lord, and load their conſciences with confuſion, that being ſubiects of miſery, they could neither ſee nor ſeeke for mercy: All men ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row for that ſinne,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.22.</note> all <hi>Creatures</hi> yet <hi>grone</hi> through that tranſgreſſion: beſides, to her greatneſſe oppoſe Gods graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to her fauours the Lords fury. Thou waſt a bondſlaue, who brought thee to this liberty? not thy God? thou waſt a ſtranger, who did prouide thus for thee? not thy God? Thou waſt a ſeruant, who raiſed thee to bee a Ruler? not thy God? how dareſt thou then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe his mercy with this miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, require his loue with ſuch diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, anſwer his power with ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſeneſſe! canſt thou doubt of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, which haſt ſuch tryall of his protection, or wilt thou diſtruſt his care
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:131928:57"/>for thee, hauing ſuch experience of his comforts? Be it that the darkneſſe of the night ſhould hide thee, or the fact remaine perpetually buried in the graue where all things are forgotten, or if diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, ſo ſalued that it ſhall be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as a thing vnacted, yet the Lords eye euer watcheth, and is of ſo piercing a power that it entreth into all ſecrets, and diſcouers euery moſt hidden deuice, and though all the world haue let it ſlip, yet thine owne conſcience will neuer ſleepe; that thy God will waken if it chance to ſlumber. What are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights here? <hi>Syrenes</hi> either ſtriuing to ſinke vs, or to ſucke our bloud. What are great ones faucurs? fading flowers, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten withered ere they can bee crop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. What can ſhe doe? Is not all <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> deriued from and belonging to God? Floweth not all <hi>pitty and compaſsion</hi> from him as from the proper fountaine?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.11.12.</note> Can man or Angell preuaile if God ſeeke to preuent them, or will they pitty if he ſeeme to prohibit? Keepe then the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:131928:58"/>of that God, at whoſe frowne the Mountaines ſhake, and on whoſe loue, thou knoweſt, attendeth life.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Pharaohs</hi> commanding the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Midwiues to kill the Iſraelites male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>children,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.16.</note> they might perceiue cruelty to brandiſh his weapon, aggrauating the ſeeming goodneſſe of the fact, extenua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the aſſured greatneſſe of the fault, preſenting <hi>Pharaohs</hi> might and the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents miſery, preſſing the childrens pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition, and their poſterities fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calamity, in theſe or the like imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous termes.</p>
            <p>Are not you <hi>Pharaohs</hi> ſubiects?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.2.</note> you muſt ſubmit. From what Soueraigne doth hee hold his Scepter? by what Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander will he be controuled, or who dare call him to account? if you reſpect your weale, obey his will. His care is your quiet, his coraſiue your calamity, his power your protection; ſeekes he in this any thing but your preſeruation? Aimes he in this at any thing ſaue your good? They ſo greatly multiply, if you
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:131928:58"/>now forbeare, hereafter they may proue too great a burden: little ſprigs if they be not pruned will grow too high; and Nettles if not cut, will ſpread too farre. Cut then the weede while it is in grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and preuent a miſchiefe, leſt you ſigh in ſorrow, through too late repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; If your poſterity in the ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding age feele the plague, haue they not cauſe to condemne your pitty and call it folly, that foſtred ſtings in your owne boſomes? Nature teacheth euery thing to preſerue it ſelfe, and euery creature will prouide for the young ones ſafety. Cut then the thred of theſe Infants liues, for what are their Parents? ſuch as with whom it is abomination for the Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians to eat, and care you ſo much to let them breath, with whom you may not participate in eating bread? Are they not diuers from you in your rites, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to you in your Religion, great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of your gods? and ſhall they liue? Thus had cruelty wounded them and become their Conquerour, if the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:131928:59"/>feare of the Lord with a mild and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpirit, diſtilling mercy and lenity, had not ſoftned their breaſts, and abated the edge of their more than humane fury, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felling theſe ſeeming-ſound poſitions with better grounded Principles; that, the Almighty had indeed transferred with his Attributes and titles his owne dignities and honors vpon earthly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, and curſed is that <hi>ſoule</hi> which <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits</hi> not to them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> either doing what they enioyne, or induring what they inflict: for to reſiſt their Rule, though vniuſtly laid, is iuſtly to procure your ruines; to rebell againſt their will, though wicked, is cauſleſly, at leaſt indiſcreetly and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natly, to worke your owne woes: for you warre againſt Heauens prouidence, and prouoke the higheſt power of whom they are. If then it be good which they bid, yeeld all ſubmiſſiue; if indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, all reſpectiue obedience: and if it be euill which they enioyne, though you muſt <hi>ſhunne the deed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.29.41.</note> yet ſhew your duties and their due, in ſubmitting
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:131928:59"/>your ſelues to ſuffer patiently when they ſhall puniſh. But for theſe Infants, what haue they done? When the Babe is cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the dug, as deſiring to haue the life preſerued, ſhall it be done to death? <hi>Doe as you would be done to.</hi> How com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable is a calme after a tempeſtuous ſtorme, but how great the griefe when the hope is fruſtrate, and expectation fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth! Are the Mothers pangs no ſooner paſt, but will you intercept their ioy, nay renue their ſorrow? <hi>Health is deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after a relapſe hath ſurpriſed.</hi> Thinke how much would be your mourning if you ſaw ſuch murther! Would not griefe gripe your hearts to ſee ſuch cauſe of heauineſſe? They poore ſoules ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected you as helpes, and will you bee the inſtruments of their hurt? Would you not iudge him cruell ſhould lay ſo hard a charge againſt you or yours, and them too bloudy ſhould be Agents in ſuch a butchery? Thinke you to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue your liues by their death, or your poſterity by maſſacres, and to maintaine
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:131928:60"/>your Religion by murder? Hell may indeed reioyce at the cruelty, but the Heauens will reuenge that impious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity and inhumane impiety. Hath their God euen before your eyes redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their wrongs, and releeued their wants, and will he not repay this wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe vpon you and yours? what peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple euer preuailed againſt them, or what policy did euer delude his prouidence? Let your hearts neither harbour, nor your hands execute this vnheard of Murder; and then their God will proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per you in your eſtates, and <hi>make your houſholds like a ſlocke of ſheepe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iob</hi> feared God and ſuffered many ſore bickerings with Satan; Sinne brought in vpon him ſuffrings, Suffrings vſhered ſorrowes, Sorrowes ſurpriſed his ſoule with impatience, which made him a <hi>burden vnto himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 7.20.</note> whereupon begunne a grieuous combat, continued with a dangerous conflict betweene his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, impatience, and the feare of God. Impatience entering the Liſts, brandi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:131928:60"/>theſe weapons with moſt furious courage-danting countenance. See <hi>Iob,</hi> how thy wife which lyeth in thy bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, thy ſecond ſelfe, which ſhould be thy comfort in thy croſſes, is the aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menter of thy calamity; thy children round about thy table, the hope of the continuing of thy name in after ages, are ſwept away as the Spiders web; and for thy friends, will not thy tongue cleaue to the roofe of thy mouth, thine eies be dim to behold them come to viſit thee? How ſtrange is thy miſery inflicted vpon thy body? did euer eye behold the like? Thy ſeeming ſanctitie was aſſured ſin, for haſt thou confirmed him that was falling, and ſtrengthned the knees of the weake? Hath thy tongue dropped ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie into the heauie breſt, and art thou as a man deſpairing of all hope? either thy conſolations to them were the flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes of thy ſpeech, and had no affinitie with thy faith, or thou art inconſtant in thy confidence. It is ſuſpicious that the practiſe of that Phyſician is counterfet
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:131928:61"/>who admits of no ſuch medicines as he hath miniſtred to others. Thou haſt perſwaded others patience in their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities, to lift vp their heads in the middeſt of their heauineſſe, yet now when thou art afflicted thou fretteſt: thou haſt miniſtred to others comforts in their calamities; tribulation hath tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched thee and thou art troubled: thou haſt aduiſed them caſt Anchor during the continuance of their ſtormes; and art thou ſo vnſetled, that with the billow of euery waue thou art toſſed? They muſt account that bleſſing which thou now eſteemeſt a bane, they muſt accept that as a Plaiſter which thou deemeſt a plague, elſe why doſt thou curſe the day of thy birth and the night of thy natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wiſh the doore of thy mothers wombe ſhut, and her breſts by thee ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſucked? It was either euill that thou then exhortedſt, or thou now wicked that doſt not now admit it. Where is thy former righteouſneſſe whereof thou ſo much preſumedſt? Remember I pray
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:131928:61"/>thee, who euer periſhed being an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, or where were the vpright deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? They that plow iniquitie and ſow wickednes, reape the ſame; if thou hadſt beene deuout, thy deuices had not beene ſcattered. Was it not thy conſcience of ſin which ſtopped thy mouth and made thee ſilent? Whence is this that thy words are ſwallowed vp? not from thy ſinne? Whence is it that the venome of the Almighties arrowes drinke vp thy ſpirits? not from thy ſinne? whence is it that the terrors of God fight againſt thee? not from thy ſinne? Thoſe who did in thy proſperitie admire thee, now mocke at thee; they who hate thee open their mouthes vpon thee; thine eies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it, and thou canſt not helpe it; thine eare heares it, and thou canſt not ſhun it; euery ſenſe is ſorrowes ſubiect, and thou canſt not eaſe it. <hi>Death is better than deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> as appeares in <hi>Sampſon:</hi> and nothing more vnpleaſing vnto <hi>Dauid</hi> than vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſſe, yet thy brethren flie from thee, thy acquaintance are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:131928:62"/>to thee, neighbours forſake thee, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliars haue forgotten thee, thy friends for hony giue thee gall, for comforts coraſiues: where before all diligence was yeelded, thy deſires are now denied; where before thy command was anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with all cheerefull readineſſe, thy praiers cannot now preuaile. Thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ſpeede is ſlackneſſe. Nay, is not thy ſoule tormented, that thy wife whoſe willingneſſe ſhould not be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to worke thy eaſe, is afraid to come neere that breath, which ſhe with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light ſometime ſucked? Neither your former faith, nor mutuall loue, nor the remembrance of the children of thine owne body, can either moue her to prouide for thy health, or pittie thy miſhap, but caſting off all care of thy good conſcience towards God, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades thee to blaſpheme him, and die accurſed. Doe not they whoſe fathers thou refuſedſt to ſet with thy flockes mocke thee? doe not the children of fooles and villaines more vilde than
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:131928:62"/>earth, ſpit in thy face, and ſpare not to abhorre and make ſongs of thee? Doth not age neglect, and youth puſh at thee, and all take pleaſure in thy calamitie? How haſt thou offended that God, who caſts not away the vpright! Thou art wicked, elſe would hee take thee by the hand, thy reioycing ſhould not be ſo ſhort, nor thy ioy ſo momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary. Doth he ſtabliſh the poſterity of the righteous, and were not thy children in the midſt of their feaſting ſent to the place of their iniquitie? There is ſome deepe matter in thee: wickedneſſe was ſweet in thy mouth; though it lay hid vnder thy tongue, thou didſt fauour it and wouldſt not forſake it, and therefore thou haſt vomited thy ſubſtance, and thy mounting in excellency is periſhed as thy dung; neither is there hope left for eaſe or remedie. Thou art compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with endleſſe care; no tongue to comfort thee, no hand to helpe thee, no muſicke to delight thine eare and cure the ſting of this Tarantula. Where is
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:131928:63"/>any freedome from byles in thy body, any eaſe in thy bed, any ſolace in thy ſpirit? Painfull nights are appointed thee, and no mitigation of thy miſery in the day. The Almighty, the Almighty hath ſet himſelfe againſt thee, and will not let thee alone till thou ſwallow thy ſpittle; and art thou not as one that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his ſoule in anger? <hi>Better a ſhort life</hi> than ſuch a <hi>lingring death,</hi> and therefore, <hi>curſe God and die.</hi> Vnto which blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my the extremity of his woes had drawne him, if the feare of God had not reſiſting preſerued the fire of faith, and continued the power of patience with theſe perſwaſions: <hi>What haſt thou loſt?</hi> that which was neuer thine when firſt thou ſaweſt the light. And what are Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, Camels, Seruants, Children? did not God giue them vpon condition, that thou ſhouldſt reſigne them? wilt thou deſire to with-hold that which hee will haue, or endeuour to recouer what he did take? haue not ſeruants bin the cauſe of ſorrow to ſome maſters? Children
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:131928:63"/>the occaſion of diſcontent to ſome Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: Riches the ruine of many men: and might not all haue beene ſo to thee? The earth is none of thy peculiar, thou expecteſt thy patrimony in a better place: It is not thy proper right, it is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen into the hands of the wicked, who many times are moſt wealthy. Let it not then grieue thee, that thou art not loaded with the clay of a ſtrange coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, nor adorned with the counterfeit pearles of a forraine people. <hi>High aduance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and great fauours in another nation, are not alwaies ſeconded with good ſucceſſe.</hi> What though thy miſery is not limited with want, but enlarged with many woes, not in miſſing good, but ſuffering griefe? Greater than thy ſelfe haue felt the weight of the Lords hand,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 12.19.21.</note> 
               <hi>for he leadeth Counſellers away ſpoiled, and maketh the Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges fooles: he looſeth the bond of Kings, and girdeth their loynes with a girdle: He leadeth Princes away ſpoiled, and powreth contempt vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; he weakeneth the ſtrength of the mighty and ouerthroweth them.</hi> But howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:131928:64"/>the ſame afflictions arreſt not, the ſame euent at the end attendeth all men: One dieth in his full ſtrength being in all eaſe and proſperity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 21.</note> 
               <hi>his breaſts runne full of milke, and his bones are full of marrow.</hi> And another dieth in the bitterneſſe of his ſoule, and neuer eateth with pleaſure; they ſhall ſleepe both in the duſt, and the wormes ſhall couer them: what plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure hath the former in his proſperity, when the number of his moneths is cut off? may he not be one of thoſe, who is kept vnto the day of deſtruction, and ſhall bee brought forth to the day of wrath? or what diſprofit hath the latter either in <hi>life</hi> or <hi>death?</hi> In <hi>life,</hi> doth not his miſeries lift vp his minde to God, open his eare to diſcipline, and draw his feet from iniquitie?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job</hi> 28.</note> 
               <hi>Iron is taken out of the duſt, and Braſſe is moulten out of the ſtone: out of the ſame earth commeth bread, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it as it were is fire turned vp.</hi> From the duſt of miſery proceedeth the ſtrength of affiance, and from the ſtone of cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie commeth contrition: from affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:131928:64"/>is fetched the bread of inſtruction, and vnder them as it were is turned vp the fire of deuotion. Be it that thy tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations be tedious, thou haſt ſinned and thou muſt ſuffer: yet thy God who ſeemeth to ſet himſelfe againſt thee, is <hi>mans preſeruer,</hi> will he deſtroy the <hi>worke of his owne hands,</hi> which he loueth, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face that image which he affecteth? Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint thy ſelfe with him and make peace, and thereby thou ſhalt haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 9.15.</note> though thy <hi>righteouſneſſe were as a robe vpon thee,</hi> yet thy <hi>ſafeſt courſe were to ſupplicate his grace.</hi> Be thou patient, and hee will ſpeake peace vnto thy ſoule; gird vp thy loines like a man, looke on his creatures, and obſerue his power, which by euery thing is obeyed; note his wiſdome, whereby euery thing is diſpoſed: <hi>He that ſhut vp the ſea with doores,</hi>
               <note place="margin">38.8.</note> can aſwell ſtop thy ſorrowes. Hee that commandeth the morning light can as ſuddenly ſparkle the beames of his bounty vpon thee.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> He <hi>putteth an end</hi> and <hi>ſetteth a bound to darkneſſe and the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:131928:65"/>of death:</hi> and cannot he chaine thy calamity, and finiſh thy perplexities? Though <hi>he kill thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">13.15.</note> 
               <hi>yet truſt in him and call vpon him.</hi> What is it he cannot doe; or what meanes is vnknowne vnto him? Let death ſeaſe vpon thee; if thou relieſt on him, thou ſhalt liue, and therefore wait: thy daies may end in proſperity; and thy yeares in pleaſure. <hi>In death:</hi> Art not thou perſwaded <hi>that thy redeemer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and ſhall ſtand the laſt on earth, and that thou ſhalt behold him, not with other but with theſe thine eies?</hi> behold him, not as an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Iudge to condemne, but a louing Sauiour to abſolue thee: behold him not as a reuenger of thy ſinnes, but as a Redeemer of thy ſoule.</p>
            <p>Thus doth the feare of God enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine for vs the combat, and fight cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly; yet this were not ſo comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, if it did not <hi>Conquer</hi> victoriouſly; but now vpon the conflict followeth the conqueſt. For did not this ſword murder the bloudy command of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roh,</hi> in the hearts of the Aegyptian Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiues?
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:131928:65"/>did not this ſtone flying from the heart of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſtrike ſinne on the head, ſo that it ſunke downe groueling vpon the ground neuer to reuiue againe? Many and ſore were the skirmiſhes which <hi>Iob</hi> had with Satan, impatience, and his affliction, but you haue heard his end; the Serpents head was broken, Impatiencies ſwelling bulke was burſt, and outward afflictions as the Clouds with the Sunnes preſence diſperſed, and he became the maſter of the field, which feared God. Though then the conflict be cruell, they that feare the Lord may be conſtant; though the battell be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, they may be comforted, for they are <hi>not forſaken, but are deliuered,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.18.</note> and the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory is certaine to be theirs; for it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers victoriouſly, and richly crownes both them and theirs, opening a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure wherein nothing which may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the eye, pleaſe the taſte, delight the ſmell, enrich the ſoule, bleſſe the eſtate, is wanting.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ecclus.</hi> 40.27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is a <hi>Garden</hi> repleniſhed with varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:131928:66"/>of Gods mercies to delight the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſmell of our apprehenſion; it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companies vs to the <hi>Temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.7.</note> which is filled with Gods glorious preſence, to content the eies of our vnderſtanding; It pleaſeth the pallat of our affections,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7, 8.</note> with the ſweet Nectar of his graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; It is a Sunne to warme our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nummed will in the practiſe of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and a fire to enflame our zeales in contemplation of holineſſe; It brings with it a comfortable vſe of worldly bleſſings,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 12.27.</note> for many <hi>hunt</hi> after worldly profit, but haue it not, haue it, but it helps not; they take great paines and attaine their expectation, but put their gaines in <hi>broken bags.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 6.2.</note> The <hi>couetous</hi> man keeps them ſo ſafely, as he dares not touch them; the Prodigall ſpends them ſo lauiſhly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 15.</note> that hee comes to want them; many poſſeſſe them comfortably to their worldly content, as the <hi>rich man in Saint Luke,</hi> but doe not bleſſedly either poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe or vſe them, only hee that feareth God obtaines them, poſſeſſeth them,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:131928:66"/>ſpends them, ſpares them, vſeth them bleſſedly; for nothing is <hi>wanting to him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>nothing that is good;</hi> whatſoeuer may hurt his hope or hinder his confidence, coole his zeale or freeze his forwardneſſe, may be wanting; but nothing that may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his faith or inflame his obedience ſhall be miſſing.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128.2.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall</hi> labour and <hi>eat the labour of his hands,</hi> he <hi>ſhall be bleſſed</hi> and <hi>it ſhall be well with him;</hi> Hee openeth his hand and giueth to him <hi>that needeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.5.</note> 
               <hi>and yet expendeth with iudgement.</hi> Howſoeuer it goes with the wicked in life or death, yet I know, ſaies <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 8.12.</note> that <hi>it ſhall bee well with them that feare the Lord and doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence before him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.18, 19.</note> For <hi>his eyes are on them to deliuer their ſoule from death, and preſerue them in the time of dearth.</hi> And that wee may take notice of the abundance of their wealth, the greatneſſe of their worth, the feare of God is compared to a <hi>Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring,</hi> an euer-flowing Fountaine,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro</hi> 14.27.</note> ſo as though the channels decay and be dried vp, this euer yeeldeth ſufficient ſupply of knowledge to confirme the mind, of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:131928:67"/>direction to conforme the manners, of wiſdome to informe our contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of caution to reforme our actions. The waies of God are vnſearchable, the myſteries of godlineſſe incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet to him that feareth God <hi>will hee teach the way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.12.</note> not that which the world followeth, the fleſh ſauoreth, Satan af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecteth, but <hi>what himſelfe chuſeth.</hi> Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon cannot comprehend, carnall knowledge cannot ſearch, earthly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions cannot deſire theſe <hi>ſecrets</hi> which the Lord reueales vnto them that are poſſeſſed of his feare.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 14.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 22.4.</note> 
               <hi>Riches</hi> attend on it, <hi>Honour</hi> will not be without it, <hi>Life</hi> is the guerdon of it. Yet here is not the bounds of this Ocean, it brancheth it ſelfe into euery Channell, euery Medow, euery Tree; the root is not only parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of this moiſtneſſe, the bole onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues not benefit by this Riuer, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery branch communicateth of this <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 33.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.17.</note> for the <hi>louing kindneſſe</hi> of the Lord <hi>endureth for euer and euer vpon them that feare him, and his righteouſneſſe vpon childrens
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:131928:67"/>children.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.13.</note> The ſoule of the man himſelfe <hi>ſhall dwell at eaſe, and his ſeed ſhall inherit the earth.</hi> Neither is this benefit temporall but ſpirituall, which from this Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine is deriued; for they <hi>ſhall ſee the wealth,</hi> not of an earthly Monarchy, ſo much deſired of a worldly Empire, ſo much thirſted after, but of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">128.5, 6.</note> that is, the true Church of the euer-liuing all-diſpoſing God, not for a little moment or a few moneths, but <hi>all the daies of their liues;</hi> yea, not themſelues alone ſhall be partakers of it, but they may certainly expect to behold their poſterity inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in it, euen the conſtant and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall <hi>peace vpon Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.26.</note> For <hi>in the feare of the Lord is ſtrong confidence.</hi> Howſoeuer Perſecutors may rage, and perſecution may threaten to ruine all before it, yet the <hi>children</hi> of them that feare God, <hi>ſhall haue a place of refuge.</hi> So as with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31.19.</note> we in admiration may cry out, <hi>How great is thy goodneſſe, O Lord, which thou haſt laid vp for them that feare thee, and done to them that truſt in thee, euen before the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:131928:68"/>ſonnes of men!</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 20.</note> Doth pride ſeeke to inſult ouer them? He <hi>hides them priuily in his owne preſence.</hi> Doth malice ſeeke to preuaile againſt them? he keepes them <hi>ſecretly in his Tabernacle from the ſtrife of tongues.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in ſerm. de Iohan. Bapt.</note> 
               <hi>This is that onely whereby our minds are corrected. ſinnes are ſhunned, innocency preſerued, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility to all goodneſſe is conferred.</hi> No euill can viſit them; euill may ſurpriſe, but ſhall neuer ſeize vpon; euill may op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, but neuer ſuppreſſe them that feare the Lord. It is like Cammomile, the more it is trod on, the more it ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth; like Spice, the more it is pounded, the better it ſmelleth; the Cheſnut tree, the more it is beaten, the better fruit it beares. Let then the feare of God finde footing in your hearts, and for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe obſerue his workes of Maieſty and might.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of Chriſts Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty was the meanes of <hi>Pauls</hi> conuerſion, for when hee beheld the glory of the Lord, though with a full reſolution and reſolued purpoſe, he was breathing out
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:131928:68"/>perſecution againſt the Saints, ſeeking to terrifie, nay, to torture the ſonnes and daughters of God, hee himſelfe was ſtrucke with terror.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 9. <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.6. <hi>Luke</hi> 2.9.</note> Doth <hi>a bright Cloud ouer-ſhadow</hi> Ieſus, Moſes, <hi>and</hi> Elias, and are Peter, Iames, <hi>and</hi> Iohn at the ſight of the ſame amazed? Doth the glory of the Lord ſhine round about the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, and are they aſtoniſhed? and ſhall not feare poſſeſſe our hearts in the contemplation of his Maieſty?</p>
            <p>His workes of might in the worlds creation, wickeds confuſion, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies preſeruation: In the worlds creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Dei Dicere,</hi> was <hi>Rerum Eſſe;</hi> Gods Word was of ſuch worth, and his brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo binding, that his onely ſaying gaue eſſence vnto euery Creature,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.7, 8, 9.</note> for <hi>he ſpake and it was done, he commanded and it was created:</hi> whereupon the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> perſwadeth <hi>all the earth and all that dwell in the world to feare him.</hi> Extraordinary acts imprint in men a reuerent awe to the Agent: what our eare heareth, our eye obſerueth, our iudgement appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:131928:69"/>to bee ſpoken, ſeene or done, and was not caſt in our mould, not por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traied in our proportion, not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible in our iudgements, leaueth in the heart a ſeale of an admiring reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and reuerent admiration. <hi>Ieremy</hi> who with <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> participated of the ſame manner of calling to their ſeuerall functions, in contemplation of the Lords great power, with whom none is to be compared, ſeemes to bee peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, and concludeth with a none-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting-queſtion-anſwering admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.7.</note> 
               <hi>Who would not feare thee, O King of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why did you,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.31.</note> yee people of Iſrael, yeeld ſuch reuerence vnto the Lord, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie ſuch feare of his name, manifeſt ſuch a we in his Worſhip? Oh you that now liue, would yee know the ground and cauſe of our fearing him? The Mountaines which did hinder our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, were caſt downe by the Lords po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; the Vallies which threatned our contempt, were filled vp by his working;
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:131928:69"/>the mighty men in <hi>Aegypt</hi> were diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, and the meane ones were afraid by his might; his power turned their waters into bloud, ſo as they wanted to quench their thirſt; his power brought Frogs ouer all their land, euen into their Kings houſes, odious to their choiſeſt ſights; his power turned duſt to Lice, abhorred of their daintieſt touch, his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer corrupted the earth with ſwarmes of Flies, offen ſiue to their ſweeteſt ſmels; his power ſent a murraine amongſt their cattel, ſo as prouiſion was hindred; his power by caſting vp aſhes brought ſcabs vpon all their skinnes, ſo as their beauty was ſpoiled; by his power the Heauens opened their windowes, and ſent forth haile and fire mingled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, haile of the nature to quench fire, and fire of the nature to dry vp haile, ſo as whoſoeuer was in the fields felt, but neuer reported the violence of them; his power brought Graſhoppers, ſo as their Fruit was deuoured; his power brought darkneſſe, ſo as the comfort of ſeeing,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:131928:70"/>conferring, aſſociating one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was denied; his power depriued of life their <hi>firſt borne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.3.</note> 
               <hi>their might, the beginning of their ſtrength, the excellency of their digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, &amp; the excellency of their power, the hope of their ſucceſsion, the comfort of their yeeres, and the ſtaffe of their age:</hi> ſo as they became like water ſpilt vpon the earth, as vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for any vſe, as it is without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of being gathered; his power diuided their waters, ſet vs free, and put them in fetters, ſo as they could not paſſe, ſtopped their breath and brought their confuſion. Theſe ſeized (O yee ſonnes of men) vpon our ſoules, filled our apprehenſions with admiration of that great God which hath ſo confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their counſels, ouerthrowne their deuices, and preuailed againſt their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, who did reſiſt his will and plot our woe, hinder his Word and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine our ruine, that wee cannot but feare him. Tell me, O <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> what hath thy greatneſſe got thee? Greatneſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out godlineſſe is become thy griefe; in
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:131928:70"/>what hath thy ſorcery preuailed for thee? it could neither ſalue thy ſore, nor procure thy ſuccour; what hath thy wiſdome produced to thee? it could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther warne thee, nor warrant thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe plagues: what goodneſſe haue thy gods granted? they could nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prouide for thy good, nor preuaile againſt his greatneſſe, whoſe moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible creatures haue beene his mighty army to ſubdue thy might. Him will I feare, whoſe hand thou haſt felt; him will I reuerence, whoſe power hath curbed thy peruerſneſſe. Can I conſider the counſell of the wiſe by him turned to folly, the ſtrength of the potent by him turned to impotency, the malice of the enuious turned to their owne miſchiefe, and not feare him? Oh the power of his feare! With it my ſoule is rauiſhed, through it my heart is enlarged, by it my affections are inflamed with a deſire of and a delight in it. When I ſuruey his rare, vnexpected, vnthought of <hi>preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of thoſe that feare him, and <hi>confuſion</hi>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:131928:71"/>of thoſe that are diſobedient to him, let the waters ceaſe to drowne, the fire to burne, winds to blow, ſeas to boile, earth their ſolidity, Heauens their glory, ſooner than I to forget or ceaſe to feare him: for what <hi>Dauid</hi> feares not, ſeeing <hi>Vzzah ſtrucke to death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.9.</note> for comming vpon what colour ſoeuer without the limits of his owne calling? my fleſh trembleth for feare of thee, and I am afraid of thy Iudgements, which worke feare of thee in the heart of the very Heathen.</p>
            <p>The people whom the King of Aſhur (after he had caried away the Iſraelites) placed in Samaria,
<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 17.24, 25, 26, 27.</note> were ſlaine by Lions, and the ſuperſtitious policy of his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces would prouide a remedy, and ſend of the Prieſts to worſhip God in their owne faſhion, according to former cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of that Nation, who being now a commixed people,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 33, 34.</note> performed a diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſeruice, and are ſaid to feare God, and yet not to feare him. It was rotten at the core, faulty at the heart, they feared him as a negligent ſeruant doth his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:131928:71"/>to auoid diſpleaſure, not as an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſonne his father to diſcharge his duty: we muſt not feare as a Slaue doth a Tyrant in dread of his law, but as a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſubiect doth a fauourable Soueraigne out of loue: That is the feare of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate, which in time of extremity driues them from him, and cauſeth them to murmure when they are afflicted: This the feare of his children, which in time of miſery drawes them to him, and cauſeth them to magnifie him when they are corrected. Whence it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times taken for his whole worſhip, and may thus bee diſcerned by the effects it worketh, whether we conſider <hi>God, our ſelues, or others.</hi> In reſpect of God, finde me <hi>prayer, patience, piety, praiſe,</hi> and you cannot faile of his feare.</p>
            <p>Where true feare hath taken ſure poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, there is feruent, frequent <hi>prayer,</hi> as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> the Temanite truly affirmed, how vnaptly ſoeuer he applide it to <hi>Iob: Surely,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>thou haſt caſt off feare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>and reſtraineſt prayer before God.</hi> Note how
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:131928:72"/>confidently he doth affirme it; his heart, his affection, his reaſon, his ſoule and ſpirit were ſo poſſeſſed with the truth of this (that there is no reſtraining of prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er where the feare of God is) that hee takes them to be inſeparable: and iuſtly, for feare being the <hi>beginning of wiſdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 9.10.</note> foreſeeth the danger and preuenteth it by prayer, preſents a bleſſing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures it by prayer, reuealeth Gods plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and obtaineth ability to obey it by prayer. There is no good which is not truly diſciphered, no euill which is not liuely delineated by feare, the one whereof is obtained, and the other a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyded only by prayer.</p>
            <p>Be it that hee deferreth to grant the ſuites we make, conferreth not his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings which we neede, or withdraweth not his hand which we feele, or conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth to ſhake his Rod, which we feare will fall vpon vs, yet by our patience may we know we feare him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.11.</note> 
               <hi>depending</hi> vpon his power, bearing of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ready to embrace his pleaſure,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:131928:72"/>either in accepting of our deſires, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting our deſerts: for the feare of God which neuer <hi>exalteth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 3.7.</note> euer ſubmitteth it ſelfe, being oppoſite to <hi>preſumption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.13.</note> bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth carnal ſecurity,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.7.</note> the feare of God <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth inſtruction,</hi> and becommeth patient to behold the Lords end in deferring the manifeſtation of his mercy, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing his childrens miſery, and in his threatning their future calamity; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiting (not daring to miſconceit any thing of the Lord) that it is either for the prouing of their faith and conſtancy, the purging of their filth and impurity, the preuenting of their ſinne and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the prouiding for the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their <hi>piety,</hi> vnto which the feare of God is alwaies glued.</p>
            <p>As when <hi>Ioſuah</hi> had called to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the Iſraelites the Lords both iuſtice and mercy;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſ.</hi> 4.14.</note> iuſtice vpon their enemies, mercy towards them, hee exhorts them to feare the Lord, but withall aduiſeth that it want not the true companion, <hi>vpright ſeruing</hi> of him:
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:131928:73"/>and the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> when he had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that man <hi>bleſſed who feareth the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 112.1.</note> hee inſtantly addeth, <hi>and delighteth onely in his Commandements:</hi> as if there could be no true reuerencing of the Lord, without due regarding of his lawes; no ſtanding in awe of his wrath, without obſeruing of his will; no fearing of his name, if failing in his worſhip. Thence is it that the Lord himſelfe giues it as a charge, and laies it downe as a ſtatute neuer to be repealed or appealed from: <hi>Thou ſhalt feare the Lord thy God and ſerue him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.12.</note> And teſtifieth with and to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> that he truly feared him becauſe he withheld not his ſonne, his only ſonne. And <hi>Salomon</hi> when hee would deſcribe true feare (his deſcription though plaine, is pithy, though ſhort, yet ſententious) paints it out to this purpoſe, and makes the <hi>hating of euill</hi> to bee the badge of it,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.2.</note> which <hi>Iob</hi> did weare, and <hi>Cornelius</hi> was not without.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, whoſoeuer receiueth from the Lords hand good or euill, ſorrow or
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:131928:73"/>ſolace, gladneſſe or griefe, how euer his prayers may ſeeme to bee reiected, his patience neglected, his piety not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, yet he giues <hi>praiſe,</hi> or elſe hee feareth not. Feare opens the eyes, and lets him <hi>ſee the Lords mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.4.</note> which deales with him ſo mildly, his wiſdome diſpoſing all things ſo warily, his prouidence at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending all things ſo watchfully, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo vnworthy, the Lord ſo wiſe; himſelfe vndutifull, the Lord for all that ſo many waies bountifull; himſelfe ſo diſobedient, the Lord ſo prouident for him; himſelfe careleſſe of the Lords ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the Lord ſtill following him with his fauour, that he cannot but both in minde and mouth praiſe his name, by whoſe power hee is thus preſerued, knowing that in this he doth put on no other Liuery than hee is enioyned, nor take any other companion to true feare than is required by the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.23.</note> 
               <hi>Praiſe yee the Lord that feare him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for our ſelues, then may we be ſure that the feare of God ſwaies in our ſoules,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:131928:74"/>when our minds are enlightned with <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> our prudence ſeconded with <hi>proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> our prouidence attended with <hi>hope,</hi> our hope aſſiſted with <hi>power,</hi> our power made apparant by <hi>preuailing,</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailing continued in <hi>ſtability,</hi> either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what may tend to Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and our good, or threaten his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour and our eternall hatred: For to whom ſoeuer the feare of the Lord is, as it is in it ſelfe, a treaſure, he drawes thence,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſ.</hi> 33.6. <hi>Geneu. tranſl.</hi>
               </note> as from an Armory, <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, Wiſdome, Saluation, Strength</hi> and <hi>Stability,</hi> as is not obſcurely declared by that Euangelicall Prophet, who ſpeaking to the heart of <hi>Zion,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting her in the deſtruction of them that ſpoiled her, aſſureth her of double felicity, the one is <hi>liberty</hi> through deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and the other <hi>ſtability</hi> in her free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; which ſtability is branched out in the meanes whereby it is preſerued, &amp; the <hi>roote</hi> from whence it is deriued: the <hi>meanes</hi> whereby it is preſerued are, <hi>ſtrength for preuailing, ſafety in reſiſting,</hi> wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:131928:74"/>in <hi>prouiding, knowledge in diſcerning.</hi> The <hi>Roote</hi> out of which euery one of theſe branches buddeth, and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation whereupon hee builds this bulwarke of their conſolation, is the feare of the Lord. Now ſeeing <hi>by what meanes any thing is preſerued, by the ſame meanes often it is obtained:</hi> we may take the Prophets gradation in the Retrograde, and then we finde the feare of God to be the fountaine out of which the reſt, as little riuers, doe iſſue, though in their different neereneſſe or remoteneſſe. Howſoeuer, as by the colours the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers diſcerne their Captaine, as by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the ſtreame we come to the ſpring, as by tracing the Conduit pipes we finde the head of the riuer: ſo we may ſee where this grace reſteth, if wee can eſpy her hand-maids wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
            <p>The firſt and neereſt whereof is <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> with which the feare of God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightneth the ſoule, as a candle the darkeſt houſe, and driueth away the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:131928:75"/>miſts of ignorance and error; as the Sunne riſing diſperſeth any clouds or vapours. For it informeth the reaſon, perſwadeth the will, tutereth the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and directeth the actions: preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to the minde, both heauens myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and helliſh miſchiefes; openeth to the vnderſtanding, the records of cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall ſecrets and infernall ſubtleties; lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth before the will, the Lords Maieſtie, and his Childrens felicitie; Satans ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and the damneds miſery; offereth to the affections, virtues dignitie, and vices deformity; and tendereth to euery action, as the proper end, glory or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 111.10.</note> paine or pleaſure: Whence <hi>Dauid</hi> (the worthieſt father) and <hi>Solomon</hi> (the wiſeſt ſonne) affirme,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 1.7.</note> that it is <hi>the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Wiſdome,</hi> and the Lord aſſureth him, in whom his feare remaineth, that hee will bee <hi>his teacher,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 25.12.</note> euen hee who is wiſdome, knowledge, and truth. So as <hi>Prudence</hi> to diſcerne is one of the notes whereby the feare of God is knowne.</p>
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:131928:75"/>
            <p>But becauſe where the enemy know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth wiſdome wanteth, hee the rather at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempteth, in that the heart is ſurpriſed with a greater feare in the approach of danger, and the ſoule tortured with a more grieuous torment in the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſafety, perceiuing both, yet not conceiuing which way either to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the one or be partaker of the other, the feare of God leauing not his harbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer either deceiued or vnfurniſhed, nor the enemy vnaffrighted or vnpreuented, hangeth forth another flag, and that is, <hi>prouidence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. in moral. Timere Deum eſt nulla, quae faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda ſunt, praete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rire bona.</note> wiſely preparing euery thing which Prudence ſuggeſted as pertinent or expedient, and <hi>neglecting</hi> nothing which wiſdome hath reuealed as requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for preuention. What was it which moued <hi>Noah that preacher of righteouſneſſe to prepare the Arke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.7.</note> whereby he and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily were ſaued in the worlds great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge? Was it not <hi>reuerence</hi> to him who threatned their ruine, reuealed his deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 9.20.</note> What perſwaded the Aegyptians to driue <hi>their cattell</hi> and <hi>keepe themſelues
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:131928:76"/>within their houſes,</hi> till the haile and the danger was paſt? Was it not a dread of his power, who had made knowne that plague and the danger of it? What was it which cauſed the Apoſtle of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, notwithſtanding the Lord promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſafety to himſelfe and all that ſailed with him,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 27.29.31.</note> in that great danger of ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke, not to ſuffer any to goe out of the Ship? was it not feare to prouoke and diſtruſt him, who had ſo gratiouſly made knowne his pleaſure? Whence it is that <hi>Iob</hi> the patterne of patience, who ſaw many of Satans plots, and was ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of many perplexities,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 28.18. <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.27. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.10.</note> calls it <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> it ſelfe; for it is a <hi>Well-ſpring of life to auoid the ſnares of death, and all they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of a good vnderſtanding that do there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now leſt any, through the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Foes, greatneſſe of contrary ſtrength, or ſtrangeneſſe of Stratagems, which he either ſeeth or conceiueth, and againſt which he prepareth, might, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious of his owne ſpirituall wiſdome
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:131928:76"/>and naturall weakneſſe, feare to faile in the encounter, the feare of God holdeth forth an aſſiſting hand, and miniſtreth <hi>hope of ſafety,</hi> by preſenting the <hi>greatneſſe of Gods power,</hi> the <hi>graciouſneſſe of his promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and certainty of his protection:</hi> For by what was the true feare of God, which neuer maketh fleſh its arme, more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in vndaunted <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17.</note> and his fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, then in their hope of deliuerance grounded on Gods <hi>power</hi> to preſerue them? By what can the beames of this grace more ſparkle out then by relying on his <hi>promiſes?</hi> Therefore the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> maketh the <hi>attending on his mercies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.11.</note> the expectation of his mercifull <hi>promiſes,</hi> an attendant on it, by which it may be knowne as a fit gueſt by his marriage garment; and leſt wee might thinke him to imply that, whereof he was not perſwaded, hee maketh his prayer the proclaimer of his hope, and manifeſteth his hope in the promiſe to be grounded on his feare of God.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.38.</note> How ſhall we know that <hi>Simeon</hi> feared God? Aske Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:131928:77"/>ſpirit, his comfortable intelligencer, our beſt interpreter of the truth, and hee will tell vs, and let vs ſee the ſigne, looke on him; behold ye his hope expecting, his expectation waiting for <hi>the conſolation of Iſrael?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.</note> Doe you iudge of a man by his mates, and of his condition by his companions?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 2.25, 26.</note> and can you not ſee <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meon</hi> to be a man who feared God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with it is ioyned his waiting for the accompliſhment of that promiſe, of not ſeeing death till hee had ſeene the Lord Chriſt? Laſtly, the hope of the Lords aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance is aſſured by the certainty of his <hi>protection,</hi> and certaine perſwaſion that <hi>his eyes are ouer thoſe that feare him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.7.</note> and that his <hi>Angell pitcheth his Tent round about them. Dauid</hi> a man ſore turmoiled in many troubles, had fainted, but his ſtrength was by the <hi>Word of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130.5.</note> the word of his promiſe, ſuſtained. Feare of the Lords Maieſty preſented his power, his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and his protection, and comforted <hi>Dauids</hi> heart, for it is alwaies accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with hope.</p>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:131928:77"/>
            <p>And when hope beholdeth aſſiſtance, as then the feare of God adminiſtreth courage to enter the liſts, entertaine the combat, ſo it furniſheth with <hi>ſtrength,</hi> to <hi>defend</hi> the ſoule, <hi>offend</hi> the aſſaylants;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.26.</note> 
               <hi>defend</hi> the ſoule, for in it is <hi>aſſured,</hi> an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>ſtrength;</hi> it is not a fayling, but a fortifying, not a ſhrinking but endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, not a falſe, but a firme fortreſſe. No dart can pierce it, no blow wound it, no ſhot enter into it, a bulwarke that cannot bee vndermined, a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle that cannot bee battered, a Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that cannot bee ranſacked. It was a ſhield to couer <hi>Ioſeph</hi> from the wound of concupiſcence; a buckler to beare off the blow of impatience bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goning from Iobs friends and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; a breſtplate to all the Saints, to keepe ſafe their hearts from all ſpirituall hurts, and more powerfull than that <hi>Lawrell,</hi> which <hi>Tiberius Ceſar</hi> is ſaid to weare, to preſerue them from the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Satans Thunderbolts, and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends the ſoule. It no leſſe <hi>offends</hi> the
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:131928:78"/>aſſailants, <hi>defeating</hi> Sathan of his hopes, and enforcing him and his to take their <hi>flight.</hi> It defeateth him of his hopes, <hi>fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring our affections, ſugring our afflictions, ſeaſoning our ſpirituall foode.</hi> It fette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth our <hi>affections</hi> with the chaines of Gods diſpleaſure; It danteth our car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reſolutions with a ſight of his powerfull anger, it bridleth our vnlimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted deſires with the reines of his threatnings, and glutteth the greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our ſinfull appetites, with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting his power. What deuilliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light is not diſtaſted? What fleſhly hope is not fruſtrated? What helliſh deed is not croſſed? where the feare of God reſideth? It, as the oyle of <hi>Nenuphar,</hi> cooleth the deſire of ſinne, and as that fountaine in <hi>Armenia</hi> turneth our hotteſt loue of iniquity to a cold liking. It <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greth our afflictions,</hi> as <hi>Eliſhaes wood</hi> ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the <hi>bitter waters,</hi> leſt griefe ſhould make vs ſenſleſſe through too much ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering; and as the tree <hi>Alpia,</hi> rather withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth with the due of mercy, then wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:131928:78"/>with the fire of miſery. It <hi>ſeaſoneth our ſpirituall food:</hi> For, hath Satan caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the pots of our celeſtiall nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the gourds of falſe gloſſes, or er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous interpretations, or any way corrupted the ſacred well of ſaluation, that we expecting an Egge might faſten vpon a ſtone, looking for a fiſh catch a ſerpent, or thinking to be quenched might be poyſoned? The feare of God as <hi>Eliſhaes meale,</hi> maketh that meate wholſome, and hauing tried it with the rules of pietie, faith, and charity, auoides as with the Vnicornes horne, the ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of ſoule-killing poyſon. Thus it defeateth Sathan of his hopes, preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his fallacies, weakning his forces, daſhing his helliſh Impes againſt the wall, cruſhing ſinne as a Cockatrice in the ſhell, nay binding Sathans hands with feruent praier, and wounding his head with the two edged ſword of the ſpirit, which is the word of God, that he is inforced to <hi>fly,</hi> hating as much the beholding of this grace in gods
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:131928:79"/>children, as the Serpent diſliketh the ſhadow of the Aſhe tree, which rather chuſeth (if it muſt needes doe the one) to runne into the fire than come neere it, whether he ſee it in the morning of their conuerſion, or the euening of their diſſolution; at the Sunne riſe of their proſperity, or the Sunne ſet of their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity, and ſo <hi>preuaileth.</hi> For it is <hi>not viſited,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 19.23.</note> not ſo viſited <hi>with euill,</hi> as it ſhall be vanquiſhed: For maugre the malice of all, it bringeth ſtability with it, and doth <hi>perſiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though it day by day bee allured to folly, as it neglecteth at the firſt, ſo at leaſt it diſtaſteth, all allurements euen at the laſt. This fire enflameth the ſoule with zeale, that it can neuer be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together quenched; this dew moiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the heart with grace which will neuer be throughly dryed vp; this food filleth the bones with marrow that will neuer be wholly waſted: For they who feare the Lord <hi>ſhall neuer depart from him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerem.</hi> 32.40</note> and aſſuredly ſhall <hi>continue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 19.23.</note> continue in
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:131928:79"/>his loue, continue in their loialty, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue prudent combattants againſt Satan, potent Commanders ouer ſinne, ſo as no ſooner can any part be vndermined, but <hi>prudence</hi> eſpies it, no ſooner any place bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, but <hi>prouidence</hi> repaires it; no ſooner any encounter offered, but <hi>hope of ſafety</hi> entertaines it; no ſooner the leaſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault made, but <hi>ſtrength</hi> reſiſteth, reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting <hi>preuaileth,</hi> and preuailing <hi>perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now wee proceed to thoſe flowers which the feare of God putteth into the hearts and hands of euery one that hath it, that hee may not (as <hi>Iacob</hi> feared hee ſhould) <hi>ſtinke among his neighbouring Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 34.</note> but yeeld a ſweet and pleaſing ſmell to others, whether <hi>liuing or dead.</hi> It reſpecteth the liuing in regard of their <hi>ſuperiority,</hi> or <hi>inferiority,</hi> or <hi>promiſcuouſly.</hi> To <hi>ſuperiors,</hi> who either in minde or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or ſtate, are better furniſhed then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, it preſenteth <hi>Dittany,</hi> not for the ſhew or ſmell, but for the vſe and vertue of it, which is double <hi>attractiue</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſiue;</hi>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:131928:80"/>ſo the feare of God at the ſight of others miſeries is touched with them and laies them to the heart, whence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth a <hi>pitying</hi> of their wants and woes, a <hi>prouiding</hi> for their wealth and welfare; <hi>pitying</hi> of their wants, neither neglecting their neede, nor adding to their calamity, knowing that they muſt doe iuſt and equall to the moſt inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, becauſe they haue one who is their ſupreme, and that they may neither put a <hi>ſtumbling blocke before the blind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu</hi> 19.14.</note> for that were inhumane cruelty, nor rule ouer the meaneſt too rigorouſly, for that were cruellinhumanity.
<note place="margin">5.15.</note> 
               <hi>Nehemiah</hi> feared God, but how ſhall that be knowne? he did ſo attract to himſelfe the miſeries and oppreſſions of the people, that he would neither <hi>bee chargeable himſelfe,</hi> where he might, nor ſuffer his <hi>ſeruants to beare rule ouer them,</hi> as no doubt they would. But is the ſigne hung out whereby theſe fruits and want of pitty may be left vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gathered? The Lord giues the token in preſſing the duty to bee performed, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:131928:80"/>
               <hi>But thou ſhalt feare thy God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu.</hi> 19.14.</note> ſo that then the feare of God is that herbe on which pittying of others wants appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth; and where vſury, taking of aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, oppreſſing a neighbour, ſuch a one as is deare or neere vnto vs, either in a ſpirituall, naturall, or politicall reſpect, or in a corporall, ſpirituall or acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall neede, doe ſpring; we may paſſe by theſe becauſe vnfit flowers to garniſh the Lords Temple, nay we muſt neglect them becauſe they ſtinke already in the Lords Noſthrils, hauing neither any participation with, nor ſent of moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture from his feare, which as <hi>Dittany</hi> not only attracting but expelling, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not the wounding but the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, not onely pittieth the wants, but <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uideth</hi> for their weales. It prepareth a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and purgeth out their poyſon, it anointeth their wounds and aſſwageth their woes, it powreth into their eares the wine of comfortable words, and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth their hands with the ſuppling oile of ſupplying workes. Their words as the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:131928:81"/>flower of the Almond-tree, ſuppled with the oyle of compaſſion, cure thoſe who are ſubiect to the falling ſickneſſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Apoſtaſie, or the Lethargy of forgetting either of Gods power and mercy, or their owne wretchedneſſe and impotency, and pounded with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of conſolation, aſſwageth the ſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a wounded conſcience, and the Vlcers of a wicked conuerſation. And as the Vine branches couer the buds of their now ſprouting hopes, that they for the preſent and in future time conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue ſafe from the Summers ſcorching and Winters ſcourge, from the boiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous winds of calumny and bitter wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of calamity, from the breath of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and from the hands of cruelty. <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diah</hi> is reported of, to haue <hi>feared God greatly,</hi> but what argument is vſed to aſſure the truth of it? What ſigne or token is there in him? What worke done by him to perſwade it? Doe wee know the Tree by the Fruits, or the day by the Sunne riſing? Oh
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:131928:81"/>
               <hi>Obediah,</hi> the feare of God ſhineth in thy facts. <hi>Iezabel</hi> hateth the Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, thy heart groaneth for their griefe; <hi>Iezabel</hi> is perſecuting the Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, thy head is deuiſing their ſafety; <hi>Iezabel</hi> is deſtroying the Lords Prophets, thy hand is preparing their ſecuritie; are they diſconſolate, and doſt thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them? Are they houſeleſſe, and doſt thou harbour them? Are they afraid of Famine, and doſt thou feede them? The feare of God was greatly rooted in thee; waſt not thou the Gouernour of the Kings houſe? thou couldſt not be ignorant that great ones haue many an <hi>Argus</hi> to watch ouer them; that they who are neere Princes, haue the eies of ambitious emulation, and enuious ambition to prie into them: thy fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight could not but tell thee, that if this were diſcouered, the diſpleaſure of the king (whoſe anger is as the roring of a Lion) would be vnappeaſeable; the ſtings of <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts (as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Bees about thee) vnſufferable; the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:131928:82"/>cruell malice and malicious cruelty of the Queene, according to her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, would be grieuous, and (as her hatred) vnlimitable. What labourer ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a cloud ariſe out of the ſea, doth not ſuſpect a ſhower? what Hare eſpying the approach of the Hound, doth not at leaſt expect a courſe? What beaſt ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lioneſſe range as robbed of her whelpes, feares not to become a prey? or who dare take the prey out of the Lions mouth? Can I then ſee her bloudy purpoſes preuented by thy pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, her cruell perſecutions to thy vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt endeuour bounded within leſſe than her intended limits? doe I looke on them miſerable, and thee mercifull, obſerue them perplexed, and thee piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and not admire it? What heauenly heart-cheering <hi>Zephirus</hi> cauſed this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? What ſpirituall-comfort-bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-fire inflamed this zeale? What di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine ouerſwaying power directed this action, which neither apparent might, nor potent malice could hinder? The
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:131928:82"/>feare of God was that tree which did beare this fruit, that bellowes which did blow this fire, whereby the feare of man and of earthly miſchiefe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. Can you perceiue this <hi>Dittany</hi> kept in the heart, held in the hand, of Superiours, by its operation ſucking out the venome, ſaluing of the ſores, of ſuch as are diſconſolate or diſtreſſed, helping any that are any way wanting or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full? Doubt not, the feare of God ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered that herbe, and there hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it.</p>
            <p>Now that which this grace proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for inferiours, is the Roſe, knowne and delighted in for two ſpeciall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, becauſe it doth <hi>decore viſum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcere, &amp; odore olfactum afficere,</hi> feedes the ſight with rareneſſe of the beauty, and delights the ſmell with the ſweetneſſe of the ſauour: So the feare of God may be knowne to be in ſuch as are ſubiect to others by <hi>ſubmiſsiue reuerence,</hi> and <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere obedience; Submiſsiue reuerence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 16.31.</note> for <hi>age is a crowne of glory,</hi> eſpecially if it bee
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:131928:83"/>found <hi>in the way of righteouſneſſe;</hi> a glorious Crowne, (by others ſo to be conceiued, but howſoeur ſo it is in it ſelfe conſidered) to which all reſpect muſt be rendred, the rendring whereof draweth the affections of all to delight in it. It is like faire weather in the height of harueſt, no leſſe <hi>comfortable</hi> than <hi>profitable, no leſſe profitable than comfortable, comfortable to them that receiue it, profitable to them that yeeld it, both comfortable and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to them that ſee it:</hi> to them who <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it,</hi> it is like the ſong of the Swanne before her death, the warmth of the fire to a cold benummed body, ſweet words to a departing friend, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derpropping to a declining wall. For this ſtirreth vp their fire that lay vnder the dead aſhes through age almoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, this addeth more oyle to their Lamps, ſo as they ſhine more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably in themſelues, more brightly to others benefit, though welnigh conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. To them that <hi>yeeld it,</hi> it is a lawrell to adorne their heads with honour, and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:131928:83"/>a treaſure to enrich their hearts with grace, purchaſing the applauſe of men, and procuring <hi>that praiſe which is of God.</hi> To them that <hi>ſee it,</hi> it is the raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of their affections with ioy, the filling of their minds with pleaſure, and their mouthes with praiſe, miniſtring matter either for imitation or inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now this leafe of this Roſe, whoſe beauty doth ſo inchant the eie, is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in true manner without the feare of God, as the Lord himſelfe will witnes. <hi>Thou ſhalt riſe vp before the hoary head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leu.</hi> 19.32.</note> 
               <hi>and honour the perſon of the old man, and dread thy God.</hi> A ſilly Ideot may riſe vp before the hoary head, and yet not conſider that grauity is a repreſentation of his Makers wiſdome: a Heathen wiſe man may honor the perſon of the aged, and yet not take notice that old age pourtraieth out in a ſpeciall manner the Lords eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: a morall Chriſtian may both riſe vp and honour the graue man, and in doing thereof meditate that the Lord is onely wiſe and <hi>the ancient of daies,</hi> and
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:131928:84"/>yet faile to performe it in a due manner; and therefore hee addeth, <hi>and dread thy God;</hi> as if this gaue the other duties their life and luſtre: and ſurely this honour giuen in a true and reuerent manner, groweth in no garden-plot, but onely where the feare of God is planted; ſo as we may know it by the firſt property of the Roſe; which is, if it feede the ſight and breed ſubmiſſiue reuerence.</p>
            <p>The other property is, <hi>odore olfactum af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficere,</hi> to delight the ſmell with the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſauour in <hi>ſincere obedience:</hi> For what is our riſing vp before the hoary head, if our heart lye groueling? What is the honouring of the aged perſon with our affections, if not teſtified by our actions? heart and hand concurring in this honour to our Superiours, is as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable as Incenſe vnto God, and as the ſweeteſt perfume vnto man; the one ſo highly eſteemeth ſincere obedience to Superiours, that he maketh it by way of motiue <hi>a patterne for his peoples practiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier.</hi> 35. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.22.</note> and by it puts them in minde <hi>of their duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:131928:84"/>him;</hi> with the other, it is of ſuch powerfull operation, that what paines ſoeuer they take for thoſe of whom they are <hi>ouerſeers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> the ſame is turned <hi>to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> and they are glad when they can promoue their good. Such is the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Roſe: but can it be plucked in euery hedge, or found in euery field? ah no, it is of Heauens ſowing, and is not to be had ſaue in that heart, nor ſeene ſaue in that hand which the feare of God directeth. When <hi>Ioſeph</hi> propounded a condition to his brethren, who knew him not, promiſing life vpon the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of that condition, by perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming whereof hee in ſome ſort was to become their inferiour, becauſe their debter, preoccupateth and preuenteth what they might obiect: Thou art the chiefe vnder <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> euen as the Lord of the whole Land of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> if one of vs be left as a Priſoner, and he miſcarry through too much miſery, who will call thee to account, dare accuſe thee of cruelty, or can cauſe thee to anſwer for
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:131928:85"/>his life? If hee continue aliue (though a priſoner) till our returne, when wee haue brought our youngeſt brother, whoſe company is our fathers comfort, whoſe health his happineſſe, and whoſe death (which God preuent) will cut the thred of his aged life (which God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue) if thou determineſt to keepe the one in bonds, and bind the other to a like condition, let vs complaine, thou art <hi>Pharaohs</hi> eare, we ſhall not be heard; let vs pleade, thou art <hi>Pharaohs</hi> mouth, our doome ſhall be harſh; let vs vpon the ſentence craue pardon, and humbly beg a mitigation of the penalty, thou art <hi>Pharaohs</hi> hand, and our burthen ſhall continue heauy. Wee haue made thee acquainted with the greatneſſe of our pinching famine, is it not in thy power to exact one after another till we all be thy ſeruants, or elſe to withhold thy helpe? But how doth <hi>Ioſeph</hi> remoue theſe miſts, and cleere their minds of theſe miſconceits? What ſigne could hee hang out that they might know
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:131928:85"/>the truth of his heart? or what pawne doth hee tender whereby they might caſt themſelues vpon his truſt? What earneſt doth hee giue to binde that bargaine, and aſſure them of his honeſt dealing? by no better token can mans faith be manifeſted, by no ſigne his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity made more knowne, by no pledge his truth more plainely demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated; for it was his feare of God which he engaged;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.18.</note> 
               <hi>Doe this and liue</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for I feare God;</hi> Intimating that whereuer this grace is grafted, truſt may certainly be repoſed, and vnblameable dealing aſſuredly expected. The ſame may be collected from the ſpeech of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thro</hi> giuing aduice to <hi>Moſes</hi> to ſelect ſome among the people to beare with him the burthen of their affaires; for in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the perſons which would bee fit to be ſo emploied, he deſcribes their properties to be foure, <hi>Men of courage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.22.</note> 
               <hi>fearing God, men dealing truly, hating coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe;</hi> Which wee anatomizing, may behold the feare of God lying in the
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:131928:86"/>midſt as the heart in man, and though it incline to one ſide, yet from thence iſſueth life both to that ſide and euery part beſide; For if there bee fearing of God, the might or malice of man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not preuent; if there be fearing of God, neither the gliſtring of gold, nor a boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull bribe can corrupt; for the feare of God begets courage, and courage hateth to be captiued by couetouſneſſe: And where courage triumpheth and couetouſneſſe is hated, there dealing tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is harboured: whereſoeuer then is the feare of God, there true dealing may be found. Why did <hi>Cornelius</hi> chuſe a ſouldier <hi>which feared God</hi> to attend vpon him?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 10.2.</note> ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he dreamed of his greater diligence: why did the ſame <hi>Cornelius</hi> ſelect that ſouldier which aboue others was <hi>deuout</hi> &amp; feared God,
<note place="margin">10.</note> ioyning him with two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of his ſeruants for a ſpeciall ſeruice, ſuch a ſeruice as was aduiſed by an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, one of heauens Heraulds, to an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, one of the Lords-Vice-gerents, for the informing of himſelfe how to
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:131928:86"/>fight that he might finde a kingdome, how to combat that hee might win, winning triumph, and triumphing weare a Crowne that doth not fade? Surely hee thought, as none could bee more fit for that meſſage, ſo none could be more acceptable, more faithfull, in that ambaſſage. It cannot be, but <hi>ſincere obedience,</hi> aſwell as <hi>ſubmiſsiue reuerence,</hi> will be found to bud and bloſſome, where the feare of God hath watered. Thus doth the feare of God furniſh both ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour and inferiour ſeuerally conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, either of them with an vſefull and mutually pleaſing poſie.</p>
            <p>Let vs now ſee wherewith it garniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſpirituall houſes of <hi>all promiſcuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> of both the meane as well as of the mighty, of the high as of the low, poore as rich, one as another. And the firſt is <hi>Helitropium,</hi> faſhioning the man, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it is, according as the Lord is pleaſed, in anger, or fauor, to abſent, or preſent, himſelfe; and lying at the heart, ſends out at the boſome the leaues which are
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:131928:87"/>of that property, that they are powerfull againſt all ſwelling tumors of ſpirituall pride, preſeruing humility: and yet al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies white, implying innocency; for he that feareth God, is not arrogant in opinion, not eſtranged from any others in affection, neither offendeth willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, nor offended eaſily; <hi>becommeth all things to all men,</hi> yet neither deceiuing nor being deceiued, neither tainting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with the Leuen of impurity, nor tainted himſelfe by others with the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of either hereticall impiety, or impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hereſie; for ſelfe-conceited wiſdome is a tumour which the feare of God breaketh, and therefore is preſcribed by the Lord as an Antidote againſt it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>Bee not wiſe</hi> (ſo aduiſeth <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>in thine owne eies:</hi> for that is a poyſon; but that thou maiſt auoid it, <hi>feare the Lord.</hi> Where there are humble thoughts without ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, brotherly care without contempt, like affection without contradictious vaine-glory, or vaine-glorious contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction: where in priuate there is not a
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:131928:87"/>ſelfe conceited meeting to encreaſe ſchiſme, but a holy aſſembly mutually to continue true zeale and a religious ſociety; in publike not a Chriſts-coat-renting, but a Church-cheering-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenticle, not a ſchiſme-furthering, but a true zeale-enflaming conference; there is <hi>ſubmitting themſelues one to another in the feare of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.21.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.16.</note> See wee any like <hi>affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned one to another, and not high minded?</hi> See we men <hi>making themſelues equall towards them of the lower ſort?</hi> See we men <hi>eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming euery man better than themſelues?</hi> Is there none ſo ſcornefull but will caſt his eies vpon others meaneſt matters, none ſo froward but will ſuffer others to caſt an eie vpon their actions, none ſo wiſe but will embrace anothers watch-word? Are they thus inwardly decked with lowlineſſe of minde? as ſure as the Lord liueth the feare of God is in them; for to haue outward cauſe of being haughty, and yet to be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; to be outwardly humbled, and not inwardly haughty, either through pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:131928:88"/>in obeying without expectation of reward or merit, or in bearing without offending by murmuring, is an infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſigne of fearing God, the property whereof is <hi>in all things to depart from euill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 8.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Further, as the Doue in her bill did beare the Oliue branch, as an Enſigne of reſt, ſo theſe in their words and workes, doe beare the leaues and weare the liuery of vnitie, which is ſo accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God and man, that it made <hi>Dauid</hi> to vſe an emphaticall exclamation,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.1.</note> 
               <hi>Oh how good and ioyfull a thing it is, brethren to dwell together in vnitie!</hi> We might haue giuen credit if he had once affirmed that it was <hi>good;</hi> we with him had had reaſon to admire, if he had only cried out, <hi>How good.</hi> But ſeeing he cannot comprehend the goodnes of it, in that he adds, <hi>Oh how good,</hi> I will doe as that Painter who was to decipher the ſorrow of a Father for the loſſe of his ſonne, who becauſe he was not able to delineate it, drew the curtaine ouer him, and left the ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:131928:88"/>to conceiue what hee was not poſſible to pourtray forth with his Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill. This one bare aſſertion of <hi>Dauid, Good it is,</hi> might haue admitted doubt: his acclamation, <hi>How good,</hi> might haue receiued anſwer among the exceptious; But his <hi>Behold how good,</hi> implieth, that either he himſelfe was not able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend <hi>How good it is,</hi> or hauing onely a glimpſe of the goodneſſe of it, he cals all to take a view of the excellency of ſuch an heauenly bleſſing, whereby men doe moſt reſemble the euer-bleſſed Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, imitate the ſtate of the glorious Angels, and glorified Saints, pleaſant to God who is delighted with it, &amp; profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to men who are enriched by it, with ſpirituall graces and all ſorts of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And though men cannot liuely expreſſe what it is, yet conſidering what the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, they may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue what it is like, out of <hi>Dauids</hi> mouth, <hi>It is like the pretious oyntment vpon the head, that ran downe vpon the beard, euen Aarons beard, that went downe to the skirts of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:131928:89"/>It is like the dew of Hermon, which fell vpon the hill of Sion.</hi> The Oyle where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Aaron</hi> was anointed, was made for that purpoſe by Gods appointment: The bleſſings which vnitie bringeth, are prepared in heauen, and conferred as God appointeth. The Oyle wherewith <hi>Aaron</hi> was anointed, ranne from the head to the beard, from the beard to the skirts of his cloathing: That bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing which vnitie bringeth falleth vpon the higheſt, and runneth along to the middle ſort, till it come to the loweſt and meaneſt of Gods people, and reſts not till euery one be partakers of it. That Oyle wherewith <hi>Aaron</hi> was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed, was powred out; while it is kept in the boxe none receiueth any be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, nor are delighted in it; but when it is powred out, the ſauour is perceiued, and thoſe that partake it are thirſting after it, as is ſeene by what the Spouſe ſaith to Chriſt,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>Thy loue is better than wine;</hi> why ô thou beloued doſt thou ſo conceit it? <hi>Becauſe of the ſauour of
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:131928:89"/>thy good ointments.</hi> But how cameſt thou to take notice of their good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? <hi>Thy name is an oyntment powred out.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 3.</note> Oh that I knew where this oliue branch might be plucked! from the roote of the feare of God, there it is growing. <hi>I will giue them</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>one heart and one way that they may feare me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.39.</note> Feare is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of wiſdome, and wiſdome is the cauſe of vnity: For demand of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> what hee meanes by wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king worthy of their calling, and he will tell them one part of it among others is this,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.</note> their endeuour <hi>to keepe the vnity of the Spirit in the bonds of peace.</hi> Aske him againe how this worthy walking may be obtained, and he will anſwer, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing filled with <hi>the knowledge of Gods will in all wiſdome and ſpirituall vnderſtanding:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9.10.</note> So as we muſt not conceiue of feare, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Lord ſpeaketh by <hi>Ieremy,</hi> as though he meant the act: For firſt in euery grace there is God conferring it vpon man; mans reflexing at the gifts collation backe vpon God, and then diffuſing of
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:131928:90"/>it in the fruits among men. Vnity in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion <hi>(one heart)</hi> and concordancy in action <hi>(one way)</hi> hath relation of man to man, and therefore is not the cauſe of that true feare which was infuſed firſt by God himſelfe; ſo as by feare there we are to vnderſtand not abſtractiuely as it is ſeuered, but concretiuely as it is ioyned with degrees or circumſtances; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, ſometimes the act is taken for the meaſure how farre it is extended; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for the extent of time to the which it reacheth, and then it is as if the Lord had ſaid, <hi>I will giue them one heart and one way,</hi> that it may bee manifeſt and made apparant to any that make queſtion of it, that <hi>they feare me</hi> in no little meaſure. Beſides, hee ſpeakes of the time <hi>for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,</hi> whereof vnitie is a great occaſion: For where a Church within it ſelfe by Schiſmes is diſioynted, the feare of God is greatly cooled, and where the feare of God is cooled, the continuance of that Church may bee iuſtly doubted. Doe we then finde in our ſelues a deſire, and
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:131928:90"/>ſee we in others and our ſelues the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes of peace, a ſtriuing for vnity, an embracing of concord? Is there among vs agreement in opinion, ſympathy in affection, concord in conuerſation, ecleſiaſticall, oeconomicall, politicall? wee may aſſure our ſelues the feare of God abides among vs, for we keepe the <hi>vnity of the Spirit in the bond of peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.3.</note> which is one ſpeciall part of our <hi>walking worthy of that calling wherunto in Chriſt we are called.</hi> Now this worthy walking is begot by <hi>wiſdome and ſpirituall vnderſtanding,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 1.9, 10. <hi>Pro.</hi> 1.7.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the <hi>feare of God is the beginning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt note of Gods feare is <hi>equity,</hi> which I may compare to Mandrakes, the ſmell whereof is commended by the Spouſe, whereof there are two ſorts, Male and Female.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.13. <hi>Geneu. tranſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Mandrakes haue giuen a ſmell, and in our gates are all ſweet things new and old.</hi> Theſe are carried in either hand one, of him that feares God; which to euery ſex, euery ſtate doth iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, not pittying the poore nor fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the rich, not fearing the mighty nor
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:131928:91"/>neglecting the meane, not vniuſtly hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping his friend nor hurting his foe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>his name is an oyntment powred out,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth the ſmell of them that come neere to ſent it in <hi>the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance of their daies; at their death. They continue as the Palme-tree in the houſe of the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.37.</note> 
               <hi>Marke the vpright man and behold the iuſt, the end of that man is peace.</hi> It is no Thiſtle that beareth this Fig. What maketh Iudges execute iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? the feare of God. What maketh the great to keepe themſelues free from oppreſſion? the feare of God. What pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth all men from iniurious dealing? the feare of God. But if that be wanting, the reines are laid on the necke of euerie ſinne, and the ſpurre giuen to euerie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurie; what wrong is neglected, what wickedneſſe is omitted, what crueltie is vnacted, if the feare of God bee not embraced?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham</hi> knew there was readineſſe to act iniurie, proneneſſe to commit iniquity, promptneſſe to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate all wrong, where the <hi>feare of God was wanting,</hi> for how can they deale faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:131928:91"/>with any who haue no feeling of the goodneſſe or greatneſſe of the Lord?</p>
            <p>Thus for the <hi>liuing:</hi> for the <hi>dead,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by workes of charity towards them may we know we feare the Lord, ſo as whom the feare of God moued to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour liuing, the ſame feare will prouoke vs to giue vnto him his due when hee is dead.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 7.</note> That <hi>Protomartyr</hi> died for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, euen in profeſſing of the truth, ſuch was the height and heate of that perſecution, ſuch the frowardneſſe and fury of the Perſecutors; ſo great it was againſt the Church at Ieruſalem, that they <hi>were all ſcattered abroad through the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of Iudea and Samaria.</hi> And was there not one to interre this Martyrs body, not one to couer it in the Graue, not one to caſt this ſeede in hope of reſurrection into the earth? If there were any, who durſt aduenture to doe it? <hi>Saul</hi> made hauocke of the Church, <hi>entred into,</hi> not one, but <hi>euery houſe,</hi> and <hi>drew them out both men and women, and put them in priſon.</hi>
               <pb n="170" facs="tcp:131928:92"/>No place was vnſought, no perſon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſifted, no age fauoured, no ſexe ſpared. Did the hoare head of the ancient finde mercy? no. Did the weeping eyes of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing women behold pitty? no. Did the crying of little babes moue compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? no. Their goods were made a ſpoile to the rauenous, their bodies were vſed as a prey by the malicious, their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable credits and neuer dying names were as Tennis-balls ignominiouſly toſſed in the mouthes of the opprobri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. How was their hope weakned, their faith ſhaken, their ſpirits troubled, and they themſelues eternally endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 22.4.</note> ſeeing he <hi>perſecuted this way euen vnto death.</hi> The malice of one might by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny haue beene preuented, and many would haue receiued mutuall encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, and might haue performed mutuall duties of their profeſſion, if one onely had perſecuted: but alas, this way was contemned by the people, hated by the Prieſts, condemned by all. The people would ſpeedily report
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:131928:92"/>what they either perceiued in, or ſaw done by any which inclined to it; the Prieſts inſtantly preſſe the puniſhing of what they heard, and the Rulers were as ready to giue ſentence of <hi>ſcourging,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>ver.</hi> 5.</note> if not death. Who then durſt endanger their eſtates, hazard their liues, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terre <hi>Stephen? There were men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 8.2.</note> not meerely men, but men deuout <hi>fearing God,</hi> which <hi>carried</hi> him to his buriall, <hi>and made great lamentation ouer him,</hi> their reuerent deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion caſt out all doubt of death or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and wrought in them a reſpect of that body whoſe Spirit was with the Lord to whom it was <hi>commended.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 7.59.</note> And ſurely if it worke ſuch regard of the liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe corps of a Saint, what care will it not worke in men for the good and right of his left and liuing Image, and of euery one to whom his ſpeciall loue and care was linked? For is it not a deſperate preſumption in the ſeruant whom hopefull feare ſhould make obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, to neglect that which his Maſter hath not onely laid before him by pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:131928:93"/>but laid vpon him by precept? De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of reuerent deuotion is that man who ſeeing his glorious Creator conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing his mercies to the childrens chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of them that feare him, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his gracious Redeemer giue a charge in giuing vp the ghoſt for the good of her that was deare vnto him, takes no care for the poſterity of thoſe who were intereſt in their Creators mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and their Redeemers merits. And theſe are the ſignes by which the feare of God is diſcerned.</p>
            <p>The plaiſter is made knowne, the phyſicke is preſcribed, there wants no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the applying of it. Are thy hands often ſtretched out to God? art thou content to wait his pleaſure, to vndergoe his wrath, to endure the ſmart of his rod, though to thine owne ruine, with continuing in pietie towards him, and praiſing of him? Art thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, informed doſt thou prouide, prouiding ſeeſt thou aſſiſtance to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine thy hope in encountring, encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:131928:93"/>findeſt thou ſtrength in reſiſting, is thy reſiſting ſeconded with preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and thy preuailing accompanied with perſiſting? Art thou pitifull to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and prouident for, ſuch as are more wofull than thy ſelfe, commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in thine heart, comforting them in thy words, and helping them with thy beſt endeuors? Doſt thou yeeld ſubmiſſiue reuerence, and ſincere obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, towards thoſe who are any way aboue thee, or thou bound to? Liueſt thou humbly, peaceably, iuſtly, with all? Haſt thou a care to giue the dead their due, and is not thy loue finiſhed when their life is ended, but doſt thou mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the truth of it towards them in theirs? Of a certaine the feare of <hi>God is in thee indeed,</hi> and ſurely his ſaluation, ſauing aſſiſtance, aſſured ſafety is neere vnto thee. Thou needeſt not be afraid of the perillous time, thou ſhalt <hi>not be vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited with euill.</hi> Thou needeſt not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged for Sathans ſubtleties, thou ſhalt <hi>auoid the ſnares of death.</hi> Thou needeſt
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:131928:94"/>not feare thy finall falling, for thou ſhalt <hi>continue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 14.27.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But as for thoſe who liue as though they receiued no good from him, could haue no vſe of him, or it were vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for them to pray vnto him, who murmure in their miſeries, grudge in all their griefes, ſnarle at the ſtones which hurt them, neuer looke to the hand which throwes them, who ſeeke not to him, as men without hope deſpairing of his helpe, who adde ſinne to ſinne, <hi>drinke iniquity like water,</hi> and pull tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion to them with <hi>Cart-ropes,</hi> who obſerue no benefit or bleſſing from him, and therefore cannot hold him worthy either to be ſanctified in them or mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by them, who doubt no danger, preuent no perill, hope for no aide, haue no ſtrength to reſiſt, dare not encounter, and cannot conquer; yeeld themſelues cowardly to bee <hi>captiued at Sathans plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> and remaining without ſtability, haue their ſtates like <hi>Reubens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.</note> 
               <hi>vnſtable as water,</hi> and are themſelues like <hi>water runne
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:131928:94"/>out</hi> and ſpilt vpon the earth, vnpoſſible to be gathered vp, or at beſt vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for any neceſſary vſe in the houſe of God, who mocke at others miſeries without commiſeration, take aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage at others calamity to oppreſſe them, vſe their power, wit, wealth, to worke their iniurious wills in others wants and weakneſſe, who are ſo farre from furthering in, that they put the blinde out of his way, lay ſnares to entrap the ignorant, inſult ouer the impotent, and are faithleſſe in what is committed to them; whoſe pride, ſelfe-conceit, and arrogancy, ſtop the paſſage and damme vp the ſtreame of mutuall comfort and conference, who embrace no opinion though moſt true, ſaue their owne, though moſt falſe; who admit of no alteration in things wherein change is commendable, preferring their owne cenſure, before the graueſt ſentence, their owne diſgrace in recanting before Gods glorie, his Churches good, their owne eternall quiet, in confeſſing and diſclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:131928:95"/>what was either vnfit to bee done or thought,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prou.</hi> 31.</note> wilfully <hi>forſaking their owne mercie;</hi> who with the <hi>Salamander,</hi> loue to liue in, though they might auoid, the fire of contention and contradiction, renting the Commonwealth with ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and the Church with ſchiſmes, thinking ſuits in law to bee the ſureſt courſe to keepe what their ſoules aſſure them is anothers right, and the wiſeſt way ſtill to hold what their conſcience tels them is not truth: whoſe ingratitude forgets anothers goodneſſe, luſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects not anothers intereſt, and care is to laugh though other weepe, ſelfe pleaſing and profit making all fiſh that comes to net: All theſe are as farre from Gods feare, as they are neere to theſe faults, and as much as they are haunted with theſe hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Hags, ſo little are they frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with thoſe happineſſes which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the feare of God: For well may I ſay with the Prophet <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.1.</note> 
               <hi>The tranſgreſsion of the wicked man ſaith within
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:131928:95"/>my heart,</hi> that there <hi>is no feare of God before his eyes.</hi> My conſcience tels me that ſinne and impiety perſwade the vngodly and vnrighteous perſon that there is no God of whom he ſhould be afraid.</p>
            <p>And what is the cauſe of all impiety toward God, iniquity towards man? Is it not the want of this feare? The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet there affirmes it.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>For</hi> thence is it that <hi>he flattereth himſelfe in his owne eies, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till his iniquity be found to be hatefull.</hi> Thence is it that,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>the words of his mouth are iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and deceit,</hi> and himſelfe <hi>hath left off to be wiſe and to doe good.</hi> Thence is it that, <hi>He deuiſeth miſchiefe vpon his bed, ſetteth himſelfe in a way that is not good, and abhorreth not euill.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.10.</note> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hauing from the ſame Prophet affirmed that <hi>None is righteous, no not one,</hi> proueth it by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward defects, <hi>they had no vnderſtanding;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> by their outward failings in the generall courſe of their life,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> 
               <hi>They did not ſeeke after God, they are all gone out of the way:</hi> in the particular members of their bodies,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> 
               <hi>their throats are an open ſepulcher, their tongues de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:131928:96"/>poyſonous,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> 
               <hi>and bitter, and their feet are ſwift to ſhed bloud;</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> and then ſheweth the iuſt recompence of that their vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, that <hi>calamity and miſery is in their waies,</hi> as attending on them in all their pathes; and laſtly makes knowne the cauſe of all theſe their wants, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> and woe, to be this, that <hi>there is no feare of God before their eies.</hi> Let vs then <hi>worke out our ſaluation with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12.</note> For it is the feare of God which bridleth the fury of men, and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſteth men deepely in the fauour of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.29.42.</note>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 147.11.34.103.12, 13, 14.</note> ſeeing <hi>the eies of the Lord are ouer them, his mercy towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is as great as the heauen is aboue the earth in height, and his louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is for euer and euer vpon them that feare him.</hi> Oh let vs ponder the pureneſſe of his iuſtice, and the greatneſſe of his iudgements, that wee may attaine to a reuerence of his name aſwell as a loue of his Maieſtie, in the meditation of his mercy. Yet let not theſe two bee ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, for is he <hi>mercifully iuſt, and iuſtly mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, mixeth he clemencie with ſeuerity, and is
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:131928:96"/>not iuſtice in him ſeparated from mercie? Man muſt then render vnto him a fearing loue, and a louing feare;</hi> for, <hi>what God hath ioyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, let no man put aſunder.</hi> Now the fearing and louing of the Lord are lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked together by their, 1. Commander. 2. Cauſes. 3. Companions. 4. Subiects. 5. Acts. 6. Effects. 7. Oppoſites. 8. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions.</p>
            <p>By their Commander, for <hi>Moſes</hi> who was faithfull in all Gods houſe, and deliuered nothing vnto that people, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whom God had fixed his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aboue other nations, without his warrant, teſtifieth the Lords will in theſe words,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12.</note> 
               <hi>And now Iſrael what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to feare the Lord thy God, to walke in all his waies, and to loue him, and to ſerue the Lord thy God with all thy heart and with all thy ſoule.</hi> Where we may perceiue the two affections, <hi>Feare</hi> and <hi>Loue,</hi> equally required. So as who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer neglecteth the fearing of him, though (if they could be ſeuered) he loue him; or whoſoeuer careth not to loue,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:131928:97"/>though (if it were poſſible without the other) he ſhould feare him, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a tranſgreſſor,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ia.</hi> 2.10, 11.</note> rendring a ſingle ſeruice, where a double dutie is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſo neglecting either, he ſtands guiltie for both, becauſe he that enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the one, commanded the other, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which who ſo omitteth, goeth againſt the will of the Commander; neither of them therefore muſt bee miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, becauſe both by the ſame autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity commanded. And as they are vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their Commander, ſo in their Cauſes they are confounded, for that <hi>Mercie</hi> ſhould moue Loue none will que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but that it ſhould make vs Feare ſome may doubt, and without all perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture to affirme it would ſeeme a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxe, if the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> (a man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gods owne heart, and therefore knew what was his truth to bee deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and could not bee vnacquainted what was his will to bee reuealed, and ſurely to the Lord himſelfe durſt not haue produced the of-ſpring of his
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:131928:97"/>owne braine, a vaine conceit) turning to the Lord, had not auerred.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130 4.</note> 
               <hi>There is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with thee, therefore ſhalt thou bee feared.</hi> What is it now in the Prophets iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is the cauſe of feare? is it not mercy? This harſh-ſeeming and bitter-deemed fruit of feare muſt grow vpon that truly knowne pleaſant, and taſte-pleaſing tree of his fauour, for ſo hath the Lord or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined, as is recorded in the ſecond of the <hi>Kings,</hi> the ſeuenteenth Chapter. Feare the Lord thy God which brought thee out of the Land of Aegypt with great power, and with a ſtretched out arme. His louing deliuerance muſt bee the foundation of their feare, and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of them, the roote from which muſt ſpring their reuerencing of him: whence it is that the Pſalmiſt attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the fearing of the Lords name by the Heathen,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.15, 16.</note> and of his glory by the Kings of the earth, vnto one ſpeciall act of his mercy, the <hi>repairing of his Zion.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.11.21, 22.</note> Now <hi>Moſes</hi> though ſpeaking with the ſame Spirit, declared what the Lord
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:131928:98"/>had done for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> how he had deliuered them from their enemies, placed them in the promiſed Land, the Land of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, done for them great and terrible things which their eyes had ſeene: and further, of ſeuenty perſons had ſo mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied them, as they became as the ſtars of Heauen in multitude; and why doth hee number thus the Lords mercies? euen for this purpoſe, as hee himſelfe expreſſeth, that theſe acts of mercy might bee motiues to enflame the peoples affections to him. <hi>Therefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.11.21.22. <hi>Ioſ.</hi> 23.9.</note> In like manner doth <hi>Ioſuah</hi> his ſucceſſor, preſſe the ſame duty from the ſame ground, vpon the ſame people: For the time paſt, the Lord had driuen out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them great Nations and ſtrong, ſo fauourable hee was to them. No man was able to ſtand before them to that day, ſo mighty was he in them: For the time to come, one man of them ſhould chaſe a thouſand, ſo powerful he would be with them: all vndeniable arguments
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:131928:98"/>of his mercy towards them. But to what end doth he call to their remembrance the one, or giue them notice of the other? becauſe in the effect, the conſideration of the one is not ſo profitable as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring of the other is precious; the truth whereof is implyed by the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the charge which is added.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Take heede,</hi> careleſneſſe will proue a cora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue; take <hi>good heede,</hi> a little negligence may bee the cauſe of great and long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; <hi>therefore,</hi> you haue ſeene his preſeruations of you, haue heard his good purpoſe towards you, <hi>vnto your ſelues,</hi> ſelfe-cauſed woe is a feſtring wound, ſelfe-breeding folly is a double fault. <hi>Take good heede therefore vnto your ſelues, that yee loue the Lord your God.</hi> Is not now the Lords mercy a motiue to loue him, and is not his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour an occaſion of his feare? Surely his fauour doth inflame our affections to him, and kindle in our ſoules a feare of him: And as his mercy, ſo likewiſe his iuſtice is a cauſe of both. Iuſtice is
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:131928:99"/>indeed as oyle to continue the burning of the Lampe of feare, but it may ſeeme as water to quench the fire of loue. Seeme it may, but it doth not, in the Saints of God, for as Lime though it be naturally cold, as all ſtones are, partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pating of the earth in ſubſtance and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall properties, yet it retaines in it an hidden heat and a fiery quality,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nat. biſt. lib.</hi> 36. <hi>c.</hi> 33. <hi>Mirum, aliquid poſtquam arſerit accendi aquis. Aug. de Ciu. Dei, Quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam valde mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile accidit, quia calx ex aqua in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenditur, ex qua omnis ignis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguitur: oleo verò extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quo omnis ignis nutritur.</hi>
               </note> ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if it be once burnt (as <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith) in ſo much that it is kindled by water; ſo the loue which the Saints beare to the Lord is more inflamed by his iudgements in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on them, and through his iuſtice obſerued by them: though they may ſeeme to be an hurt, in truth they are an helpe; though they may be thought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe our loue, yet they are found to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe that loyalty which cannot be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from loue.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.175.62.164.52.</note> Seuen times a day (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) doe I praiſe thee becauſe of thy righteous iudgements: though then the thinking of his iuſtice may be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined to daunt our courage, yet the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring of his iudgements is the
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:131928:99"/>cauſe of comfort; <hi>I remembred thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of old, O Lord</hi> (ſaith that anointed of the Lord) <hi>and haue beene comforted:</hi> though the appearance of them quench our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in them,
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> yet the experience of them ſtirres vp our deſire vnto them. <hi>My ſoule breaketh for the longing that it hath vnto thy iudgements at all times,</hi> And leſt we ſhould conceiue it onely of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> of his iuſtice in his word (as may be collected ſometimes in that Pſalme to be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued as verſes 137, 138.)
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> hee addeth the reaſon of that his deſire, <hi>Thou haſt deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the proud,</hi> (and by thy puniſhments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that) they <hi>are curſed which doe erre from thy Commandements,</hi> ſo that there it muſt needes bee vnderſtood of the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of them in his wrath vpon the wicked, or in his wiſdome vpon the godly, which ſorts of people may by them ſee his equity, which will cauſe them to loue him, and bee ſenſible of their owne miſery, which will moue them in affection to flye vnto him;
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> yet the ſame Prophet in the ſame Pſalme te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:131928:100"/>to the Lord himſelfe, that <hi>his fleſh trembled for feare of him, and he was afraid of his iudgements;</hi> and by his actions as well as words declared, that hee conceiued Gods iuſtice to be a iuſt cauſe why eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhould feare him; for though before, in all ioy, and with ſuch ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity as teſtified the delight of his heart, he was bringing into his owne City the Arke,
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.9.</note> yet as ſoone as <hi>Vzzah</hi> was <hi>ſtrucke dead,</hi> he durſt not aduenture to bring it any further, but deſiſted, though it were the teſtimony of the Lords preſence: thus both iuſtice and mercy are the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, either of them, of both loue and feare, and as the <hi>Lord</hi> doth adorne the heart with his feare, ſo <hi>hee</hi> doth enrich the ſoule with his loue; as the <hi>Word</hi> by his promiſes drawes our affections to him, ſo the ſame <hi>Word</hi> by his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings cauſeth vs to ſtand in awe of him: we may ſee them both then growing vpon the ſame ground, and vnited in their cauſes. No leſſe in their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
            <pb n="187" facs="tcp:131928:100"/>
            <p>For as <hi>ſeruing</hi> of the Lord is required where the fearing of him is enioyned,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12.</note> ſo the <hi>louing</hi> of him is preſcribed where his <hi>ſeruice</hi> is commanded. <hi>Feare</hi> muſt haue with it <hi>walking in his waies,</hi> and <hi>walking in his waies</hi> may not bee without <hi>loue:</hi> as there is required <hi>the keeping of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements</hi> by them that loue him, ſo there is a <hi>delighting in his Commandements</hi> by them that feare him: Where as true ſociety and ſociable vnity for the greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of mutuall comfort, will ſeeke to ſettle and ſolace themſelues in the ſame (and that a ſelected place) ſo theſe graces will be lodged in the ſame (and that a peculiar) Cabinet: For both theſe pearles are not found together in euery Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, both theſe Gems are not digged together out of euery ground, both theſe flowers are not growing together in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Garden; for in the hearts onely of Gods children are they both harboured, in the ſoules onely of Gods Saints are they both nouriſhed, in the affections onely of the Lords elect are they both
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:131928:101"/>planted <hi>Caine, Eſau</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> had a kind of <hi>feare,</hi> but falſe, for they wanted <hi>loue;</hi> the <hi>Phariſies</hi> and <hi>Simon Magus</hi> had a kind of <hi>loue,</hi> but counterfeit, for they wanted <hi>feare;</hi> if the former had had loue, they had deſired, and deſiring ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Gods grace: if the other had had feare, they would haue neglected their owne reſpect, and haue ſought for and aimed at Gods glory; they all wanted both true feare and loue, for of the one ſort the hearts were enuious, and they deſpaired, which <hi>loue</hi> entertaines not; of the other, the Spirits were vaine-glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and they preſumed, which <hi>feare</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits not. Neither let it ſeeme ſtrange that <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>loue,</hi> whoſe very names im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a great diuerſity in their natures, ſhould with an vnanime conſent lodge in the ſame breaſt, ſeeing the bitter Rue and the ſweet Fig-tree draw moiſture in the ſame ground, the ſolitary <hi>Turtle</hi> and the ſociable <hi>Doue</hi> muſt bee offered in the ſame ſacrifice. <hi>Feare</hi> that ſeemeth to bee bitter in the obiects (threatnings and
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:131928:101"/>iudgements) and ſolitary in the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (trembling and being aſhamed to appeare in preſence) and <hi>Loue</hi> which is ſweet in its proper obiects (promiſes and goodneſſe) and pleaſing in the effects (hope and boldneſſe to approach the Throne of grace) flowing from one heart as the Lords <hi>Altar,</hi> are as incenſe in his acceptation. For they act one and the ſelfe ſame thing, though diuers waies, in the ſoule of man.</p>
            <p>For let it be granted, which cannot be denied, that <hi>Loue vniteth, Dauid</hi> will affirme that <hi>Feare knitteth</hi> the heart vnto the Lord. Let it bee auerred,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.</hi> 86.11.</note> that <hi>Loue</hi> willingly <hi>heareth, Zephany</hi> dare aſſure any who ſhall make ſcruple of it, that <hi>Feare</hi> is not altogether ſlacke to <hi>receiue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.7.</note> 
               <hi>inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi> Will <hi>Loue</hi> prie into the ſecrets of the party loued, to be partaker of them? <hi>Feare</hi> is as obſeruant of, and as loth to want, thoſe myſteries which the party feared hath reſerued for it. <hi>Loue woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth</hi> the ſoule when it ſees Gods fauour, and <hi>Feare woundeth</hi> the ſpirit in behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:131928:102"/>his diſpleaſure. <hi>Loue inflameth</hi> the deſire to doe what it knowes is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and <hi>Feare ſets on fire the affections,</hi> to conſume what it conceiues to be abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable. <hi>Loue humbleth</hi> a man ſeeing the greatneſſe of the beloueds mercy, and <hi>Feare caſteth downe</hi> the pride of minde, in viewing the glory of the feareds Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, together with the number of its owne offences. <hi>Loue</hi> as the <hi>fiery piller,</hi> guides in the night of aduerſity: &amp; <hi>Feare</hi> as the <hi>Cloud,</hi> giues directions to our paths in the day of proſperity. <hi>Loue miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gateth</hi> the ſorrow which feare had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and <hi>Feare qualifieth</hi> that ioy which <hi>Loue</hi> produced. <hi>Feare</hi> as Rew tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <hi>Loues</hi> Figge-like ſweetneſſe, leſt it ſhould paſſe the golden Meane, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vnpleaſing, and <hi>Loue</hi> as the Figge-tree, moderateth <hi>Feares</hi> Rew-like bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that it exceed not its equall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and be made vnprofitable.</p>
            <p>As for their effects;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note> is Gods <hi>mercy ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thouſands of them that loue him?</hi> it is no leſſe from <hi>generation to generation on them
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 1.50.</note>
                  <pb n="191" facs="tcp:131928:102"/>that feare him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.16.</note> Is <hi>Feare</hi> made partaker of his bleſſings? <hi>Loue</hi> communicateth of his bounty.
<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> Is <hi>Life</hi> the promiſed recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of <hi>Loue?</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> 
               <hi>Death</hi> ſhall not bee the allotted reward of feare. Doth <hi>Loue</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due the heart with abundance of celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all grace?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 33.6.</note> Feare is a <hi>treaſure</hi> to enrich the whole man with all good. Doth <hi>Feare</hi> make man acceptable vnto God?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 10.30.</note> 
               <hi>Loue</hi> makes him at leaſt as gratious with him. Doth <hi>Loue</hi> prouide for poſterity? <hi>Feare</hi> leaues not the ſucceſſion in calamity: if any either temporall, ſpirituall, or eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall good attend vpon the one, it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe becomes a follower of the other, ſo like they are in their effects. There is as mutuall a conſpiring betweene them in their generall and particular <hi>oppoſites.</hi> For as diſpleaſing of the Lord is auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Loue,</hi> ſo offending of him is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred by <hi>Feare.</hi> Will not <hi>Loue</hi> cleaue to Heatheniſh, either workes or worſhip?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſ.</hi> 23.11, 12.16. 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 17.35, 36</note> 
               <hi>Feare</hi> will fly from heatheniſh, both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy and Idolatrie. <hi>Feare</hi> hateth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption as the Serpent the Aſhe tree,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:131928:103"/>and <hi>Loue</hi> ſhunneth raſhneſſe as the Scor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion <hi>Aconitum. Ioſiah</hi> durſt not diſobey when hee heard what was threatned, nor <hi>Dauid</hi> preſume when hee ſaw what was inflicted,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 13.12.</note> for they were withheld by <hi>Feare.</hi> The Diſciples would not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt their Maſter,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 8.24, 25.</note> till there was no hope of ſafety, becauſe they were bridled by <hi>Loue,</hi> as the Church would not ſuffer any to awaken her Spouſe in ſigne of her affection.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>Feare</hi> participating of the nature of the Lion which is terrible, loatheth a putrified denne, and loue which communicateth in property with the Doue which is louing, ſhunneth a foule cottage: ſuch is their ſympathie in reſpect of their oppoſites.</p>
            <p>Now for their <hi>conditions.</hi> Wee cannot but ſee how neerely they are in them conioyned, if we obſerue their mutuall, 1. Excellency. 2. Dignity. 3. Validitie. Their <hi>Excellency</hi> appeareth to bee the ſame, in that God hath indifferently made knowne himſelfe (as it were by name) by either of them. Wee iuſtly
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:131928:103"/>make account of the name, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if it bee giuen of purpoſe, not by peraduenture, for the better finding out of the nature of that whereunto it is giuen, and if Embaſſadors receiue their reſpect according to the Maieſtie of their Maſter whom they preſent, how ſhall we not eſteeme of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of both <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Feare,</hi> ſeeing the Lord himſelfe who did all things (gaue euen names) in <hi>number, weight and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> in his ſacred Word, where euery one may and ought to reade, his pleaſure will haue vs to conceiue himſelfe ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times when <hi>Feare</hi> is mentioned, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſomtimes when <hi>Loue</hi> is repeated. <hi>Iacob</hi> cals him the <hi>Feare</hi> of his father <hi>Iſack,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> which lay on Chriſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, that beloued Diſciple, cals him <hi>Loue.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.</note> Can a Chriſtian heare himſelfe called in the Scriptures by the name of King, and not conceiue of what repute he is of through Chriſt in the eies of God? Can any heare the names of <hi>Feare</hi> and <hi>Loue,</hi> to be transferred to the Lord himſelfe, and not confeſſe the <hi>excellency,</hi>
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:131928:104"/>the mutuall <hi>excellency</hi> of either? For he bearing their name, they muſt needes partake of his nature. Their mutuall <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> is as manifeſt, for theſe two compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all what man can performe to God, or which God requireth of man. For our Sauiour for the accompliſhing of the Commandements, calls for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Loue,</hi> whereupon <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Loue is the fulfilling of the law;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.2.</note> and <hi>Salomon,</hi> who had too much experience of falling from God, hauing teſtified his diſtaſt of his too much taſted vanities, affirmeth that <hi>the end of all</hi> which any can perſwade, aduiſe, or preſſe, is to <hi>Feare,</hi> and to <hi>keepe the Commandements,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.</note> and he giueth the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for that is <hi>the whole duty of man.</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our bleſſed Sauiour and his elect veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, extolling <hi>Loue,</hi> include feare, or they contradict <hi>Salomon:</hi> and <hi>Salomon</hi> in his <hi>Feare,</hi> and <hi>keeping the Commandements,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Loue,</hi> or hee gainſaied our Sauiour and his Apoſtle. But they all ſpeaking by the ſame ſpirit, affirme the ſame thing. For nothing but theſe two (which giue life and luſtre vnto euery duty beſides,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:131928:104"/>and therefore ioyned ſometimes with one, ſometimes with another) are aboue other, yet indifferently required; And <hi>now Iſrael what doth the Lord thy God require of thee, but to feare and loue him?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12.</note> Whereby we may obſerue theſe to be all are expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by him, accepted of him. Shewing in his expectation, what are to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to him by vs as our duties, intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in his acceptation, how greatly he delights in theſe graces, and in both ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting what is in his eſtimation, <hi>the dignity</hi> of them: either of which indeed were of no worth, if they were not both <hi>permanent.</hi> But now the <hi>Validity</hi> of either is ſuch,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.</note> that as <hi>much water cannot quench loue, nor the flouds drowne it,</hi> ſo many trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles cannot ouerturne <hi>Feare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 15.15.</note> nor cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity conquer it.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.7.</note> 
               <hi>Loue</hi> is not to bee drawne by force, for it is <hi>ſtrong as death; Feare</hi> not to be vnited by flattery, for it is ſuſpicious of danger.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.20.</note> 
               <hi>Loue</hi> is not to be perſwaded from God by any power, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fully taſted of his fauour: <hi>Feare</hi> is not to bee enforced from the Lord by any terror,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.8.</note> hauing drunke deepely of
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:131928:105"/>the cup of his power.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.17, 18. <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.40.</note> 
               <hi>That heart</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Lord <hi>hath put his feare, departs not from him;</hi> and that ſoule which hath yeelded to his <hi>loue,</hi> will not leaue him. <hi>Feare</hi> looking on the promiſes, and the power of him that made them, groweth vp to the perfection of full holineſſe, till it be indued with it;
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1.</note> and <hi>loue</hi> wanting full fruition of prepared ioyes, aſpireth to perfect happineſſe till it be inueſted in it. Neither of them ceaſing before they be made partakers of their expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Thus then they agree in their Commander, Cauſes, Subiects, Acts, Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, Oppoſites, and Conditions, of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Excellency, Dignity, and Validity. And therefore aſwell the one as other, to bee harboured in euery Chriſtians heart.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.18.</note> But <hi>perfect loue driueth out feare.</hi> It is true, one poiſon preuaileth againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. ſer.</hi> 13. <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erb. Apoſt. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor ſervus eſt, Charitas libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra eſt.</hi>
               </note> two contraries cannot ſubſiſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one ſubiect in the ſame meaſure of contrariety, and looke how much ſoeuer is the power of a <hi>ſonne-like loue,</hi> ſo much leſſe is the ſtrength of a <hi>ſlauiſh feare;</hi> where <hi>loue</hi> hath apprehended the firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.17.</note>
               <pb n="199" facs="tcp:131928:105"/>of Gods fauour, there is no <hi>doubting</hi> of his helpe in the time of danger, no want of <hi>boldneſſe in the day of iudgement.</hi> That <hi>loue</hi> then which the Lord accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth as <hi>perfect,</hi> caſteth out that <hi>Feare</hi> which he reiecteth as <hi>faithleſſe.</hi> That <hi>loue</hi> which ſtriueth in expectation of prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red pleaſures to <hi>perfection,</hi> baniſheth that <hi>feare</hi> which laboureth in apprehenſion of allotted iudgements with <hi>painfulneſſe,</hi> as plunged in the gulfe of deſpaire. To <hi>feare</hi> him then, not as a Iudge that will <hi>condemne,</hi> but as a Iudge that will <hi>diſcharge</hi> vs, is that <hi>feare</hi> which <hi>loue</hi> is ſo farre from driuing out, that it <hi>liketh</hi> it, liking it <hi>loueth</hi> it, louing it cannot <hi>liue without it:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.11.</note> 
               <hi>Serue the Lord with feare, and reioyce before him with trembling,</hi> is the exhortation of <hi>Dauid;</hi> where <hi>loue</hi> is not harboured, ioy cannot be expreſſed; as then there muſt not be <hi>ſeruing</hi> without <hi>feare,</hi> ſo neither muſt there be <hi>trembling</hi> without <hi>loue,</hi> for there is no ſeruice acceptable which wanteth <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence,</hi> nor reuerence commendable which is rendred without <hi>affection:</hi> And as one well ſaith,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hugo de S.V. de inſtit. nouit. c.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Reuerentia ſine amore ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:131928:106"/>ſeruilis, &amp; amor ſine reuerentia puerilis iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicari debet. Reuerence</hi> without <hi>loue</hi> is too ſlauiſh, and <hi>loue</hi> without <hi>reuerence</hi> is too childiſh: if there be <hi>loue</hi> and not <hi>feare,</hi> it anſwereth not the Lords worth; if there be <hi>feare</hi> and not <hi>loue,</hi> it argueth the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our vnwillingneſſe:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.7.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> had exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted others, hee reſolueth and promiſeth that he himſelfe will practiſe, <hi>I will come</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>into thine houſe, O Lord, in the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy mercy, and in thy feare will I wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip toward thy holy Temple. Mercy</hi> moueth him out of <hi>loue</hi> to come, and <hi>feare</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him in <hi>reuerence</hi> to continue; <hi>loue</hi> draweth him to the duty, and feare dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteth him in his deuotion. Such is the efficacy and dignity, end and vſe of them where they are vnited, that this lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>feare</hi> and fearing <hi>loue</hi> is the way by which <hi>God</hi> walketh <hi>vnto man,</hi> and the Ladder by which man climeth vnto God. They humble God, but exalt man, bring God downe below, and lift man on high,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.23.</note> for that heart where <hi>loue</hi> is har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured will hee <hi>inhabit,</hi> and that ſpirit
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:131928:106"/>which in feare of his diſpleaſure is <hi>bruiſed</hi> will he <hi>viſit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 57.15.</note> For by them are the fetters of ſin looſed from our feet, the manicles of iniquity taken from our hands, the caule of hardneſſe remoued from our hearts, and the ſome of calumnious blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy &amp; blaſphemous calumny wiped from our mouthes, for <hi>Loue</hi> ſoftneth as the Goats bloud the adamantine, <hi>Feare</hi> breaketh as the hammer the ſtony, heart; <hi>Loue</hi> looſeth the ſpirits as the hot Sunne the frozen Fountaine, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out flouds of teares; <hi>Feare</hi> maketh man, as the fire the hardeſt mettals, plia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to euery truth; <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Feare</hi> vnited in one ſoule, diſſolue there the curſed workes of the Deuill, and kindle the fire of true deuotion, and therefore not to be ſeuered, becauſe the <hi>Lord is both iuſt and mercifull, mercifull and iuſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fulg. l.</hi> 1. <hi>de rem. pecc. ad Fabiol. manſ.</hi> 23.</note> Let all men therefore entertaine theſe deere and inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable aſſociates. Let the <hi>wicked</hi> learne to <hi>feare and loue the Lord</hi> for his <hi>iuſtice</hi> and <hi>mercy,</hi> that being conuerted they may miſſe of that puniſhment which his <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> hath threatned, and receiue that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:131928:107"/>which his <hi>mercy</hi> hath promiſed. Let the <hi>good loue and feare him</hi> for his <hi>mercy,</hi> and <hi>iuſtice,</hi> that being preuented by his <hi>mercy,</hi> through loue of it they may continue in good workes, and in <hi>Feare</hi> of his <hi>iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> keepe themſelues carefully from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full waies. Let the <hi>wicked</hi> thinke of his <hi>mercy,</hi> leſt too much ſwallowing of his <hi>iuſtice</hi> they forget his fauour and be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by ſinne through deſperation. Let the <hi>good feare</hi> his <hi>iuſtce,</hi> leſt too much ſwilling his <hi>mercy</hi> they neglect his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and bee ſeduced by Satan to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption. Let all men both <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>feare</hi> him, <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>loue</hi> him, that his <hi>Angels may pitch their tents round about them,</hi> his Spirit in all their waies direct them, himſelfe take them, while they remaine here, vnto his protection, and hereafter in his due time tranſlate them to an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall Crowne of glory, which hee giue vnto all vs, and euery one that are his, for his ſake who hath ſo dearely bought vs, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:131928:107"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:131928:108"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:131928:108" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
